[Music]
Tyrael the things that guys docket
obviously the midterm is this Wednesday
in class I posted the the URL to the
study guide on online in Piazza and then
at the end of this class we'll have a
review of the midterm go over the topics
at a high level
alright and then we'll cover everything
you need to like you know what you need
to bring and show up and do okay and
then project number two checkpoint 2 is
due this Friday at midnight quick show
of hands who here is done
checkpoint 2 done the entire thing we
got one okay don't be so meek he's done
okay who here has not started on
checkpoint two I saw a hand okay it's
okay all right fine okay again this is
why I may do on Friday and I realize you
guys have midterms in other classes so
that's why we push it off them okay so
the other thing I want to go over real
quickly is some administrative stuff so
these are the department basically got
back to me and they want me to curse
less in this class so I'm gonna try to
do that I can't always promise it but we
uh there's some other things going on
that I think you're actually kind of
interesting kind of relevant so first is
that I found that there's a Chinese
version of YouTube that's basically
copying all our our our videos right so
good for them okay and then the other
thing is too because you know not that I
post this on youtube just for just
pickles right I do it because I wouldn't
you guys have access to to everything we
get a lot of email or these I get email
from people complaining about the course
so this is I'm like the list here hold
up sorry I don't use their names every
okay sorry
so this is this is Jael in Seattle he
basically says that we're all full he
doesn't like us and he give you back
your money
this is CM in in San Jose
he says I'm a joker I have I smell the
guy of diarrhea whatever like so it is
true I did have a medical problem where
had bad hygiene a year before but I'm on
medicine now so this I I think this is
old news what he got but occasionally
you get actually useful emails right so
this is actually somebody Erik darling
he's from a major sequel server debate
consultant company and he watched the
lecture from last class or enjoins and
he said they said that I said something
that was actually incorrect he's
absolutely right so when I was talking
about joins I was saying that oh well
building hash tables like building an X
on the fly and as far as they know no
database system actually would build a
B+ tree on the fly only they're only
gonna build hash tables to do hash joins
and he actually says actually this is
incorrect the sequel server has a
feature called index pooling where they
will build a B+ tree on the fly just for
the query that you're actually doing and
SIBO light does sort of something
something similar may say this is
actually a really cool website where you
can dump out the secret server.xml of a
query plan a quick sell of a query plan
from sequel server and you upload it to
the website and it gives you a nice
visualization of this alright so we
thank Eric for correcting us there's
much more comments in YouTube for other
things we've gotten correct and
incorrect but I'm not gonna read all of
them ok so again I take any feedback you
guys can provide because I wanna make
the course better year after year so
don't don't sum any bad email something
good ones okay alright so today's topic
is on query optimization so this is
actually one of my favorite lectures
we're only you know it's a my favorite
topics in in databases and part of the
reason why it's one my favorite topics
is because I'm actually really bad at it
or this is the one area I will fully
admit that I of all of database systems
that I don't fully understand and maybe
to the extent that I would want to and
for whatever reason that makes me like
it even more and so to understand what
we're gonna do in this in this lecture
we had to go back and understand what
sequel actually is right so so sequel is
a is a query that someone sends to the
database systems and that says here's
the answer I want you to compute right
it's done in a declarative way so
there's nothing about what it's in the
sequel that says you know run this joint
algorithm run you know run you're
sorting this way it just says give me
this answer and it's up for the database
system to figure out the the best way to
actually do it so we saw this right when
we talked about joins and sorting I said
there's a bunch of different algorithms
you could actually use right in case of
joins you can do nested loop you could
do hash joints you can do sort merge and
they have different algorithmic
properties and trade-offs and under
different scenarios you may actually
want to run one algorithm versus another
but when you write a sequel query to
join two tables you don't say join table
at you know take table a and do a hash
joint on it or table B you just say I
want to do a join are you just saying
what the answer you want to be and so
it's up for the database system in
particular the query optimizer was
referring to focused on today to figure
out what the best album to use for your
particular query based on what it knows
about the data and so we saw that there
was a big difference in performance when
we talked about joins right we said that
if you do this no stupidest thing with
the nested loop join then you can take
your query take one point three hours
but if you're do a hash join then you're
down to less than a second so as we go
along we'll see or I'll sort of mention
that in various cases that this is the
one thing that really separates the
commercial database systems from the
open source ones right this is what
makes commercial data part of the reason
what makes commercial databases so so
expensive right because it's gonna be
this query optimizer because they're
gonna have an entire floor at these
database companies with much you know
dudes with PhD he's trying to figure out
how to squeak the best performance you
can get out of a database system through
its query optimizer right and there's
been studies that show in that they
actually the Microsoft query optimizer
was actually the best one out there the
nuts say the open source ones are bad in
particular Postgres it just in terms of
level sophistication that the kind of
things that can support the commercial
ones are much better
so the original idea of a query
optimizer goes back you know as many
things do in databases goes back to IBM
system are so remember I said that in
the beginning of the semester system R
was this internal project by IBM
research down in San Jose where they
took Ted Cod's paper on the relational
model and said here let's actually try
to build a system that actually
implements this right and so Ted Cod
never actually proposed sequel he later
proposed his own declared language
called alpha but nobody ever actually
implemented so IBM came up with part of
the system our project they came out
with with the earliest version of sequel
so given again it's a sequel to the code
of language they then need to be be able
to take that query and actually generate
a execution plan that was that was that
was efficient so at the time in the
1970s people were arguing that a
database management system could never
produce a query plan as efficient and
what a human can write right so
therefore it was you know sequel is a
dumb idea or having quick knowledge was
a dumb idea because that's never gonna
be as good as what a human can do right
you can sort of think of this is the
same argument of having the time to
1970s about see the programming language
they argued that no human would ever be
able to write algorithms and write
applications in C and then have a query
optimizer sorry a compiler generate
execution machine code for your program
that would be as efficient what a human
could write and assembly of course
nobody writes assembling it anymore
right everyone relies on compilers so
it's the same argument but just in a
different context right for sequel
people argue that be better off people
writing codasyl or whatever they wanted
to do their joins themselves rather than
having a compiler figure things out so
as we go along through today we'll see
that there's been many cases where the
so the high-level concepts of what the
system our guys came up with back in the
1970s we're actually still used today
but this idea about cost based query
optimizer is sort of a key one the
algorithms may be slightly different and
some of the assumptions that IBM made in
the 1970s may not be so valid anymore
but again the core concept is exactly
the same and the woman that came up with
this at IBM Pat cell
I said system are they got like seven
people with PhDs in one room said and
they said go build a database system and
every person sort of carved off their
own piece so this one woman Pat Salinger
carved off the query optimizer part she
was at IBM for a long time she was that
sales horse and just retired and I had a
former student his class was working
with Pat Salinger took all my classes
knew about the seller generic query
optimizer and didn't put one didn't put
one one together that the woman she was
working with us the same woman we would
study in this class so she's still
around today and she has a lot done a
lot of great work in this area so for
query optimization we're basically going
to have two approaches the first it's
going to be using heuristics or rules
written by us as humans to do some
massaging of the query plan to apply
some some obvious options or fix some
obvious inefficiencies and apply some
some simple optimizations right so the
idea would be you have your query shows
up and you do some line a rewriting of
the syntax tree you never operate
directly on the sequel and the idea is
that we there are certain things we know
we're always going to want to do to make
the query run faster so we just have
rules to go ahead and just do them
before we go into the second phase we're
actually now we do a cost-based search
so the second phase is where we're gonna
say all right we know how to think need
to figure out other things about our
query plan and I don't have rules that I
can apply to say here's exactly what
you're always going to want to do
because it's the the choices you'll make
will depend on what your data looks like
and I'll explain what that means in a
second and so we do a search to find
what it would be what is an optimal
query plan for our query right the idea
here is that we're gonna have this cost
model say given to potential query plans
for a single sequel statement which one
is actually better in terms of
performance so just to understand the
sort of pipeline it is in a real system
at a high level it would look like this
so your application Smith so sequel
query and the first step is that it
always goes through a sequel parser
alright and the sequel parse is gonna
then convert it into an abstract syntax
tree alright it breaks up the tokens and
you know the Select statements of where
clauses
and getting gives you this tree but
inside this tree now all we have are
just the strings or the names of the
things that were in the sequel statement
like select star from table foo right in
our syntax tree at this point we just
have you know the string foo we don't
know anything about it we don't know
that it corresponds to a particular
table so in the binder phase we go do
lookups in our internal system catalog
about the database it's the metadata
about the data what tables do I have
what columns do I have what index do I
have things like that and it's gonna map
the the names that are in the strings
that are in an abstract syntax tree to
internal identifiers I just think of
like it's a you know internal ID number
for a particular table and then we feed
now this annotated abstracts index tree
to this query rewriter the thing I
showed in the first step in the previous
slide where we can apply some rules that
we that we know we're always gonna want
to apply to our query plan to to to make
it go faster make the query run faster
and I'll show examples of what that is
as we go along so not every single
database system has this right you can
still just have a query optimizer
without this initial step but this is
actually very common in most systems and
then in the last step when we take the
output of the the rewriter and feed this
into our cost based query optimizer I
can think of this is doing like an
optimization search looking at different
query plans getting information about
the what the tables look like from the
catalog and then using some kind of
internal cost model to say here's the
but here's the potential runtime cost of
exiting this query plan the idea is you
want you want to be able to examine as
many query plans as possible within
either you know sort of some kind of
budget like in terms of time or the
number thermal plans you investigate and
then whatever which one is the best one
you've ever seen that's the one you'll
spit out as the final query plan for
this query so as we see as we go along
the the the optimizer is actually not
always going to pick the globally
optimal plan right because that would
actually be really expensive so it's
going to try to use
methods to prune down the search base so
that can generate a good enough plan
within a regional amount of time so I
say this in the beginning I'll say it
again this is actually really hard to do
so the joke in in databases is that if
you try to do query optimization and you
fail the fallback plan is you go work on
rocket science right because query
optimization is harder than building
rockets this is again this is the
hardest part about building any database
minute system this is part of the reason
why a lot of the no sequel guys didn't
end up using sequel in the first place
because if you have sequel then you need
some kind of query optimizer this is
hard to do it's hard to get right
there's all these different corner cases
a seed will expand the do you have
nested queries and other things this is
really hard to get right the one thing I
will say also too is that if you're good
at this if you really like query
optimization you will have no problem
getting a job so I have friends and
various database companies and they
email me asking for you know what
students are looking to graduate looking
for jobs they have one thing I always
get is like yeah we want database
students but do we really want anybody
that knows query optimization so if
you're good at this you can have no
problem getting paid a lot of money
because when you think about it you know
what like 22 year old kid coming out of
grad school or undergraduate program has
experience in query optimizers right
it's like crusty old guys from the 1990s
and they don't really want to you know
move maybe to it like a startup and
things like that so this is the one
thing that that david's companies are
really really interested in so as we go
along i imagine and talked about various
problems we have to solve in our query
optimizer a lot even be saying in the
back of your mind
Oh can't machine learning solve this you
know can't can I use AI to make this all
go away make it much easier yes but no
there has been some early research in
the last one or two years of looking at
using machine learning to to improve the
accuracy or improve the the quality of
the query plans that the optimizer
generates but as far as they know no you
know this is still early work and no
major gated system actually supports
this persico's has a genetic algorithm
based query optimizer that if you try to
do joins with more than 13 queries then
it falls back to that to the genetic
algorithm but
what will describe today is basically
how most most systems actually do this
on a sale so two for the apply machine
learning to krauser is actually
something we're interested at here at
CMU we do have students looking looking
into this now but it's still very early
I love query optimization so much again
I'm really bad at it and it just makes
me want to do it even more so I get
better at it so in the advanced class
you know previous year to already spend
two weeks on query optimizers and cost
models but if you take the advanced
class this spring I probably add another
week to go over you know more complex
scenarios right we build our own query
optimizer from scratch here at CMU and
we just very used in making it better
okay so for today's class we're going to
talk about we're gonna have sort of four
parts talking about different query
optimization steps we have to do so
we'll talk about how to do relational
algebra Linc's to do the rewriting that
we talked about before then we'll do
plan cost estimation how do you actually
say for a potential query plan how many
tuples how much disk am I gonna have to
read to make it make it execute it then
we'll talk about how to do enumeration
or searching for different query plans
and sort of build up a query plan
holistically and look at the cost at
each step and then we'll talk about how
to do the two to two ways you can do
optimization with nested queries and
we'll finish up talking about again the
the remaining times going over the the
midterm at a high level okay okay
awesome
all right so we didn't really mention
this in the beginning of the semester
when we talk about relational algebra
but the the high-level idea is that what
we're gonna try to do this in this
rewriting step is a query is going to
show up will generate the relational
algebra from from from the abstract
syntax tree and then because of rules we
know about the relational algebra to
determine you know to permute the
expression and still have them be
equivalent with the with each other we
can apply certain rules to generate a
more optimal query plan that way and
this has nothing to do with what my data
looks like these are just general rules
that we can apply for every single query
because it's always going to be the the
almost always going to be the right
thing to do and so the idea here is that
this can be done efficiently we just
have some
some sort of a rule engine that can
check patterns in our in our index tree
to see whether we have matches and if we
have matches then we can easily apply
apply those rules and modify the tree so
give me example what I mean I'll go say
we have a simple join on the student
table in the enroll table right and the
so we have our join predicate on the
student ID in the student table in the
role table and then we have an
additional predicate on the on the on
the enrolled grade and so the if you
just take the the sequel and I must
generate exactly the the relational
algebra put this you would end up with a
query plan that looks like this right
but what's one obvious thing we can do
to optimize this query yes exactly check
the predicate except to check the
predicate before we join
so we have our filter on grade-a here
but we're doing that after we do the
join so again always try to think in
terms of extreme numbers to see you know
how something would actually affect
performance
so say we have a billion records in the
enroll table and only two people got an
A in the entire university right so that
means that when we feed this data into
this joint operator we would do a join
on one billion two books from the enroll
table then we have 1 billion two was
come as the output which is fed into now
the filter operator but then we're gonna
go now check we're you know grade equals
a but that's only gonna match to two
pools so we did a join on the billion
tuples where all but two of them is just
wasted work because it's not gonna get
produced as the output to to the user so
a simple optimization we can apply here
is called projection push sorry
predicate push down where we just moved
down the the filter operator to be below
the join all right this is sort of like
a no-brainer I'm always going to want to
do this so when you look at now the
relation out row for these two different
query plans week again we know that
they're equivalent right so in this case
here we do the join first then do the
filter in this case here we do the
filter first then do the join right
there's rules relational algebra that
would tell us that these two query plans
equivalent so the query optimizer can do
rewriting of this query plan and apply
this change without worrying about we
still guaranteeing that's could produce
the correct result
all these optimizations don't work if
you produce query plans that are you
know gonna give you the wrong result
that doesn't help us so there's some
sort of standard rules you can do for
selections right obviously perform the
filters as early as possible you can
reorder the predicates so that you apply
the more selective ones first right so
say I had something like we're you know
great equals a and you know age above 30
if there was fewer students that had the
age above 30 then students ahead with an
A then I want to apply that that age
filter first so even though the grade
may appear first in the sequel statement
I'm free to reorder the expression any
way that I want and maybe apply that
that the most selective predicate first
so I throw away as much more you know
much useless data as possible before I
go into the next stages and then you can
also do you know break up complex
predicate and you push down so you don't
always have to have the you know if they
have a where clause and bunch of
conjunctions put a bunch of predicates
you don't have to take all those
predicates and push them down in the
query plan right you may want to select
some of them right and this may be
because some predicates are more
expensive to compute than others right
say one predicate might be computing a
hash of some value so maybe you don't
want to do that down below for you
before join maybe you want to do it
after join so you're only you know
wasting the computational resources for
things you know are going to match or at
least at least get to the joint there's
other optimizations you can do as well
again relying on the transitive
properties of boolean logic so here we
have a complex predicate like x equals y
and y equals 3 right but we would know
that in this case here if y equals 3
then X always has to equal 3 so we can
rewrite this expression to be like this
so now maybe we could break up the
predicate and do the filters on the x
table or maybe filter on the on the y
tuples do them separately
yes so this question is if you're doing
squat choice can does it make it does it
make sense to always move all the
predicates down close to the skin as
possible and never break it up right so
in the end definitely the open source
guys I think they always push things
down right there could be an example
where it could be an example where a
predicate would be expensive to execute
I can say like predators can be anything
right you can actually you can write a
user-defined function that makes it an
invocation to an outside system to
compute whatever you want right and say
that call cost you money right I'm not
saying any system would actually do this
but like you could have you could
recognize that all right this is weak
expensive to do so I don't want to do it
before my join I'm gonna do it after my
join because it might be a join filter
that's gonna filter out even more right
so you may have a billion tuples going
to the join but the joint may only
produce two things rather then rather
than having for a billion tuples and
booked that offense of predicate you do
it after the join for that for that for
example you have to be yes but my UDF
exam owes my UDF ones a bad example
because UDF's are treated as black boxes
that the Davises and doesn't know
anything about that right but that would
be the guys maybe the difference I'm
trying to make here is that it's see
when I say cost I think in terms of how
it's related to the actual database
itself the computational cost would be
is sort of independent in some ways to
what how many tuples you have like the
computational cost and booking one
predicate it's the number of times he
would execute that predicate for the
neutral room or tuples that's something
will you on the cost model separately
all right for projections
this is mostly can be true for row
stores and for distributed databases but
the idea is that you want to maybe you
want to push projections down as early
as possible so that you reduce the size
of the tuples that you're copying from
one Operator to the next let me talk
about the materialization model the
iterator model and the vectorization
model you're copying data that the
operator generates from one Operator to
the next pushing it up the tree and so
if your tuples are really wide and
you're you're copying the entire thing
all the way up then you're wasting a lot
of space for four columns you know
you're never actually gonna need later
on all right so you go back to our
example here again at the top of the
query plan we're doing a projection on
the student name and the in the course
ID so say that the student enroll tables
were really wide we had a lot of columns
a lot of attributes so it might actually
be better for us to move down the
projection before the joins so we're
only passing in the student ID in the
name and this one only passes up the
student ID in the course ID because
that's the only thing you need to do for
the join here and the idea is that from
one operator to the next we're copying
less data again in distributed databases
this matters a lot because if you have
to then send data from one node to the
next then you're going over that network
and that becomes very expensive to do
again an ik column store we said this
wasn't gonna be an issue because the
column store can be smart and recognize
that oh I only need to read data from
this one column so I'm not gonna stitch
the entire tuple back together then pass
it up from one Operator the next it just
passes the bare minimum data you need
but if you're in a row store and as
you're scanning this you're basically
getting everything all right so let's
look some other examples how to do
optimization without without a cost
model so this actually comes from a
really great blog article that came out
last year from a DBA where he basically
mow a bunch of different types of
optimizations you can apply for queries
again without having a cost ball and he
looked at how the different database
systems actually would support them and
whether they can recognize the
inefficiencies in the string and what
what's in the sequel query and try to
rewrite them to be
more efficient or better right so the
first class class optimizations we can
apply or recognizing that when we have
impossible or unnecessary predicates
right so select star from table where
one equals zero right obviously one can
never equal zero
so it doesn't make sense for us to
actually scan through every single tuple
and apply this predicate because it's
always gonna be false and note people is
never gonna match right so some systems
can recognize in this case here that
this you know this will never value it
to true so it just skips the scan
entirely it'll give you back a result
set right because you because if I
execute a query I always want back I
always want a result set right this is
not an error right this is there's no
reason this is still valid sequel but it
can just be smart and say well I'm
actually I don't need to run anything
here's your empty result another example
would be like this right select star
from a where 1 equals 1 obviously in our
where Clause 1 will always equal 1 so
the optimization we can apply here is
just throw away this predicate entirely
rewrite the expression to not include
this and then now we're just gonna
basically take the this do you know a
complete spectral scan on the table and
just dump everything in our in our
output and the thing we're trying to
avoid is again not have to check whether
one equals one for every single tuple in
our table because that's that's useless
so it can just rewrite this like this
and these are equivalent another
optimization would apply is join
eliminations so say we have a query the
self join right from a as a 1 join on a
as a to where a data ID a 1 ID equals a
2 ID and up above I'm showing the schema
and ID is the primary key so this is a
unique column so there'll be a
one-to-one match between the ID in an a1
with a2 because the exact same table so
the the David Simmons can recognize that
this join is actually useless right and
just remove this entirely and rewrite it
like this right this is still equivalent
yet I don't need a cost model to figure
this out I can just look at my catalog
understand that the column ton join onto
this table is the primary key are you
we column so therefore I just throw away
throw away the join throw away the where
clause all right another one is to
remove useless projections so here we're
doing select star from a on as a one and
then we're going to have a in our where
clause we have an exist
function that says with the inside of
this we're now we're doing a join
between the outer a a and the inner a so
a1 is the outer a2 is the inner right
why is this useless what does the exists
exists to yes exactly
it checks whether at least one row
return is returned and then evaluates to
true so this is basically saying for for
my tuple do I exist in this enlighten my
own table it is always true so this is
so this is useless and we can further
rewrite this be like that all right the
last one is to do merging the predicates
so in this case here we're doing a
select star from a and then we have in
our where clause we have two between
between predicates so between just
there's a shorthand way to say like
greater than and less than or less than
and greater than right so this is saying
we're val is is between 1 and 100 or bow
between 50 and 150 right
what can we rewrite this to its a
disjunction 1 to 150 right because
because these two ranges are overlapping
so again instead of looking at every
single predicate every single to point
and evaluating this predicate I can just
rewrite it to be like this and that now
that's much more much more efficient to
to execute all right again so there's a
bunch of these different rules that the
very standard systems support and can
have some are better than others
and we can try this out real quickly to
see what kind of things they support
students
so this is gonna be a sample database
from the blog article I highly recommend
you guys check it out the link is in the
the slides and so he had a he provides a
sample table or sample database that's
based on that doesn't work that's based
on a like a video store
so there's films and people like rentals
right so it's sort of a sample schema
and it's awesome about is they provide
it in for my sequel Postgres sequel
server oracle sequel like they provide
it for a bunch of different data systems
so we can try it for all these systems
at the same same scheme in the same
query alright so this one we have
Postgres we have my sequel I got the
Linux version of sequel server 2017
running them on my machine and then we
also have sequel light so let's start
with the first one in Postgres right
select star from actor where 1 equals 0
and here I'm doing explain analyze
because I actually want to execute the
query and see what Postgres actually
does right and so again this is this is
an impossible where clause so we know
that it shouldn't actually look at any
data in this case here as far as I can
tell it actually it looks like it didn't
actually run at law right because it
says Rose equals 0 so it's a one-time
filter that's always valid to false so
it knows that there's this thing will
never value it to true so it just
doesn't execute anything and this gives
you back an empty result let's try this
in a my sequel so my sequel doesn't have
explain analyze like Postgres does and
they're explained is not as good as as
Postgres expressed great actually gives
you the the query plan tree which is
actually really nice so my sequel gives
you this is 5,7 it gives you some
metadata and you see here it says some
powerful where clause so it didn't
actually run anything it just recognized
that this thing I never bad wait to true
so it knows is doesn't actually need to
scan anything on the table
we'll try this in instakill light I
don't think see Colette gives you a good
explanation yeah it doesn't really tell
you anything
I just says idea scan on table if I
remove the query plan clause from that
it gives you a bunch of this I won't I
won't explain this now but basically the
way single light actually excuse queries
is that they convert the query planets
opcodes think of like the byte code in
the JVM and then they have an
interpreter for it right which is kind
of interesting so that's what all that's
what all these op codes are and then
this is sort of roughly showing and what
put they're actually doing so as far as
I can tell it doesn't doesn't look it
doesn't look like they're able to
recognize that it's an impossible query
alright the last one was a sequel server
so the sequel server as far as I know
does not have does not have explained
you have to do this like show show plan
thing right and tells you that it's
turned on and then we can now run a
query and doesn't actually run the query
it just tells you that I did it and here
again there's no there's no there's no
metadata to say whether it recognized
was impossible erases constant scan and
I suppose that would evaluate the false
and knows it doesn't actually do the
scan at all alright let's try the the
range query one say we go back to
Postgres so Postgres 2 is is not able to
recognize that these predicates we
merged and they rewrote the between
clause to be greater than equal to and
less than equal to but it still looks
like they're still going to perform the
the you know the scan for both of those
predicates right the book both of those
ranges we go to to my sequel no matching
row and cons table eyes alright sorry I
let me go back to this I'm you clean it
so actually I'm not doing the same range
gain I had before I'm actually doing an
impossible range
I've between 1 and 2 and between
199 and 200 right so these are disjoint
sets for doing a conjunction on them
disjoint ranges so it should never get
never actually match so my sequel
actually does the right thing and it's
able to recognize that this is actually
says here no matching brillouin
constable so maybe actually did apply it
but in case of in Postgres again it
didn't recognize that these are
impossible ranges and still did the scan
on it let's try this in sequel light
again as far as I can tell it's it's
still doing the it's still doing the
range scan on the on the query it
doesn't recognize that these things are
disjoint and the last one would be where
are we there we go
try this in in sequel server again
doesn't tell you anything tells you
constant there's a way to turn on the
more verbose like XML query query plan
of the sequel server but you need it you
need a viewer for that which I don't
have right it's just we just at the
terminal alright so the last one I want
to do is the projection pruning so this
is BEC this is Becker Postgres so here
we're going to do a select statement and
all we have is just exist where select
is 1/0
right so again exists returns true
whether there's at least one thing that
will match inside of inside of the
whatever you have inside of it right so
I could do something like this select
one right something will match because
there's a tuple with with one attribute
the values one and then the outer select
will say alright is there anything
inside that inner select if yes then
return true right so that's what we
expect like this so the question is
whether Postgres can recognize that no
matter what value I put in for the
inside this inner part here right no
matter what's in there there's it's
always going to be a tuple so therefore
always gonna evaluate to true so
therefore it doesn't need to even
execute whatever that projection is in
there so I can try to compute you know
the millionth digit of pi it's still
going to evaluate to true so you want to
see whether post cuts can recognize this
and not actually execute anything and
the way we can test this is by doing it
invalid division right 1 divided by 0 so
if it actually executes so that that
predicate then it'll throw an error if
it doesn't then I'll just say true raise
your hand if you think it'll execute it
1 2 yeah 5% he thinks it's smart enough
to know not to do it
no one's wanna think that bad few people
ok it can do it
alright so we can try this in in sequel
light alright comes back is true let's
try this in my sequel comes back goes
true question though is I'm actually not
sure if my seat will actually execute
this right so again if I do this and I
used like that it'll it gives you back
no but then it gives you a warning and
then for for my sequel you have to do
this command and then it says division
by 0 right if I try this in in Postgres
it should actually just throw an arrow
alright division by 0 so I'm not sure
whether my sequels actually executing
this or not but we tried another case
where we can try to give it an invalid
power and that that comes out to be true
too so that I think I think it's doing
the right thing right in that case it
throws an error I could try to do that
whereas like the divide by zero doesn't
throw an error again so the main
takeaway from these these are all rules
that are gonna that the system can use
before you even get to the call space
search because it knows
these are some optimizations that can
apply because they're always almost
always gonna be the right thing to do
okay okay so for for its single table
queries you know this crap addition is
pretty straightforward for joins as with
the tricky one this is this is the one
where we're having those problems
all right and the the part of the reason
we're gonna have problems is that we can
apply both commutativity and
associativity rules for for our joins
and reorder them in any any way that we
want and we're still always could
produce the correct result right if I
went to join R and s that's equivalent
to joining s with our right it's still
going to always computes the correct
result or if I want to join our SMT I
could join R and s first and then join
that output with it with T or I could
join SMT first and join that with our
all these are equivalent all these are
valid and so we hit but they're gonna
have different performance
characteristics but we solved this when
we talked about joint algorithms you
always want to put the smaller table as
the the outer table so now how are you
gonna pick which one to pick you know
which one which to join first and which
one should be the inverse of the outer
so what makes it so hard is that the
total number different combinations we
could have is 4 to the n right you know
it's a big number when it has a special
name right so it's called a Catalan
number all right and so then because
there's so many different choices we
could have for our join orders and that
we're not gonna be able to to compare
every single one we need a way to prune
the search space right cuz they're doing
the results a search is just gonna be
way too slow so we're gonna hold off on
this for now we'll talk about how you're
going to estimate whether one joint is
better than another and then we'll see
how we can then figure out what the
joint ordering should be so the in the
the the call space search search
optimization the idea is that for a
particular query plan so the ideas can
take a query you generate the syntax
tree and then now say there's joint you
want to figure out what order you should
actually join your tables and so you're
gonna try a bunch of accommodations of
those different joint orderings and
way to figure out which one is better
than another so you're gonna use the
cost model to be able to do this
estimation all right and so it's the
cost model is going to generate a number
that's internal to the database system
meaning it's not really gonna be a you
know tied to wall clock times I can say
you know miss Cory's gonna say ten
milliseconds that squares gonna take 100
milliseconds but is this internal metric
that it uses just to compare whether one
query plan is better than another but
it's gonna be derived from a bunch of
different information that it can
collect about your data and about your
hardware right so try to think think
about like all right well this joint
algorithms can take this many CPU cycles
and I'm gonna have this many cache
misses so you know I'll wait that'd be
more than the other one I know how many
blocks me have to read from disk or how
much data at the center of the network
how much memory I'm gonna use so this
cost must be a combination of all these
things and again the commercial guys are
way more sophisticated than the
open-source guys and then it's gonna use
that again to determine whether one is
better than another so the way you need
to figure out how much resources the
query is gonna use is based on the
statistics and information you're gonna
drive about the underlying database
right you want to know how many tuples I
have for the table from table a and on
joining with table B how why do those
there's those tuples how fast the disk
that they're stored on all this
information you need to maintain then in
order to figure out what the estimate
how much things gonna cost to execute it
so every single database system that has
a query optimizer has to have you know
it's gonna have a cost based query
optimizer has to maintain these internal
statistics that it's gonna collect about
the data so if your data is read-only
then this is not a big deal because you
just sort of scan over at once and then
we try to collect what much data as you
can
shouldn't say it's not a big deal but
it's it's it's less challenging than if
you're in a dynamic environment where
your data is always getting updated so
the way database systems manage this is
that they typically have a background
sort of stats collector I think that's
what Postgres calls it that's going to
scan through your data every so often or
whenever you invoke it
and derive some information about what
the distribution and when the values
look like and then maintain that in the
internal system catalog that it can then
be used by the optimizers cost model to
make estimations so again the different
data systems have different rules about
when you actually collect this data or
it can be like if my if I update 10% of
the tuples in my table then I'll fire
off the the background stats collector
if I delete all of it and load it back
in I'll run it run run them again you
can also mainly invoke these things
right the Postgres in sequel light and a
lot of other systems have the analyze
keyword that just tells you to again
scan through a table and and collect
this information single server it's
updates of physics and then db2 is
runstats so there's nothing in the
sequel standard to say do this most of
the times you see analyze right but it
Oracle my sequel have to be different
when analyze table so what are these
tags what do these look like well the
highest level the most easiest thing is
obviously the the number of tuples I
have my table right if I want to know
how many tuples I'm gonna feed into my
joint algorithm after after do my scan
you need to know that and you can simply
derive that based on the number of
tuples but then we need to know
something about the values inside those
tuples for all the different columns so
the most basic thing we can maintain is
the the number of distinct values for a
given attribute in our table so we'll
define this as a function VAR whether
this just says again the number distinct
values I have for actually a in table R
and then for this we can now derive
things we actually can use to estimate
the cost of executing query plans so I
and this is me the first thing we're
going to derive is called a select it
little selection cardinality and this is
just gonna be the the average number of
records that have a particular value in
an attribute for that for the table
all right so you think of something
really simple like you know if I have 10
to 'pls and I have a single attribute
and there's 10 unique values for that
attribute then the selection cardinality
is is 1 because before I became in
predicate you know if I'm gonna say does
something Eagle something I'm gonna get
back one tuple
and so this is just taking the number to
lose I have and dividing it by the
number of distinct values for it for a
particular attribute so what's one
obvious limitation about this we're
taking the number tools they have and
dividing it by the number of distinct
values it assumes yes are go ahead yes
so he says you need to maintain a set
for the distinct values I thinking more
high-level than that exactly yes so a
big assumption we're gonna make here and
this is goes back to the system art is
is that we're assuming we have uniform
distribution of values to make this work
right but we know in reality it's not
the case at all but I just think of like
just in CMU right seeing you has ten
colleges right the school computer
science is one of them there's way more
students in SES than what the other
schools are right music or something
like that right so if we assume our data
is uniform then every college if seem
you will have the same number of
students but that's not the case at all
I think of like zip codes there's way
more people that live in York City and
those zip codes then live in Wyoming and
Montana so real data does not fit this
pattern at all but to simplify our
explanation of what our cost cost
estimations are doing we're just going
to make that assumption right again we
go through examples of how it doesn't
work out all right so if we assume our
data is uniform then it's really easy
for us to estimate the number of tuples
we'd have for own unique keys when we do
a quality predacons right so say i've
select star from people where ID equals
one two three ID is the primary key so
the selection cardinality for this is
obviously one right because only one two
book could ever have a particular value
for that for the ID field
so therefore this predicate does
something equal something has to always
return one things get tricky though is
when you start having other predicates
range queries inequalities an inequality
easy
range queries and other things like that
and now complex are conjunctions and
disjunctions as well right so now how do
I estimate things like value greater
than 100 or age equals 30 n status
equals something all right so now we're
gonna introduce to you know handle these
we can use a new concept called the
selectivity by predicate and it's just
think of this is like the fraction of
the two pools that will qualify forgiven
forgiven predicate for like one one
component of a where clause
and so the we'll have a bunch of
formulas we can use based on the
statistics we'll collect to estimate the
selectivity but and they're based on
what kind of operation you're doing a
quality range predicate and then
conjunction disjunction
so we'll go through a bunch of these
examples again we're gonna assume that
our data's uniform so that the math
works out in most cases but in reality
again this is not always the case and in
commercial systems don't always make
this assumption all right so we already
showed how to do predicates where it's
you know something
eatle something at a quality predicate
on a unique key let's look an example
when a key may not actually be unique so
for assuming this we're gonna have the
table people and they'll be an attribute
age and the number distinct values for
this this age attribute will be 5 0
through 4 and then the number two boys
we have in this table are just me 5 so
if you want to determine whether
something equals something you know does
at radik all constant again assuming
that this is this is non unique then our
our the math works out to produce the
selectivity it's just to take the
selection cardinality with this
predicate and divided by the number of
unique values right so say we're in this
example here we're age equals two we can
represent our data as a histogram right
so for each age the number of tuples we
have that people at that age and again
assuming in this case we're only have
five two pools so each of these bars
equal one so the first thing we would
get the number of distinct values along
the the bottom the x-axis is just
and then the selection a cardinality of
age equals 2 which is 1 therefore the
selectivity of this predicate is just 1
over v 1 v right simple example and this
works out if we look at range queries
like where age is greater than equal to
2 right you can use this formula where
you you take the max value subtracted by
the the value trying to do a look-up on
the constant and divide that by the the
max value minus the min value and then
that produces roughly the right roughly
the estimate but it's not not exactly
accurate so what I think about is we
want to know what what the selectivity
is for this range here we're greater
than equals to 2 so we had the min and
the max and we can we can do that
particular that and then we produce a
1/2 because we're taking the the ceiling
of this again it's not entirely accurate
because in this case here it's actually
the correct the correct selectivity
would be 3/5 the formula comes out to be
1/2 so this is a good example where the
math is not exactly right there's some
corner cases like this where you don't
get it perfect if it was instead of
greater than equals equals it was just
greater than then it would just be from
this over and then it would be 2/5 right
and again but if we use that simple
formula then it doesn't work out for
negation queries this is actually really
easy to do right age doesn't equal to 2
well we already know how to compute the
selectivity of h equals 2 so we just
take the selection cardinality of H
equals 2 and just negate it so that we
get these other bounds here and then now
our selectivity is just 1 minus 1/5 so
we get 4/5 there so it should be kind of
clear at this point that these the
selectivity looks a lot like
probabilities right it's like what's the
probability that my predicate is gonna
match a particular tuple in in in my
input and so if we assume that they're
probabilities which is not again it's
not always exactly
not entirely accurate but if we assume
that they're actually probabilities then
we can take all the rules that we
learned from you know probability 101 in
our intro math courses and apply them to
our to our predicates here so say again
you have if you have a conjunction right
you're even an Clause in this case here
I or H equals two and name like some
some wildcard
then I can just take the the predicate
take the the selectivity of age equals
two and multiply that by the predicate
or the selectivity of the predicate name
equals wildcard and then that produces
my my my total selectivity for the
entire predicate right so think of this
p1 is this range here are the tuples
level match the first predicate p2 is
the range of the tuples that match the
second predicate so the area in which
the both credits will evaluate to true
is just the intersection of this part
here and we get that by multiplying the
two probabilities together so the big
assumption now another big assumption
we're making here is that the predicates
are independent of each other and
therefore you can multiply them together
that's not always the case either right
think again think of real real datasets
I could have a I could have a table
people their dresses and I have zip code
and city alright and for a particular
zip code so our particular city it's
always gonna be in in one and only one
zip code so if I assume they're
independent then if I say you know we're
zip code equals one five two one seven
and City Eagles Pittsburgh if I take
those two predicates and multiply them
together I'm gonna be sort of under
estimating the number of triples that
will match me because it's really if I'm
in if I'm in zip code one five two one
seven I'm sorry if I'm in City
Pittsburgh that I have to be in one five
two one seven so therefore they're not
independent cuz they're correlated with
each other so this math doesn't actually
work out in real data sets there's a
bunch of rent ways the commercial guys
can handle this but this is again
another big fallacy or another big
assumption that was made in the 1970s
that still carries through to gay
because this makes things easier to
reason about
disjunctions it's it's the opposite of
conjunction right again we want to take
all the predicates that either match
this part or this part and it's just the
entire area and then this is the math up
here that takes fix the that makes that
assumption that they're independent and
adds them together in the back yes the
typo we're sorry on this yes yes I'll
fix that thank you that's a good
correction thank you and you didn't
curse okay all right so where's this all
leading to so we want to now estimate
the result set size of joins this is the
thing that all the the optimizers are
gonna get wrong and this matters the
most right the idea is getting given two
tuples I'm sorry two tables are ns and
some some some where clause of how
you're going to join them we want to
estimate the number of tuples we're
gonna produce as output right if we're
just joining two tables this doesn't
matter that much because we really care
about the number two was getting fed
into the query plan because we can
decide which ones the universe of the
outer but now if you're doing multi way
joins or multiple joins in your inner
query then it matters a lot to know how
much tuple how many tuples are getting
output about you join because you would
then you want to figure out who should
be at the bottom and who should you know
who should be the universe at the outer
that way because now you're joining on
derive tables or joined tables rather
than the base tables themselves so in
the sake of time I'm gonna skip the the
math here but the basic idea is again
it's just we're estimating the number
two was getting fed in from from from
one table and the other table and then
we have some simple formula to estimate
the number two plus that will match on
this but as I said in in the in most
systems they get this horribly wrong
actually in all systems they get this
horribly wrong because the problem is
that if you get the if you get the
selectivity slightly incorrect for the
joins at the bottom the query plan then
as you go up big that
that error increases right because now
you're throwing errors on errors on
errors and it gets worse and worse and
worse so again we'll cover this in the
advanced class when I'm time to do it
here but sequel server actually does the
best job of figuring this thing out and
most systems underestimate it and you
would get under estimations if you make
the assumptions like uniform data
distribution or or independent
probabilities all right so this is fine
so now we have some basic formulas you
can use to estimate the selectivity of
predicates right and we can use that to
figure out how many two boys are getting
fed into an operator and how many tuples
are gonna it's gonna output but how are
we actually deriving those that's
selectivity you're like what is the
underlying information we have we have
so the the way the David Simmons going
to maintain information about what your
data actually looks like is through
histograms right the the basic idea is
that for every you know every unique
value or a range of values
how many tuples actually have had that
particular value right so in the case
here along the x-axis we have the number
distinct values for an attribute and
then the y-axis is the number of
occurrences again for this particular
example I'm assuming our data is uniform
so there's actually nothing I really
really need to store here I disagree to
store one value say all tuples have you
know all values for every value in my
table for this pickle attribute there
will be five tuples that match it the
problem is real data looks something
like this right it's the the
distribution is all over the map
it's oftentimes it's as if theand
distribution right so let up our law
curve but for our purposes here this is
fine and so now the problem is for a
particular attribute particular value in
that attribute we would have to maintain
a giant map that says for this value
here's the count for right and this you
think about how you actually would
implement this if you just for every
single distinct value to maintain this
mapping it would be huge right for a
column where you have say unique numbers
if you have a 32-bit number and that's
unique throughout the entire column in
your histogram map
you would have another 32-bit integer
just keep track of the number of tuples
I have that value and it's always gonna
be one right always or some small urban
so you base actually doubling the size
of every single column because you have
to store this additional information so
way to to fix this is to use buckets all
right so the idea here is that for every
for every three values in our in our in
our histogram we're just gonna bucket
them together count the number of tuples
that they have are the number of values
that there are number of currencies that
they have and then for every single
bucket we just have keep track of that
the min and Max and then the count for
that I say we're condensing down the the
the the information so that it's more
manageable size of course what's the
obvious problem with this right
say it again sorry he says the problem
is get the maintain these numbers so
we're not so much yes you have to
maintain the numbers we talked about
that before the you run analyze or you
think you have this background process
actually does this I'm thinking more in
terms of the accuracy of this
information right he says they could be
largely different numbers right so we're
sort of blindly bucketing together
contiguous values in our range list and
that may actually not be the right thing
to do because there may be because since
we're taking essentially just computing
the average now you could be some of the
really low value a really high value and
we're missing those outliers so way to
fix this is use what are called equity
with histograms and for this one I'll
use quantiles and the idea is that for
every as we go along for every single
bucket
the counts always gonna be the same it's
just we're gonna have a variable number
of elements or values in that bucket so
in the fruit and the these three buckets
here bucket one bucket - bucket for the
count will be 12 so we try to add as
many values as we can to get that you
know they get that count be 12 this this
middle guy here is sort of an outlier he
has a larger bucket size or bucket width
and the counts only 9 all right so then
we end up something like
so the number elements or the count per
bucket will be the same roughly but the
number of values distinct values in a
bucket can can vary another option also
to do is to maintain a separate data
structure for heavy hitters like if I
know I have one value that has way way
different number of occurrences in our
column than all other values I'll
maintain that as a separate data
structure because I wouldn't have really
accurate predictions for that one so
sort of combination of these things to
make this all work so again these
histograms are essentially you're
compressing the data about the metadata
about about your data and we have to do
this to make it more manageable but
again we sacrifice accuracy well it's
another approach we can you and use a
set of maintaining histograms
to estimate you know the number of
tuples for particular value I try this
every year and no one actually can guess
it
sampling right so the the idea is that
rather than checking histogram to say
you know how many what's my selectivity
for a predicate for this particular
value I'll just collect some sample data
from the underlying table and then this
run a complete scrunch will scan on that
sample and that helps me I can use that
to figure out my selectivity of my
predicates right so let's say I have a
query here almost like all the people
with age greater than 50 say I have a
billion tuples all right so what I'll do
is for that query I'll just sample every
other or something like that it's
usually much smaller small amount store
this in a sort of temporary table that's
only accessible to the query optimizer
so you're treating this like a regular
table but it says you can't run queries
against it right so using all the same
you know table storage and heap storage
stuff we talked about before and then
when my query shows up and I say all
right what's the selectivity of age
greater than hippie I just do a
sequential scan on my on my sample to
figure out what it is all right I don't
look at any histograms and the idea is
that if I have obviously a a
reasonably large enough sample size then
that would be an accurate reflection of
what the underlying table looks like yes
one's fine
yes question is why is called equal to F
where's the bucket or not call it I
could with um good question so this
would be echoed with records you always
take two three elements let me
double-check that what's that wait
echoed what echo death all right is that
what it's called
all right we'll do it but double check
this okay all right so we have like
eight minutes left I'm gonna I'm gonna
pause this now we'll come back to this
after the midterm because I want to get
to the review but just to understand
we're at we've able to we have as we
have a way to derive information about
the tables we go around queries on we
have some formulas we can use to to
estimate the selectivity of predicates
and then the next phase we want to
figure out how we actually can use that
information to help us guide our search
to find a better query plan so let's
pause on this from now because we only
have ten minutes left and we'll go to
the midterm review okay
so again the midterm is this Wednesday
in this class at the same time right
everyone needs to take the midterm no
one no one is excluded right you should
bring your CMU ID because I need to use
class of hundred people so I need to be
able check who's who you need to bring a
calculator to help you dude you know the
basic formulas that we've talked about
and then you're allowed to bring a
one-page double-sided of handwritten
notes with anything anything you want
any format things like that so that
means you can't take the slide and sort
of compress them down and try to fit
them onto a page everything that's
behind written
and I do that because I think you get
more out of it that way and so just copy
and pasting alright so this is my list
of what not to bring and it gets longer
every single year so a few years ago
someone brought a live animal don't do
that right and then last year somebody
brought their wet mangy from their dorm
right and I was like what the hell's
going on right so they brought it and
wasn't this room but it's another room
they brought it to dry while they were
taking the exam and it smelled kind of
funky because it was like sitting in the
washing machine
overnight so you do not bring your wet
laundry all right if you have something
crazy you want to bring email me
beforehand and let me know and just
figure out whether it's okay because
otherwise I gotta you know add you to
the list here right so no snakes no dogs
no what laundry okay so the midterm will
cover everything up and tune up to and
including the the joint lecture lecture
twelve you're gonna be closed book you
get get one one sheet of handwritten
notes double-sided and then if you need
any special accommodations please email
me now so we can make sure those things
happen and then this is the link to what
I post on Piazza for the midterm study
guide it has the list of chapters that
are covered in the textbook that are
relevant to the exam and then a link to
go find the solutions to any I think the
odd problems if you want to expand the
things that you're looking at and a link
also to the the practice exam that we
gave out from a few years ago okay all
right so what's gonna be on the exam so
obviously the relational model the you
know the focus on integrity constraints
what does that mean in relational
algebra we didn't cover any relational
calculus so don't worry about that if
it's in the textbook right again I'm not
gonna ask you to write more complex
things just understand what these basic
operators actually do for sequel again
everyone should already know Siegel from
the first homework assignment and so
I'll ask sort of high-level questions
about the more complex things that we
covered I join zagraz to common table
expressions these are the things that
you guys did in the first homework
assignment I won't cover window
functions because you guys weren't
actually able to do that in sequel Lite
but again think about it we're not gonna
ask you to write really complex queries
because you have to write it you know on
paper we're not gonna
in testan see whether that key works so
we're more we're more interested in the
high-level concepts about what these
queries are actually doing and then this
comes up every year and then for a
common table expressions they would
include recursive expressions so then we
get into the actual implementation of
the database system so we covered things
like buffer management policies so you
know LRU mru clock how to handle ntral
flooding we talked about how to actually
represent the database on disk or heap
files or link lists page directories
things like that then we talked about
when you bring her at what section side
the page right we talked about slotted
page layout we talked a log structured
layout we talked about what the tuple
how to represent data and tuples all
right what's in the header things like
that then we talked about hash hash
tables so again there's two high level
approaches to hashing there's the static
hash tables like linear probing the
robin hood cuckoo hashing then there was
it dynamic hash tables extendable
hashing chain hashing and linear hashing
and again we're not going to ask you to
you know write code it's more about the
high-level concepts of what these
different hashing schemes actually do I
don't care about hash functions it's
more about the hash table itself and
then we also want to care about how
these data structures relate to or
compare with B plus trees right when
would you want to use the hash table
versus a B plus tree then we talked
about order preserving tree indexes then
we spent a lot of time talking about B
plus trees you guys are building this
for your first second assignment so
insertions deletions splits merges how
they differ with a b-tree or B link tree
at a high level and how it actually do
latch grabbing Blackledge coupling
including doing leaf node scans and any
basic optimization is like you know
delayed or delayed parent splitting and
then we talked about a little bit about
radix trees and skip lists I realized
this is not in the textbooks we're not
going to complicated things it's more
about a high-level what are the what are
the high-level design differences
between these different data structures
versus versus B plus trees
then we talked about sorting and
particularly focused on the external
merge sort which I've got two variants
of it right there was the two way merge
sort and then there was the the the K
way or the general-purpose external
merge sort and the basic questions are
going to be things like as you're seeing
in the the current homework assignment
right if I have a data file that looks
like this and I had this new many
buffers how many passes a trauma need to
do or how quickly can I sort it all
right query processing we talked about
different processing models iterator or
volcano versus vectorize Arce
materialized again what are the design
trade-offs and performance
characteristics of these different
approaches what kind of workloads would
you want to use one versus another right
and then we talked about joint
algorithms nested loop joins hash joins
and sort merge joins again what are the
performance implications of them if I
give you a data set with this how many
this many tuples in many pages you have
this many blocks how many you know how
many disk i/o is it gonna take you to do
the join all right so this is it so any
any questions everyone feels very fairly
confident Stata basis where I should be
fun awesome ok that's it then we're done
so next class after the exam will cover
parallel query extent will finish off in
the query opposition stuff then let's
talk about doing parallel query
execution again the idea here is that
everything we've focused on so far has
been sort of running single thread to do
your joining or whatever you want to do
now you want to say in a modern database
system that has multiple cores how does
the execution change if yeah if you can
run parallel threads and be just to say
this is not the same thing as
distributing execution that'll be
covered later on this is like a single
box how can I run things in parallel
okay all right all of us ours now you
know if you have any questions and those
questions about the practice exam on
Piazza will take care of that later
today alright guys see ya
yes it's the SD cricket IDE mess I make
a mess unless I can do it like a gia are
you with the G to the e to the T comes
dope I play the game with no rules
homies on the trucks are y'all looking
for my room with the bus a cap on the
road with a blow and faint eyes when I
party by the 12-pack case of a bar
six-pack for the egg gets the real I
treat put your drinking proper 12 ow
they say build nation but what's a nice
is straight so it really don't matter