[Music]
maybe on the Jill's
today is the second part electric you're
doing on tree indexes is real quick go
through what's on the schedule for you
guys coming up right I want you know
that project one is due on Wednesday
who here is done project one already
it's got a 1% rage man
alright small spattering who here has
not started at all in the back really
you know what kudos are admitting this
right cuz I asked every year and I was
like no right nice nice
ok so homework 2 again it was really
dude this Wednesday has been bumped out
to be due on on Friday at midnight and
then project 2 will be announced on
Wednesday in class this week and then
what we're doing is for project two
because everyone can last year assume
project tools can be as easy as project
one and maybe that I you heard me say
it's easy that's why she hasn't started
yet more new checkpoints in the first
week and a half you'll have to submit
something on grade scope to get further
sort of the first half the project done
and then the final grade will be due a
week a nap after that so sort again it's
a it's a checkpoint halfway through to
make sure you least have started and
look at the projects so that way you're
not trying to build a B+ tree in 24
hours which is gonna be a bad bad time
for everyone okay so any questions about
project one at a high level okay okay
so again post any technical questions
about great scope or other aspects of
the coding assignment on Piazza and then
the TAS will be able to answer it for
you alright so today's agenda we're
going to focus on sort of sort of split
into three parts so in beginning I want
to talk about other ways you can use
table indexes in a database system that
go beyond what we've mostly been
assuming or talked about so far and then
I want to talk about two alternative
tree based data structures for for
building a table index as an examples of
other options beyond a P plus tree the
spoiler would be to be plus tree is
still superior in some cases to these
other two
so but I still think it's useful for you
guys be aware of them and understand how
they work and then we'll finish all
talking about at a high level another
example of a non exactly tree based data
structure but an example of another kind
of index you can have in your database
system called an inverted indexes and we
see how we do full-text search on these
ok alright so there the there was
somebody had a question at the end of
last class and about how the database
system was was actually building these
indexes and I don't mean so much like
most the process actually taking the
keys and populating index more about are
there cases where the Davises would
automatically build indexes in order in
order to do certain things and answer is
yes so most database systems will
automatically create indexes to enforce
different kind of constraints so
integrity constraints and possibly also
referential constraints so integrity
trait would be like a primary key or
unique constraint right so like if I
call create table like this and I define
a primary key and a unique key then
implicitly what this means is that the
database system is going to centrally in
a book these sequel commands to create
these two indexes for you right so for
the primary key it'll automatically
create the unique index on on the ID and
then for the second value the bar chart
it'll create a unique index on that
because it has unique key word and when
you think about it this makes sense
right because what's how else would the
database database system actually
enforce these constraints right how's
gonna know that nobody else tries to
insert the key with the same primary key
or to point the same primary key the as
always in data systems the fallback
option is just to do a sequential scan
and look at every single tuple to see
whether you have the same key already
but of course now if I we have 1 billion
tuples in our in our table every single
time we insert insert something at the
scan through 1 billion tuples so we can
build it we can build an index to do
this very quickly for us and doesn't
matter whether it's a B+ tree or a hash
table right the same idea at a high
level the same thing right we want
something we can check very quickly to
see whether there's a conflict and if
yes then we know we should not insert it
if no then it's okay for us to insert it
so this is mr. du integrity constraints
I also thought it would do the same
thing for referential entrants or
foreign key constraints right so let's
say I have a second table here bar and
this ID field has a foreign key
reference on the value 1 in the food
table so at this point here the the
value 1 in the food table is not unique
so there isn't an index already built
for it and I thought actually the data
system would automatically recognize oh
I'm having a foreign key reference from
this table to that table I don't already
have an index over here I thought it
would actually they were all gonna go
ahead and create one automatically for
you turns out I try this my sequel in
Postgres they don't actually do this at
all actually they won't even let you
create the foreign key unless you're
pointing something in the parent table
that already has a unique index for you
again it's the reason why you need index
is the same reason we need it for the
primary key and unique constraint right
every single time you wouldn't insert
something into bar the foreign key says
whatever you're in storing for value
sorry for the ID field since it has a
foreign key preference on the food table
there must be a key that exists in the
food table that matches what I'm trying
to insert in this table so again you
would use an index to make sure you
didn't have to scan everything to find a
match so turns out in Postgres in my
sequel they will throw an error my
sequel actor will throw a silent error
for this one
Postgres will do it correctly at least
my sequel five point seven and say you
can't create this foreign key reference
because you need to have a unique index
on on the food table for the thing
you're pointing to but there's nothing
about the relational model that says
that this is the case I think this is
strictly an implementation issue maybe
has to do something and the sequel
standard says something about this but I
think at a high level there's no no
reason this is they have to require this
this is why I thought they were gonna
automatically create one so the only way
to really make this work is actually if
you change the the food table to make
the the value the first value attribute
be unique and again that automatically
doesn't index and then this thing can
now point to it right so this is sort of
clear right
anytime you define a constraint when you
create the table at automatic
create the index for you now I can also
go back and create the indexes manually
but you can do it directly when you call
create table alright so another
interesting way to expand what we have
we can use indexes are called partial
indexes and the idea here is that so far
we've assumed that anytime I call create
index it's going to scan through every
single tuple in that table and build an
index for the entire table but there may
be some cases where you don't actually
want an index on the entire table you
want a subset at the table so this is
what it's called partial indexes so the
way you make this work is that in the
where you add a where clause to the
Krait index statement and you add some
additional predicates to say only index
the tuples on the base table in this
case foo where C equals mooting or some
expression has to evaluate to true so
inside of this index we're only going to
index a and B but implicitly there's
some metadata we're maintaining to know
that for this particular index there are
only B entries where C equals wu-tang
from the food table and so the advantage
of this is now if you come along with a
query like this let me say we're a
equals 1 2 3 and C equals whoo tang so
now we for for a the a attribute we can
get that from the index but we would
even afford them we would check to see
whether this the C predicate matches
what we've declared as the the partial
index where clause for this index if it
doesn't match that we can't use the
index if it does match then we know that
it's safe for us to go inside of it and
then extract out the new apply to a
predicate to get the keys that we want
so this is actually a very common setup
in a lot of applications when you maybe
want to partition the index based on
things like date so you have like say
you split up your you know the list of
orders for your business you can have
one index for each individual month
right and then this reduces the size of
the index and it makes maintaining them
much easier because they're more compact
if you have a lot of queries that only
focus on a single month then you don't
have to maybe swap in you know a you
know giant index into your buffer pool
that has a bunch of keys that don't
actually matter for you
so this this is this is very common
approach that people use to sort of sort
of manually partition the database or
partition the data in such a way to
reduce the overhead of large scans so
one additional thing about this query if
you want to notice also too is that
everything I need to answer this query
is actually contained in the index
itself right so I'm doing a look-up on a
I did my where calls on see you there
and then the only thing I want to
produce is my output was B so do I
actually need to look at the tuple for
this rank is how would we normally
execute this we'd follow the index the
index at the value at the leaf node
assuming we have a B+ tree would have a
record pointer and then we would go
follow that record to go get the tuple
and then evaluate the rest of the query
but this particular query there's
nothing from the tuple itself that we
don't already get from the index so
these are called covering indexes so the
idea is that a covering index covers all
the data you need to exude a particular
query so this is not something you would
declare you don't say make this index B
recovering index it has to do on a query
by query basis write the data to system
can recognize that for this particular
query everything I need to answer the
question that you're asking me can be
found in a particular index and if so
it's considered a covering index all
right so to simplify our theme for for
the our simple query select B from food
where a equals 1 2 3 we can get the B
that we have needed from the output from
from the index after the arrows are
wrong right that should be there that's
read there all right so a would be for
this a D for that that that'd be there
right
so I've already sort of slowed and
what's the advantage of this I don't
have to go look at the tuple because
everything I need is is directly in the
index but we know this from our from you
guys are implementing your profitable
manager memory is limited so I already
have to bring in the index pages in
order to traverse the tree to get to the
leaf node that I wanted but now if I
have a covering index I don't have to go
look at the tuple there's one less page
read
one less entry into the buffer pool I
have two good make to get the data I
need for this query so this can
significantly speed things up in a lot
of cases especially for doing a lot you
know large range scan where you only
want to get things you know you were
doing a large reading scan and your
tuples are really big so I mean to go
fetch the data for the tuple would be
you know you have to read a lot of pages
so this is something that is widely used
in the the major commercial systems
MongoDB supports this uh I think
Postgres supports it now they're getting
better and post eleven which comes out
later I don't think my sequel at least
my sequel five point seven doesn't does
not support this I don't know what
sequel light does right again the idea
here is we can reduce contention in a
buffalo and not only for the amount of
memory we have to fetch from disk to go
into the query but also just the we have
to go into the buffalo manager fewer
times we take fewer latches so this this
is a big win in a lot of situations
now that may be some cases also to where
the data I need though for to make it a
covering index is not not actually being
indexed right in theory I could if I
have say actuaries ABC on foo I could
index make an index on a and B and C and
just never you know never do the lookup
on C so in this case here it would make
a covering index more often than not but
you're sort of wasting space now because
in your upper levels of the tree the
Internode's
your index and see when maybe you don't
actually need to so way to get around
this is called index include columns and
the idea here is that in our create
index statement we add a little include
clause and then we list a bunch of atras
that we want to get packed into the leaf
nodes for any key that were indexing
right so this again this case here I
build my index on a and B but now in the
leaf nodes for every entry of unique
pair of a and B I'm also going to
include the values of C so now if I have
my query that from before where I say
you know select B for food what a equals
1 through 3 and C equals whoo tang I can
get a and B from the index and then get
C from the where clause
so I as far as I know I know sequel
servers from Microsoft supports this
again Postgres 11 will support this
later this year my sequel doesn't do
this at least not in version 5,7 sequel
light doesn't do this and actually I
don't think Oracle and db2 does this but
I might be wrong so in theory again you
could just pack everything in the
include clause but then you essentially
end up with an index organized table and
you're just really sort of duplicating
things unnecessarily so sort of this
trade-off between how much I want to
include my index versus you know how
much extra space I'm willing to pay it
is try to speed up queries right so the
last thing I will talk about are what
are called functional and expression
indexes Postgres originally used to call
these functional indexes sometimes in
the literature it'll call expression
indexes but the way I think about this
is everything I've shown so far anytime
you created an index we would just
always say oh and attribute a 1 actually
be and would copy the exact values of
those attributes from the table and and
build your keys on those but there may
be some cases where I don't want to
store the keys exactly as they appear in
the underlying table let's say I have a
query like this I have a new table
called users and just think of like
people it's a user account and you keep
track of the timestamp of when someone
logged in and I have some query that
says I want to give me all the users
that logged in on a Tuesday so the
extract function says for given
timestamp login extract the day a week
from it and I'm checking here to see
equals to which is which is Tuesday
right sunday 0 Monday 1 Tuesday 2 so
let's say I build the index on login
like this would this help me for this
query shaking head no why correct he
says the data that we want in order to
that we need for to satisfy our where
Clause is not in the data itself it's
derived from the function we invoke
right so think about what this index is
actually doing it's going to create you
a sorted list of all the users based on
their login but I want
people that are logged in on Tuesday so
there's not gonna be a single range
where I can get these values that give
me all the people that are that logged
in on Tuesday I can may be a little bit
tricky and recognize my lower bound and
upper bound and try to calculate you
know what ranges would be people logging
in on Tuesday but as far as they don't
know data some what actually would
actually do that so this index doesn't
help us so instead what we can do is
that we can just take the expression
that we want to compute and embed that
in the index itself so now when I define
my import Keys I want to put my index
instead of having you know a single
attribute I can then put the same
function I would have normally in my
where clause in this case here we're
gonna we're gonna index everyone based
on the day of the week right we're still
getting everybody on Monday Tuesday
Wednesday and so forth and then now when
I execute this query it can it can you
know it you can know that I have the
function my where clause exactly matches
what I need in my in my index and
therefore I can use that so is there
another way to sort of do the same thing
and that we talked about before so far
another type of index we can use it to
essentially do the same thing for us say
we want to get exactly everybody that's
on a Tuesday with an index how would I
do that partial index right the where
clause means again to be anything you
have in a select statement and a where
clause you can put in your create index
in a where Clause right so let's do a
demo and we can see a little bit now
also how Postgres is gonna pick plans so
excuse me somebody asked why am I always
using Postgres and my demos is it
because I'm like you know a fanboy or
just you know obsessed with Postgres
postgis is really good post-crisis has
all the things that we're talking about
in this class
Postgres has available to us and we can
it's almost like almost a textbook
definition or implementation of a
database system and another thing I like
about Postgres too also is that it has
many of those things that the commercial
guys have Postgres eventually gets as
well right I said that the index include
columns was in sequel server that's
where its first implemented post
adding that now in 11 and it's open
source and free it's amazing alright so
let me do this let me drop the table of
users I'll create a new one right it
only has two fields has the ID field for
the primary key and just a wandering
current key always increasing and then
it's going to have this timestamp field
and then let's generate some synthetic
data so for this what I'll do is I will
do now I will do an insert query that
it's going to insert into the login
table and then it's gonna there's this
function in Postgres called generate
series that's just going to generate a
monotonically increasing a list of
values so it's going to generate me a
bunch of time stamps from 2017 generate
first until today at one month of
one-minute intervals and it's going to
created 900 thousand records so let's
say I take the query that I wanted right
like this if I run it it comes back
pretty fast but if we go check the query
plan you see that it's doing a
sequential scan on the user's table in
order to apply the predicate right so if
I now go create my index on just a login
field when everyone explain again it
doesn't pick the index because it
doesn't help us it only does this
winchell scan so let's drop that index
and make one with the partial index the
expression index and now when I run my
plug query plan it recognizes that it
can use the index that is created for a
for the for to do next and I'll explain
what a bitmap scan is later on but
basically just think about it
it's how post is keeping track of what
to post match so now let's create though
the partial index that I had before so
to Postgres login where
right so this is creating the partial
index where I'm still going to long get
all of the login information that the
login timestamp but my where clause says
only get people where they logged in on
on Tuesday so now if we go back to our
query plan let's take a take a bet who
says post dress is gonna pick the
partial index who says it's going to
pick the expression index raise your
hand for partial and if you say raise
hand for the expression index so why do
you think it would pick the expression
index horse isn't it
although the partial index is pretty
specific right
the partial index was which one was it
this one this one right where extract
we're day a week with a lot from login
equals two that's exactly what I want to
execute in my query right from one my
index is where day a week from login
Eagles - so take the partial index again
it knows how to match the where clause
with what's in with that's defined for
the index with the where clause that's
defining your query and pick that if I
change this to b3
right it picks the expression index
because the partial index doesn't have
any of that information all right this
is sort of clear what's going on to meet
the covers and it uses the same all the
same storage information that we talked
about last class right it's doing the
same thing all right there's nothing
special because it's an expression it
just knows that when I insert a record I
run that expression and insert that into
as the key rather than the original
attribute the original value of the
thing I am indexing yes
his question is when should you create
or drop an index I is that just an
open-ended broad question do you mean
and mean something specifically in
people notation or is it like like if
I'm administrating a database when
should I do this this question is from
the application level when it when is
the right time to drop a created index
so this is essentially what DBAs do for
you right you you basically look for
your application and say what queries
are running slow and which ones are you
know what queries running flow and are
the indexes that could help me improve
the performance right so there's tools
to sort of do this for you and a lot of
cases for like OTP applications like if
you use like an ORM like you know Django
or Ruby on Rails
you know you define you get implicit
index for free right because you say I
want this activity unique because most
of the time I'm doing the lookups on
that so then it'll create the index for
you so you gets you things speed up the
more complicated things are when you
have to let the local it queries are
running slow and there's ways to turn on
this it's called the slow query log and
my sequin Postgres in those systems to
say show me all the queries that run
longer than 20 milliseconds you look at
a bunch of those and say well what's
what's that what indexes could I use to
speed things up all right so it's sort
of like you just let the look and see
what's slowing you down there's no like
there's no the conventional wisdom a
hard fast rule to say if your query
looks like this then add it index if
your quarry looks like that and then
drop an index it depends on the
application what you care about
right it's maybe the case that I have a
query that's just like it takes you know
100 milliseconds but it runs once a day
so who cares
all right it depends what you want your
application ok all right so any
questions about like these other ways to
use indexes all right pretty
straightforward again it just builds on
top of the things we've already talked
about like what you have a you know
awesome underlying data structure that
you know is its thread safe and reliable
you can stand start implementing all
these other cool things on top of this
and it's essentially what you know that
do it why more older database systems
have more way more features than the
then let the newer guys like Postgres
has been around for a while and there's
adding all this we'll call some stuff
you know on top of their existing
infrastructure
all right so I want to step back now and
start talking out different data
structures so the way to think about
what we talked about last class with the
B plus stream is that we were
essentially building a sorted list of
keys right if you think of like the leaf
nodes the leaf nodes were just just
essentially just a linked list of keys
in sorted order and then there was some
infrastructure on top of them to keep
the the the tree portion of the data
structure that we would use to route
ourselves to find the data that we're
looking for but the most simplest way to
actually implement an index would be
just just a single linked list right the
problem though is that all the
operations on that linked list would be
always in oh end time because you have
to do a linear search alright so again
think of this is just the leaf nodes of
our of our B plus tree we have keys and
then we have values the value portion is
just a pointer to the next key so
anytime I want to find Pickler key I
don't I can't jump to the middle I have
to scan across from the beginning and
check as I go along worst worst case
scenario I'm at the end best case
scenario I'm the first one I'm looking
for right again it's just just a simple
linked list so one way to sort of speed
things up is that rather than doing our
searches in literally by just looking at
one key after another we could actually
maybe build sort of a way to jump ahead
in our linked list to find keys the key
that we're looking for more quickly
right so it's a really simple way to do
this would just be add another pointer
for every other element that points to
that jumps over that element that key
right so from key 1 I can either go from
key to or jump ahead and go to key 3 so
now if I'm looking for a particular key
say key key 5 I can look at key 1 so
that's not the one I want jump ahead to
key 3 that's not the one I want either
jump ahead using the top level over key
for - key 5 and then I found what I
wanted yes
so this question is our belief notes and
gatito's regions of memory for this
assume no statement is if we if we
assume yes can we just do a binary
search that will make searching go
faster that makes insertion slower
because now you got to slide everything
over right just keep it really steep
ascent with a linked list writes the
easiest data structure to implement ok
so we knew this and skip ahead and that
helps us that cuts things down further
we can just go add another level of
pointers and skip every 4th one right
and so forth right so now to find the
key that we'll be looking for is is we
can follow along the top point and we
realized we go too far can we go down
the next level may follow those pointers
until we reach the very bottom and find
the thing we want or find that we've
gone past the key where we we've gone
past the key where our key should be so
we know it's not there so this is a high
level is what a skip list is so skip
list is essentially a multiple level two
linked lists and you could have extra
pointers there skip over intermediate
nodes in your linked list there's a
quick show hands who here is heard of a
skip list before ok but about a third
maybe lesson happen so again the way to
think about is it gonna have multiple
levels of these linked lists and what
have these extra pointers allow us to
jump ahead things now if you sort of
think at a high level when I show the
diagram it's gonna look a lot like a P
plus tree right but we'll see some
differences later on because we don't
have to end up doing any rebalancing
anytime we do it insert and delete with
a linked list we don't have to ever do
splits and merges because all we know
that we we want to add our entry we just
update the guy that came before it to
now point to us instead of pointing to
the one that we now point to so this is
sort of one of the advantages you're
gonna get within a skip list so it's not
a new data structure it dates back to I
think 1990 it was invented by a
professor at University of Maryland but
in the last 10 years
skip lows have become sort of
fashionable because you can actually
implement one as a lock free data
structure
we can argue whether that's a good idea
or not and actually show numbers I
showed it is not a good idea but there
has been a couple systems in recent
years that that you skip list so rock DB
is a log structured system that we
talked about earlier right instead of
sorting the tuples they store logs in
the heap files and then they build it in
memory skip lists to keep map u from
keys to offsets in the log Y our Tiger
builds builds an in memory skip lists as
an ephemeral data structure when they
fetch in a page getting sort of the same
thing you build some way to jump to
different offsets very quickly in an ER
page the most famous Skip list database
system is mem sequel we can talk offline
about how they came around to deciding
to use a skip list but there are all the
non skip lists they do not have a B+
tree they do not have any other index
that they're all they use nothing but
skippers yes why does what sorry well
what will make more complicated so it's
quite this question is does this make
insertion more complicated let's go
through an example of insertions and
you'll see why not again comparing this
with the B+ tree the B+ tree I do an
insertion and I may have to split my
node but then that that recursively goes
up the tree and I have this put my
parent would may split the root maybe
split everyone else so with a single
insertion a worst case scenario I have
to rebuild the entire tree in a skip
list you never have to do that every
modification is always localized to the
portion of the list you're modifying
okay so the way you think about skip
list as I said is just a collection of
linked lists and so at the very bottom
is like the leaf nodes and B plus tree
you have to have every single key that
exists right because otherwise you know
you'd have false negatives because the
key wasn't be there
all right so every kid exists is always
at the bottom and he had pointers from
one key to the next but then the next
level above bag is gonna have links or
pointers to every other key going above
that you can have every fourth key and
so forth so in general what's gonna
happen is at every level you'll have
half as number of pointers as the little
below you and so the way you figure out
whether you want to add a pointer at a
level when you do an insertion is you
actually flip a coin
you use a random number generator decide
whether you're going to actually add a
pointer at a level so this mends up
making this a probabilistic data
structure which is different than the B
plus tree or the radix tree you want to
see a second which are deterministic
data structures so that means that if I
had take the same set of keys and I
insert it to my Skip list and you know
use a different random number generator
seed I may end up with a different
physical structure of the data of the
index every single time I rebuild it and
it B plus tree you wouldn't have that
because its terminus t'k meaning when I
do an insert I know where it's gonna go
and then if I do a split merge long as
you don't you know flip a coin when you
decide whether you want to steal from
the light sibling of the left sibling
you're gonna always end up the exact
same physical layout of the data no
matter how many times you rebuild the
index in the case of the Skip list it
can change every single time because you
have this randomness to it so because
though even though it's it's it's gonna
be random the math works out that will
get approximately log n
search and insertion operations which is
the same thing we saw in the in the B+
tree so worst case scenario we get
completely unluckily and know that we
always have no no pointers that upper
levels but you know with a billion keys
that's almost impossible to ever happen
so in the end we work out almost the
same asymptotic properties as as a B+
tree so let's look at example so as I
said the way they're going to skip lists
in some ways it's just a it's just
another B+ tree the way everyone
represents it in these diagrams is
always a flat list like this but if you
certain things you should have rotated
it in some ways it looks a lot like a
binary tree so the first thing to point
out is that we have at the beginning and
the end we have the starting entering
point for our our index with these
different levels and at the end we have
just these these markers to say we reach
the end of the linked list at a given
level right and then we just love what
we have the probability that we're going
to have a pointer for a given key you
know based on how high we are so at the
very bottom the first level the
probability of
a pointer for particular key is one and
above that it's half that and above that
it's half of that and so forth the very
bottom is is again is the linked list
this is where you have to have every pot
every ski every key we could represent
as a triplet so you have the key that
that you inserted the value would be the
P the record pointer to to the actual
tuple and then you have a pointer to
your neighbor in the linked list in the
levels above that you replace the record
pointer with actually a pointer to pick
the same key below you so in order to
have a key above in an upper level you
have to have obviously the key below you
so this vertical sort of strip of having
the same key across different levels
it's called a tower in skip list right
so what that means that I can't have a
key to be up in here in level three
without having a key in level two all
right and then at the top one we haven't
we haven't had any keys end up in the
first level so it just points to the the
end marker in reality what way this
would work is you just keep a counter it
says how many what's the highest level I
have so that when you do an insertion or
do a lookup you know where to always
start off with so in this case here we'd
say all right the highest link I have is
in the second level so I always stop
start at level two I never started level
three all right let's see an example of
how to do an insertion so let's say I
want to start key five and I've
conveniently left off space here to
start a key five in my diagram so to do
the insertion what we're gonna do is
we're gonna flip a coin decide how many
levels we want to go we want to add a
tower our new key into so you always
have to have key at the first level we
flip a coin to the second level
it comes up heads so we say yes we want
to insert it we flip a coin again for
the third level it comes up ahead so we
wanna start it again we flip it the
third time and it comes up tails so we
know we don't want to add a new level
all right we keep going until we hit
tails all right so that means that we
want to add key five to these these to
be levels like this so at this point
here I've allocated a memory I've
created my triplets to store the key but
it's not fully integrated into the index
because the
keys that come before it in the list
still are pointing to key six okey four
is pointing to key six on the first
level and key for is pointing to the
endpoint in this in the second level so
the first thing I need to do in my tower
is add the pointers now going down right
so then that way if anybody lands at the
higher point they can always reach it
reach reach to the bottom and then going
from the bottom to the top I'm now gonna
all right same thing I have that pointer
to the end but going from the bottom to
the top I'm gonna add I'm gonna modify
the key to come before me to now point
to me right and at this point the key is
integrated into the index mean the
anybody that scans along the bottom will
find us but what what happened two
priests came across the top when we find
it no right is that cuz is that so okay
she's taking her yes and he seemed real
emphatic about it why that says that
we're gonna eventually add it but think
of this scenario alright at this point
here the index looks like this key five
is there anybody that just comes along
the bottom and scans along here would
find it but anybody that maybe starts at
the second level scans along here and
they're looking for key five this thing
still points to the end so it's a oh
well key font
there's nothing beyond key for at this
point that I'm looking for so I've just
skipped past it right it would miss it
it'd be a false negative so I'm not
gonna explain it all in detail now but I
sort of set us up a little bit for next
class and later when we talk about
transactions this is okay to have this
right this is this is this is a higher
level logical thing that where
transactions may not see all the changes
immediately and that's okay what's not
okay if we have corrupted data structure
so this thing said uh pointing to key
five or key six appointed a garbage and
some other thread came along and
followed that pointer and started
reading garbage that would be bad right
cuz he would crash we'd read something
we shouldn't we shouldn't
reading but in this case here the data
structures sound all the pointers are
going to the correct things just whether
a thread comes along that you know maybe
was here at the moment this thing got
got flipped in and it would miss it and
keep going logically that's okay we can
we can rectify that later on but
physically it's you know physically we
don't want to have it point to nothing
so this is a good good distinction
between having a consistent data
structure versus a corrupted data
structure the higher-level semantics of
what our queries are doing are allowed
to miss this change but we obviously
don't want to crash so we'll cover more
about this on on on Wednesday we're
mostly going to focus on how do we make
sure our data structure thread safe when
we talk about transactions we then we
talk about the problem of one
transaction not seeing the changes from
another transaction that they probably
should all right so the main thing I'm
trying to point out here is like
swapping the pointers like this may not
make it so that any threat can see the
data that we need at this moment but
that's okay I could do to avoid all this
by having a single latch on the entire
data structure so that no thread could
could ever read it anytime I modify it
but that would be slow cuz now
everyone's gonna bottleneck on that so
instead we're gonna have we just do the
single compare and swap here allow other
threads to read inconsistent data and
that's okay okay
all right so again now I'm going from
from the bottom to the top I go to the
next level say anything I felt my
pointer now anybody comes along that
sees us and then the level here gets
swapped in and then out anybody can find
us and now our key is fully integrate
all right so that's that answer a
question of inserts okay yes this
question is how do you know which node
is before you so to do an insert you
have to basically figure out where I do
a search and forgot where I should be
and you keep track of the steps along
the way
okay yes this question is does this mean
you do a search on every level
yes actually let's go through that demo
now okay all right so they say yeah
sorry so your statement your question is
the gap between two nodes at a different
level are not the same ones the second
part you said same what yes alright so
his question is in this case here at the
second level key to jumped over one
tuple one key here and what a key for
but now this at this point here the the
number of tuples that this thing's gonna
jump over is is actually zero because
you go to there so again it's a
probabilistic data structure I flipped
the coin to decide where I want how I
want my Tower to be when I insert it so
this by chance by random it said all
right I want something key to and I want
I'm sorry level two and level three so
this made the gap be zero right in
practice with a really large data set
this randomness works out that on
average you're you're skipping at least
one this particular exam why doesn't
right because the alternative could be
if you think about it if you if you
hadn't forced it so that every single
time you add a new key and you don't
want to add it to a level that you
always make sure that it jumps at least
one if now I insert say if I insert and
say something four point five in here I
would have to then maybe modify other
things in the tree to make sure that
it's only jumping one but it's random I
don't care I don't care whether it's
exactly one or or some some you know
exactly one or zero or something large
in that I don't care
hey because I it makes the change be
localized and in practice with a large
enough you know the billion keys it
works out just fine
yes yeah so his question good basic
start here
I had a key five right initially nobody
points to me now I go through and I at
every level going from the bottom to the
top I have to then swap this point or
now point to me yes you have to do
what's that this question is the cost of
doing the swap small absolutely yeah so
in if it's an emery index its compare
and swap in modern CPUs that's a single
instruction that's super cheap okay
again it be done atomically
this is sir he made a comment before to
is like if i assumed everything is in
pages together opportunity memory then
you know maybe don't the swap pointer as
much cuz you just move things around the
way people try to mm up these sort of as
a first pass is just you just have every
node sort of be its own sort of chunk of
memory and then you do have the swap
this point if you cluster them together
group them together you can you may not
have to actually swap a pointer but in
the in addict able here at you do and
it's cheap to do and again if I do it
here like he's in there it's not that's
another thread may come along and miss
me that's okay and then I end up and
then I've mentioned I'll swap the rest
and then now I'm fully integrated right
the reason why we go from the bottom to
the top that way if someone someone is
here if I'm here and someone's trying to
start key four point five same time I'm
trying to start key five we do the
compare-and-swap
only one of us is gonna win because
compare-and-swap says check to see
whether the value I want to replace in
memory equals what I think it should
equal if yes replace it with my new
value if no then you fail so if both
these guys try to do the compare and
swap thinking that key four points to
key six
only one of them will succeed they don't
have to back off and retry so doing this
is really cheap adieu okay let's just
see how we do a search now all right so
I want to find key three so I at this
point here I know from my data structure
I have three levels so I also have to
start at the first level so I'm gonna
look ahead and the pull in the pointer
and it says oh it points to key five I
know that key five is greater than key
three so I can't continue along this
path in the Skip list at this level I
have to go down to the next level and I
do the same thing I fall along the path
now I see key 3 is greater than key 2
so I do want to skip ahead jump along
and now look ahead to the next the next
node the next key which is key for but
key 3 is less than key 4 so now I go
down and then now I just scan across the
leaf nodes until I find the one thing
I'm looking for so sort of like you're
stepping down different levels trying to
go as far as you can across horizontally
because that means you're skipping it
way more keys at the bottom but at some
point you'll hit a boundary you say I
can't go past this because the Kia that
I'm looking for is less than what your
key is so I go down a level and
eventually reach the very bottom and
then now it's just a linear scan to find
what I want it so this clip nice pretty
straightforward alright so let's do
deletion so the thing I want to focus on
here is that we have this distinction
logical deletes and physical deletes so
a logical leap is late means that any
thread that comes along should will not
see the key I just deleted but
physically it's still there and memory
is still inside of my pages right that's
different than what we saw in the B plus
tree because when we did a delete we
went and took the key actually out we
may have to do a merge to reshuffle
things around accordingly so what I'm
going to do now is along the leaf nodes
or sorry the bottom level for my my keys
I'm gonna add a simple boolean flag that
says whether it's been deleted true or
false so now let's say I want to delete
key 5 I do my search just like I did
before and I walk down until I find the
the leaf node that I want
for the key that one delete and then I
just flip its flag to be true it's now
at this point any thread that comes
along and they see and looking for key
five would say oh the belief flag is
true therefore I should just ignore it
right but physically it's still there
and then now what I do is I start
removing the pointers going in reverse
direction from the top to the bottom so
I'll unlink it from from the top level
and the second level and so forth and
the very bottom I get here and then now
anybody that's getting along would be
rerouted around me so the reason why
we're doing this is because it's sort of
work where we want to let everyone know
that things have been deleted as soon as
possible so to minimize that we know
where someone might get a false positive
and so because we have to go to the top
to the bottom right we would just go we
want to flip this thing to be true so
that way as we're going down our towers
and linking things anybody that comes
along can just ignore the key that it
sees right because otherwise we only
delete it till we reach the very very
bottom right and then once we and then
you know we're not gonna talk about
garbage collection or thread safe Tina's
here but once you know that no other
thread could ever possibly looking at
your node it's okay hey free the memory
again this avoids having people read
corrupted data all right so to finish up
skip list the advantages are the main
thing is that the insertions deletions
do not require any major rebalancing
because all the changes are localized to
just that point of the of the Skip list
right it's not like a B+ tree where you
have to recursively grow up and do
splits emerges that calls you to
reshuffle everything in practice the
Skip list could potentially use less
memory than a typical be blushed reading
if you don't use the optimizations that
the compression stuff we talked about
last class and only you only get that
benefit though if you don't include
reverse pointers so I showed in the loop
at the lowest level the linked list
always went one direction if I wanted to
reverse scan I can't do that as is being
shown because I don't
pointers in the other direction if I had
other points in the other direction then
then I can't do that compare-and-swap
atomically that I talked about and happy
you know store extra space for those
pointers so case MMC Co if you find the
early blog post when they announced hey
we're a new in a memory database system
and me you skip less because they lock
free the first thing people point out in
there so let's get less we can't go in
reverse direction so then people guys
came back and said well the way you
you saw that just usually make a second
set a separate second skip list that has
things sorted in reverse order and that
defeats the purpose the memory savings
you get from the Skip list so the
downside and the skip lists are that
they are not dissing cash friendly as he
was asking about before because we're
following all these pointers and jumping
along to the different locations every
single time we traverse things and then
as I said reverse search is non true to
implement you have to do something extra
which we'll cover in the advanced class
of how to do searches when you don't
have pointers in the other direction so
in the advanced class 15:21 for the last
two years in the spring ii programming
project was you have to implement your
own thread safe walk free skip lists
debating whether do that again this year
no and just I don't know interesting it
is and skip lists are not that common
but all right
all right any question that's goodness
yes his question is are they store the
buff ball yes if if you want to be
backed by disk yes means you have to
organize it in pages anything you wanna
be able to spill to disk has to be
stored in the buffer pool organizing
pages so you'd have to you can pack
multiple keys in a single page right but
then it that does require rebalancing if
you now insert things that expand the
key and you mean move it left and right
yeah this question is what the level
does get let's increase as we insert new
things yes because the probability that
you're gonna have a tower go up to a
really high level increases if the more
Keys you have
it's random every time I insert I flip
that coin and I keep I keep going until
it comes back with a head with tails
meaning like false right it's a random
data structure probablistic data
structure yes his question is why would
you want to even use a probability to
build this data structure over a B+ tree
or just for this particular data
structure Thanks I mean what's the
alternative the alternative would be you
have a heuristic and say all right for a
key that looks like this I add so many
levels and member I said before the
issue of that one now is like I don't
know what all the keys are gonna be
ahead of time so I may pick a bad
heuristic that would say you know four
keys that mod two equals zero
you know add it to level two key mod to
equal three add it to level three that
maybe bags I may never see keys that
have the had the particular batteries in
it I have just I just have a stupid
linked list at the bottom by making it
random you sort of make a good best
effort for all possible domains of
values and again really large key spaces
it works out fine for a billion keys
it'll look it almost looks exactly like
a P plus tree
all right red X trees so red X trees are
less common but what's interesting about
them is that they they have different
properties than a B plus tree in a skip
list so I think that worth worth
discussing and I think that the current
research trend is that these things are
very interesting and a lot of the newer
systems are thinking about people think
about exploring them now so also say
ahead of time so there's a Ameri
database system out of Germany called
hyper that is very influential in state
of the art got bought by tableau last
year they use a radix tree as their main
data structure they don't have B plus
trees I know the data stacks guys that
are working on Cassandra
they are super keen on the radix trees
and tries less than I talk to them and
they look about integrating tries all
throughout
Cassandra which i think is really
interesting so a ray dextry
the way to think about this is that
we're gonna represent keys we want to
store in our inner index by their
individual digits rather than the entire
key and so by digit I don't necessarily
mean like you know a number like one two
or three like if I have a string of
characters each character is a digit or
if I have a number that each each number
is a digit so the the reason why we're
going to do this is now we're gonna be
able to do comparisons on the digits of
the keys in sort of prefix order one by
one rather than having to examine the
entire key so you sort of already do
this in some ways with with certain
functions like doing sring comparison
like you know it's this a four that
walks through the characters the
beginning of a string and actually
compare them and if it stops which means
you don't have a match but now the data
structure itself is gonna be designed to
do this very efficiently so the the
reason why what's what interesting about
is that now the height of the tree is no
longer dependent on the number of keys
that you have ranked in the B+ tree if
I'm sort of billion keys right depending
what my fan-out level is about how many
entries on I want to pack on my node
that's going to determine the number of
levels that I have in a radix tree
because the height of the tree actually
depends on the length of the key right
so I could have a billion tuples or
billion keys and have a really you know
a small key because they're not really
long strings but I can have another
billion key to the really long strings
and now my index will be really long
right so in a radix tree we're not going
to not require any rebalancing the major
level or reshuffling the same way we do
splits emerges in nmp plus tree and
instead of actually storing the entire
key at every single level and then we
destroy these digits and then we can
reconstruct the key based on what path
we take down into the tree so quick show
of hands who here has heard of a radix
tree before even fewer patrcia tree
anybody who here is heard of a try all
right there we go good excellent so a
radix tree is just a variant of a try
okay so here's a tribe so I have three
keys hello have an hello hat to have so
in this sort of visual representation in
the Tri I'm storing at every edge
represents a single character of a key
so at the root I have H because all
three keys start with H in the case of
hello I'm gonna have now path down
h-e-l-l-o right I can reconstruct that
key by following that path so if I want
to check is the key hello in my index I
can start at the root I CH IC e you see
llo so forth and I reach my record
pointer at the bottom in the case of hat
and have they both start the second
character is a so I only need one entry
for a and then I have my split point for
the e for have and T for hat so the
tribes were first discovered back in
1959 by some French dude and then two
years later after that there was a
professor
edward edward fredkin coined the term
try as a concatenation of retrieval tree
he apparently his faculty at CMU I think
he's retired he's like a famous dude he
doesn't show up any faculty meetings but
apparently he's here I don't think that
he's in the directory so a radix tree is
sort of like a compressed version of the
Tri so in the try for h-e-l-l-o no other
key shared those those characters after
the after the h-e-l-l-o was specific to
hello but it still had that entire path
in a radix tree you recognize that
nobody else stores is storing PLO
so I just have a single edge with that
information there right sort of it's
packed together and the same thing for I
hat and have we're both sharing a so I
have my entry for a and then for have
nobody else shares ve so it's there by
itself right so that so a ray dextry is
a compressed version of a try if you
look in the literature or Wikipedia
sometimes they'll call Patricia Patricia
trees it's not named after a person it
has some other meaning from the 50s or
60s n I'll remember sometimes in
literature these are called
Suffolk's arrays or suffix trees the the
basic idea is the same databases we call
them radix trees so let's see actually
how you actually really store this so
nobody actually really stores the in
that sort of edge oriented diagram that
show before where you have the
characters the digit stored in the edges
you storm the nodes right and your nodes
have to fit in pages so the way you
would actually mmm this is maybe try to
pack in as much data you can within a
single page at a different level in the
tree so in this case here for the second
level I have elo for hello and then a
shared by I hadn't have I would pack
them into a single page now let's see if
I wouldn't start a new key on the sort
hair in this case here I would recognize
that the H and a or row share so that I
just follow along term up to my third
level here and then I see that I already
have space to store I R and so I can
pack it in there so it's not we are
gonna do potentially do merges but we
never have to do we may have to do
splits as well but it's always sort of
in and we never have to do it be
balancing the same way that you have to
do it in a B+ tree so let's say I went
delete hat in half so I go ahead and
find my two injuries here and I delete
them and then I recognize that I have R
by I R by itself and I can decide to
leave it here if I wanted to and
everything's still correct or if I'm if
I'm gonna be aggressive about using Rena
reusing memory or saving space I can
just can compress it and move it back up
alright so this sounds awesome right
because now we're storing using way less
data to store are like he's like if this
was a B+ tree but I want to store these
these these two keys hello and and hair
I'm going back here maybe the better
examine when I had all my keys in there
back here I would have maybe the root
would have hello or hat I have you know
in this entire form and then down below
in the leaf knows that I have the keys
in there time form again as well in this
case here I don't have to do that and
only store the key essentially once
a path into a record pointer can only
point out with the obvious downside of
this that is though what's the one
operation I said was really efficient in
a B+ tree you made the hand gesture
sorry yes scratch your scans along the
leaf nodes how do i how would I do that
here right I can't write I essentially
have because I because if I scan along
these guys I don't know what the key is
because the keys not being stored down
with me so I essentially have to keep a
stack of how I traversing the tree and
go back up and go back down and one of
the scan alone leave notes until I find
my end point so this is me way more
efficient for for storing storing keys
it'll make in the second we'll see well
Hawaii point queries are much more much
more efficient insertions are much more
inefficient as well but the scans are
gonna be much slower because again we
have to backtracking all right so the
the major thing to talk about though is
how we're actually to store keys in our
in our raid extreme so not all the ash
trees we want to store can we just split
them up by their digits or characters
and store them directly in the index you
actually do some transformations in
order to put it through a form that
makes it amenable to doing the comic you
know digit by digit comparison we want
to do and this has to has to do a lot
with how the the underlying CPU is going
to represent data let's say you have an
unsigned integer so we want to maybe
split it up by by bytes and struggles
bytes as our digits in the in our in our
tree because we can do really efficient
single instructions and do comparisons
of bytes the problem is though if we're
on Intel CPUs which are little endian if
we go from you know from left to right
and look at that then we're actually
looking at the most literally the least
significant bit first and that's how can
you do incorrect comparisons so we're
need to flip it and start it as big
endian form and then store the prefixes
that way and I'll show an example what
that looks like in a second same problem
for sign integers right we have the two
complements bit in the front so we had
them flip back to make sure that
negative numbers are less than positive
numbers and then we can store everything
else in
inform that we talked about before for
floats be more complicated you have to
classify them whether deposit or
negative whether there's normalized
denormalize and then just try to store
them as unsigned integers right cuz I
think about this way the the harbor's
can represent the floating point so it
keeps track of where that floating point
number is so that means you know thirty
three point zero is is greater than
three point three zero so we need to
keep track of you know where that
floating point is so that we can do our
correct comparison so we can normalize
everything for compound in keys like if
I have two integers I'm going to build
an index on that I do my transformation
then concatenate them together and
everything worked up just fine well
let's look at the unsigned integer
problem let's say that I want to store
this key here 168 million I don't to
sort of store this as an unsigned 32-bit
integer so we're about two compliments
here all right so I can represent this
as 4 1 byte hex codes alright and would
look like this so now if I store it
though in order and big-endian versus
little-endian form we see that we get to
lead to totally different sort orders of
these right so for big endian the most
difficult it will be represented first
but a little endian it's at the bottom
so say now I want to compare whether 3
is less than 116 million in the case if
I was stored in little-endian then I
would happen I wouldn't know until I get
to the very bottom right but if I'm big
endian but I would know at the very top
that yes 3 is less than a hundred
sixty-eight million so I can terminate
the search immediately right so it
looked like this in our tree right and
so this would be a path down into store
hundred million I mean compare whether
the value 1 is there right because I
want to compare if I'm stored in
little-endian form the value 3 the
integer 3 at the the most difficult is 0
0 right but the bottom would be mean you
know 1 0 out right yes 1 1 and 1 1 would
be great in them rather than this and
therefore I it would be incorrect so we
flip it around when we want to store
this on on little-endian cpus to make
sure we can do faster comparisons so if
they do this for all the possible basic
data types we want to
I is this sort of clear this is
something but the architecture with the
ticket be mindful of and and transform
our data to make it amenable restoring
in a rate extreme so now for this entire
class I've not shown you any benchmark
numbers because I want to sort of focus
on the fundamentals of the databases
that we're talking about in this this
course but I want to show you in case
you get the wrong idea of how amazing
skip lists are some benchmark results
we've done in our own research to show
that it's not actually the case so this
is a comparison we published in sigmod
this year written by was done by a PG
student here at CMU and we compared a
data structure that we implemented
called the called the BW tree so this is
something originally invented by
Microsoft for the hackaton system for
sequel server from five or six years ago
we when I showed up a CMU I thought was
amazing thing and we went we set out to
build our own because it was an open
source one so we built our own open
source BW tree was a lock free data
structure and we want to see how well it
would compare against other existing
data structures let's the spoiler is
that it sucks and gets crushed but we
also compared the BtoB tree against the
B+ tree a skip list and a raid extreme
and so for this this is on a single
socket CPU and we're running with ten
cores or twenty twenty threads we're
doing insert only read only and then
read an update and what you see is that
for the radix tree crushes every one
right it's just so fast to do these
quick you know breaking up these values
into digits and doing insertions and
lookups and updates very quickly the
Skip list always loses right the BW tree
turns out actually almost always loses
to a regular actually skip list is doing
okay here yeah that might be wrong
yeah these might be flood baby might be
swept swatch there's no way yeah there's
no way sorry my fault okay I shoulda put
bread maybe for my C to go check the
paper now make some papers right so the
raid x-tree blows everyone away right
it's just because the the amount of work
you have to do to do comparisons is so
much less than a B+ tree for doing
insertions you don't think these splits
emerges right in the Skip list this is
an in-memory database we're not worried
about reading from from the buffer pool
the the you always lose out because the
cache misses in an indirection from from
chasing pointers and the BtoB tree just
has so much overhead to make it lock
free this is again we'll just if you
take the advanced class we'll discuss
this lock free sounds like an amazing
thing we want to use this for all our
data structures but in the day and B
plus tree which is you know latching
that we'll talk about on Wednesday
outperforms it and the radix tree is
using latching well it's not it's not
walk free okay any questions yes so his
question is for the rate extreme when I
showed the compression or the compare
the collapsing collapsing of one node
into another node his question is is
that only don' at the leaf nodes or is
it done anywhere in the tree so the
textbook definition of a radix tree does
not actually do any of this collapsing
in a practical implementation you won't
you'd want to do this so in the hyper
system but the German system I mentioned
was bought by tableau they have a paper
where they show how to adaptively do
this there's collapsing or splitting at
all different levels yeah there's one of
those things were like a radix tree was
an old idea it's been around for a while
and it wasn't till like people actually
oh this seems like a good idea let's
actually try to make one work in
practice that people recognize oh this
is something we should revisit yes this
question is the rate of trees so fast
for special stands I don't have the
graph here and answers now B plus tree
is always gonna win
the Skip list does okay too because he's
just following leaf nodes but the
pointer chasing always loses out okay so
we have five minutes left so we'll do a
crash course on on on inverted indexes
so all the tree Anika's we talked about
so far are really good for what are
called point queries and range queries
pointed queries are fine you know Andy's
find a customer record where they had
the zip code one five two one seven or
range query be fine all the orders
within a particular time range right
from June 27th June 2018 is September
2018 but these data structures are not
good for keyword searches so I'm going
to find all the Wikipedia articles that
contain the word Pablo right I can't use
my index for that right because think
about how you actually would store the
Wikipedia article I we saw this we saw
this before right this is the the sample
schema from the real actual Wikipedia
software okay we have user accounts and
your pages and there's revisions for
pages right and then the so the actual
content of the article is stored here in
this content field as a text field so I
could build an index on text field but
that is actually not what we want right
because that's going to be an exact
match of all everything that's in my
text field and actually I think
databases will let you do this but it's
actually a terrible idea because these
text fields are gonna be you know
kilobytes I think how long is the it's
always like some Star Wars article it's
always the longest we compete the
article what might be Pokemon now right
if I build an index on that I'm storing
that entire Pokemon article as a key and
then I can only men use it for exact
matches this is - so this is not what we
want so even if I go again if I try to
build my index on content it won't help
for this particular query because it's
just me it's I want to find a partial
match with this in actuality this is
actually not the right sequel itself
higher because I'm gonna find maybe the
word Pablo but this is gonna find any
substring that matches with pop whoa all
right a lot of times people want to use
these these these these data systems you
want to find you know show me the word
that says Obama
not in a mobile or something like that
right so this is what an inverted index
does so an emergent index is going to
map words within a record or the
hatchery that were indexing to the
actual record itself right and the
reason why it's called inverted because
think about like your strong documents
like in these Wikipedia articles instead
of storing this the whole document you
have you you invert it so you store
pointers to this documents based on what
words they use alright so in the
literature these are sometimes called at
least databases called
full text search indexes to go back to
like the 1800s
they were neighbors called concordances
right so the concordance would be like
somebody in 1800s some woman spent 16
years making essentially an inverted
index to track every single word in that
Shakespeare used in this entire like
bibliography alright so but nobody
already calls that now an invert usually
called an inverted indexes so we're not
gonna have time to go into the actual
implementation of this but essentially
you can think about it as we can use
some tree indexes to find the words that
we want and then some additional
metadata and say here's here's where the
work can be found or here's what words
are close to it so all the major
databases would support full-text
full-text search indexes in some form
the other the commercial guys actually
have obviously have much better packages
Postgres of course has this thing called
gin the generalized inverted index I
think it was called and it has a bunch
different ways you can use B plus trees
or hash indexes to represent the data
structure itself and then they have
extensions to sequel to allow you do
more complicated things than than the
like that I shared before so again all
of the major systems have that have
these but there are all sorts these
specialized database systems that are
designed explicitly for these full-text
searches so elastic search is probably
the most famous one that's built on top
of leucine there's another project
called Sphinx and then Apache Solr I
think is I think also maybe built on top
of leucine as well but again think of it
again like they build inverted they're
designed to doing searches on
two indexes right instead of doing
searches on B plus trees so the separate
type of queries we want to execute our
go beyond what we saw before
I'm gonna do phrase searchers I want to
find exact phrases in my text I wanna do
proximity searches so I wanted to say
find me find me all documents or all
records where one word is if within
three words of another word right and I
don't care what words come in in between
it but I know I have to be exactly three
words you do wildcard searches or
regular expressions to find more
complicated patterns you want to match
them in your in your text and the
various systems all sort of have their
own proprietary extensions to expose
this information I think there's a
sequel standard that says how you can
write these kind of queries but no one
actually follows it very well when you
actually implement this again what what
distinguishes one implementation from
the next is what information they're
storing so the very least the most
minimal thing you need to store is just
an inverted index that map's the words
to the records right and then how do you
define a word depend on you know how you
actually split the text up you and
punctuation the spaces sometimes there's
stop words like the word though would
always split you know things together
things like that but you know also store
things like how often the word appears
where it actually appears and other
metadata about the data you're indexing
and then the big thing we care about in
a database system is when we actually
update it so you could just only do this
in a batch mode where you say take all
my documents or my records and build my
index you know once every day ideally we
want to keep it up to date so we could
maintain a sort of Ziller data structure
to keep track of all the changes and
eventually merge them into a batch again
the different systems do different
things so the main takeaway from this is
that there are additional data
structures we could build in for our
table indexes that allows to do more
complicated things than the B plus tree
or the hash indexes or the Skip list and
the radix trees that we seen before
because all of those guys are doing key
matches this allows us to do way more
complicated things again I realize I'm
going fast on this but if you if you're
really interested in inverted indexes
then we have a whole course at CMU 11 4
42 or 642 I think it just called search
engines
so the inverted index is essentially the
underlying data structure implementation
that the data store of how search
engines are implemented and as I said
they store way more complicated things
than just the actual key in order to you
know do do ranked matching and other
things that you may want to do in your
system okay so it's my opinion that B
plus trees are still the best way to go
for doing indexes radix trees are
promising and I think the start seeing
more in them in the future but the B
plus tree there's a reason why you know
it was called a 1979 u ubiquitous beat
up B plus tree it's so good so even now
even with loffley data structures it's
always the way to go so we didn't have
time to also discuss geospatial indexes
so think of indexes do you want to do
matching on like geospatial data like I
have a I have a map of the United States
and it's broken up by state I want to
know whether a given point is in a state
or not so you can't use two B plus tree
for that because again it's not doing
key matching the way we talked about so
far so the specialized data structure
it's called geospatial data structures
or multimedia data structures or
multi-dimensional data structures that
can handle these kind of things so I
just want you to be aware that they
exist are trees quadtrees KD trees if
you want to learn more about that
there's a class 15 826 taught by
christos flutist the guy go and tour
with his pop cover man I don't think
he's back in the spring so may not be
offered in the spring but it might be
offered the fall 2019 okay okay any
questions we're done all right next
class we'll talk about how to make all
these indexes thread-safe be focus on
crabbing because you need to know this
for a project to which I'll be
presenting as well on on Wednesday okay
all right guys have a good week
[Music]
to the party by the 12-pack case of a
boy six-pack for the egg gets the Real
ID replete with your drinking proper 12
ow
they say bill makes your breath but
saying eyes are straight so it really
don't matter