[Music]
maybe on the Jill's neck okay today
we're talk about joins and for
administrative things as I said project
to check when one is due today I did a
quick show of hands as he see was
actually finished but it's more people
I've come in the room who's actually
done this and got a hundred percent
there we go alright more people okay who
has not started good nobody alright the
other thing too is that there's no class
this Wednesday I had to deal with my
parole officer so I can't come to class
so that's gonna be entirely cancel and
use the time obviously to work on your
assignment but of course no one's gonna
do that but that's okay and then the
midterm exam will be in class in this
room Wednesday next week on October 17th
and it will cover everything up to and
including what we're talking about today
so on Mondays lecture next week
I think there's query optimization we
won't discuss that will be covered in
the exam at all and there's a homework
going out today on joint algorithms that
will begin germane to what's on the exam
so I'll post a study guide with again
again just to list the chapters and
homework problems that you should be
looking at I can also provide in the for
the textbook I think the odd problems
the answers are solutions are on the
internet so if you want to sort of do a
further you know further problems and
prepare for the exams you can do that
and then you can show up with a one page
or sorry a one sheet double-sided
handwritten notes with whatever you want
on it right can handwritten doesn't you
know you don't take the slide and try to
condense them down the small as possible
that's the urine running because I think
you'll get more out of it that way okay
and then also bring your ID and if you
have any
I think there's what if you need any
extra time or it have a medical issue
you need to deal with frit exam you know
please email me now we'll get that
tanker as soon as possible okay all
right
so the entire lecture today is going to
be on joins this is probably the almost
a difficult but the most challenging
aspect of building a database system of
relational data system is supporting
joints and doing this efficiently you
know the the the nose Siegel guys when
they came out they said Oh joins are
slow we're not gonna do joins some of
them are certain add joins not quite
well but that's okay but this isn't
really gonna be the most expensive thing
where the data system is gonna be
spending most their time on in in in for
analytical workloads for all it to be
workloads they're usually you know doing
single key lookups or the doing joins we
can use index nested loop join which
we'll see in a second so joins aren't
that expensive in ultimate workloads
because you're just not joining large
segmented data in analytical workloads
this is totally the case where you know
we've done our own profiling I've seen
reports and other things where an
overwhelming majority maybe over even
50% of the time that Davidson is doing
work - excuse queries well we spent in
joint algorithms so it's really
important for us to get this right so to
understand sort of at a high level the
why we actually have to do the joins we
talked about this in the beginning of
the class when we talked about how we
would normalize tables to reduce the
amount of redundant and unnecessary
repetition of data in our in our
database and so the way to sort of think
about this is like we have our original
tuples and there may be columns or
attributes where we're repeating data
and then we're going to normalize them
essentially split them up into two
separate tables so that we don't repeat
this information so the join algorithm
so the join operator is essentially
putting them back together to
reconstruct the original tuples all
right and we need to talk about normal
forms because I didn't I didn't want to
to sort of be torture you guys with that
information but the high-level concept
is pretty pretty basic and this is
actually the example database we looked
at the very beginning of the lecture
right we want to keep track of our music
store we have artists that put out
albums and we said that we're gonna have
this cross
in stable art of artists album it has a
foreign key reference from be from the
artists table to end the album table we
did this because there may be some
albums where we would have multiple
artists appearing on it and instead of
having you know an entry we're repeating
the album information over and over
again we can again normalize it by
breaking it up based on these foreign
keys and and then now we have one entry
for the album one entry for the artist
even though there may be too many met
many to many relationship between the
two of them so normalization is the
process of designing your application
your applications database at a logical
level and splitting it up into
normalized tables and then joins are
essentially just putting back together
right so that that's what we're trying
to do today so today's class we're going
to focus on the the algorithms for
joining two tables specific we're gonna
focus on joining two tables with an
equijoin because that can be the the
most common approach we're not going to
talk about there are ways to do K way
joins or multiples of more than two
table joins excuse me we're not gonna
cover that in this class we'll cover
that in the advanced class this is the
most common type of join and you know I
can't say exactly exactly how many
numbers we're about percentage but
workloads that look like this if you're
doing join you're most always going to
be doing a inter equi-join so the
reoccurring theme we'll see as we talk
about these different algorithms is that
your own is always going to want to put
these the the the smallest table that
you're trying to join and smallest in
terms of number tuples that are being
fed into the join operator you're always
want to put that as the outer table I'll
explain what an outer table is in a
second because this is always going to
produce the the best the best execution
time the lowest cost of doing the join
as possible so before we get into the
actual algorithms don't spend time
talking about two additional things
we've got to talk about what these joint
operators are actually gonna produce as
output and then we can talk about how
we're going to determine whether one
algorithms better another what are we
going to use for our criteria determine
what's the cost of executing a query or
start executing a joint so say that we
have this sample query like this we're
doing a equi-join
on our
on the r ID equals SI b and we're gonna
have a joint operator in our query plan
that's going to produce some output and
shove it up to the projection operator
above it
and we talked a little bit about this
when we talk about query processing
about what the output of these operators
look like but in the case of joins it's
this is you can actually have the most
variance because it's a bunch of nth
ways you can do these things and it
really depends on things like what query
processing model you're using whether
it's vectorized materialization or the
iterator model depends on most of the
storage model if your column stores a
roast or then it also depends on what
the query actually looks like meaning
what data are we going to need above the
joint operator in our query plan and
that'll determine what we need to
produce as our output so we talked about
this before right we talked about the
concept of latent materialization in
inappropriate processing models and we
said that the sort of most easiest way
to do to produce output
it's just copy all the data that you're
fed and fed it into your operator and
shove it as your output all right so say
that in this example here we're joining
you know R and s together then we have
one two point R and two tuples in s so
our joint operator would essentially
just concatenate all the attributes of
our and all the attributes s for every
tuple that that's produced in our output
and then we shove that up through in the
query plan right and in this case here
we have a above that we have the
projection and the projection would know
that we only need to filter out the you
know the the data that we actually don't
need so in this case here we only need
our idea and see date so the projection
operator will just pull out those two
attributes so the advantage of this
approach is that you never have to go
back to the base table and get more data
because everything you need at this
point is that produce the rest of the
query plan is baked in this output here
but there may be some cases where you
you know at the table are really tables
really wide meaning there's a lot of
columns for both the init the the two
tables trying to join together it may
make sense to actually only produce a
subset of the output right in this case
here say FS had a bunch more attributes
I mean we only know we need value our ID
going up then maybe we don't want to
copy all the other crap into the join
operator and they have the join up or a
copy of it back out we talked about this
approach as well in the context of a
column store system where we can only
pass around maybe the record IDs our
offsets of the tuples from one operator
to the next and we do this because we
don't want have to copy large you know
glorg to 'pls going forward so in this
case here our join operator would only
produce the the keys that we joined on
and the record IDs of the matching
tuples and then we shove that up into
the query plan and then when we get into
our projection operator it knows that oh
I need see date from the s table so let
me go to the s table and pick out that
information if this is a column store
then this is super easy to do because
the C date column the creation date
column will be in US and its own
separate pages and we just jump to the
right all set for what we need for
others if it's a roast or this be kind
of you probably would not want to do
this because then you have to go back
and copy the entire tuple which would be
wasteful so no matter what what this
technique was called before we talked
about it we told a query processing
late materialization right we're
materializing the tuple that we need to
produce for the output as late as
possible in our query plan a lot of the
columnstore systems did this vertical is
really big on this as well but as
talking with them over the summer they
turns up they stop doing this because it
actually turned out to be too slow I
don't remember the full details but this
is one technique that people can use it
the Torn advantage you get from a column
store over a row store for doing
analytics again the way just a way to
think about this is we know what the
query plan is ahead of time because it's
sequel we know exactly what we're
executing we know what actually so we're
going to need and at the lowest level or
in our joint operator we can make
decisions about what we actually need to
maintain or produce from one Operator to
the next and no matter when we do our
joins because when we do a hash doing
we're going to populate a hash table and
then we don't want our hash table to get
too big because we're gonna run out of
memory so
we want to be we know just have the
minimum amount on information we need
inside our hash table to compute the
join and not a not weigh space oh crap
so now when we start talking about these
different joint algorithms the method
we're going to use to determine whether
one album is better than another
determine what the cost is is going to
be strictly based on disk i/o right as
we said in in this class going to disk
as always the most expensive thing so
when we you know we always want to
determine you know make choices about
our algorithms based on how much how
much we're gonna read and write from
disk once everything's in memory then
then you know the cost changes what the
cost metric we should use changes like
cache misses and other things like that
but for our purposes here the disk is
always the slowest thing so that's what
I mean that's what we're going to be
worried about so we're gonna use this
join query here as a running example
throughout the lecture and we're going
to say is that we define our cost
functions or cost formulas for these
Joran algorithms in terms of the number
of pages and tuples and in these two
tables so we're gonna say that those m
pages in table R and in total table or
has and lowercase M tuples and the N
pages and s and lowercase and tuples and
in that in that table as well so for
this class although I just talked about
the output of these joint operators
we're gonna ignore the cost of
outputting the the joint of the join up
operation in our calculations because
that depends on what the data looks like
and what your query is right we could
have a billion two blows fed as the
input into our joint operator but then
it only produces 1 1 1 2 plus is output
right and we don't know because we don't
know what the actual data is we're
trying to do this at our asymptotic
analysis at a high level this is also
the output the cost of producing the
output is gonna be the same from one
algorithm to the next like if I used a
nested loop joint and it produces the
billion 2 plus as output the same joint
algorithm sorry this the same joint
using a hash joint algorithm will
produce the same number of tuples
so therefore the output cost would be
the same there so we can ignore that
cost that is gonna be the same no matter
what
album we use so we also again don't know
we just get as I said we don't know how
much tuple how many people's were gonna
prove citrus output but we'll know this
we'll figure out well learn how to
compute this
on Monday next week when we talk about
query optimization well look top we have
derived for sistex from our tables and
use that to estimate the number of
tuples that we're going to use as input
an output for our our different
operators in the query planner so the
last thing to mention also too is that
as I said the beginning we're focused in
this class on the cost analysis of
equi-join
or inner joins between two tables
because again this is going to be the
most the most widely used joint
algorithm we're gonna have in our system
most queries are gonna actually execute
like this and we don't really care about
things like cross product because
there's not really any way to make those
things go faster right cross product is
just to for loops to combine all
possible you know tuples you create all
possible pairs of tuples in our two
tables so there's there's nothing really
we can do to make that go faster we're
in in our inner joins or Ecuadorians we
can be bit more careful how we staged
our data and and do better than sort of
the then that naive approach so we're
also not gonna talk about left outer
joins or sort of outer joins in general
we're focused on inner joins
I'll talk all about this when we talk
about sort merge because you'll see how
you can easily do left outer joins or
sort of outer joins the the basic
algorithms are the same you just maybe
do some extra strap like backtracking or
check a little bit more data than then
you wouldn't otherwise if you're doing
an inner join for all our algorithms can
we focus on inner joins with with
equi-join predicates alright so at a
high level there's three classes of join
algorithms there's nested loop join sort
merge join and hash join so we're gonna
spend most of our time at the end
talking on hash join but it's good to
understand these other joins because
there may be different scenarios where
you may want to use one versus another
for example the index nested loop join
is what you're almost always going to
want to use for all TP workloads because
you're gonna have an index available for
you all right I'll say in general that
the main spoiler that hash join it's
always gonna be fastest and we'll see
how to make it perform well
as we go along right so the most basic
join algorithm is called the the simple
nested loop join and I'm putting a
little slow marker here just to say that
again this is like the dumbest thing you
can do but it will produce the right
output so it's exactly as it sounds the
next loop join is comprised of two
nested for-loops so the first for loop
iterates over one table and for every
tuple in that table we're gonna iterate
over the second table and we check to
see whether the tuples match our joined
predicate and if so then we omit them as
our output and so the and the parlance
we're gonna use in describing all our
joint algorithms are the ideas of outer
outer versus inner table so it's exactly
as it looks so the outer for loop will
be iterating over the outer table and
then the inner for loop iterates over
the inner table so I'll use the inner
tape I'll use inner and outer table
multiple times throughout the lecture
and this is just just what it means so
why is this algorithm bad right sort of
obvious right for every single to but
we're gonna have in our our table are
we're gonna scan the entire inner table
from beginning to end all over again so
if you now compute the cost of this in
terms of pages it's gonna be m Big M
plus little m times n right so we had to
scan the outer table once we have it has
m pages so that's what that cost is and
then for every single tuple in the outer
table of which there's little case M of
M we're going to scan every single page
in in the outer table right so when you
actually now put numbers into this to
say we have our database has thousand
pages in the outer table with a hundred
thousand tuples and 500 pages and the
inner table with forty thousand tuples
when you run this formula with these
numbers you can see that for just doing
the simple nested loop join on these two
tables produces 50 million iOS and
assuming you have like even a fast SSD
where it's one tenth of a millisecond
per IO
then compute this join it takes one
point three hours right look that's
that's pretty bad right it's pretty slow
so what's one thing we could do to make
this go faster just just this algorithm
what's not what's a simple thing we can
do
what's that I thought somebody said swap
excellent yes perfect yes so as I said
in the beginning you always want to try
to make the smaller table be the outer
table so if we do that right table asks
is smaller than the table are so we use
s as the outer table now your your iOS
get down to 40 million and your total
time is still 1,1 hours yes why say say
it again sorry yeah sorry move that over
right one thank you you know squared
listen stick sit down actually no I
don't break this but yes just move it
over by one sorry it doesn't change it
though it's still gonna be our right so
right so we even if we swap the the
inner table with the outer table we're
still doing pretty crappy here right
because again we're doing the dumbest
thing we're ignoring the fact that we
actually can pack multiple tuples in a
single page we know this because you
guys put your own buffle manager so you
can have multiple tuples per page so in
this case is algorithm you're assuming
that for every single tuple it can be a
page fetch to go get that that tuple
right and so what you really want is
sort of a buffer or a page nested loop
join the textbook call is that a block
nested loop join the basic same idea
where now we're just going to iterate
over every single block in the outer
table and every single block in the
inner table and then within the page the
tuples within those two blocks or two
pages where then do our comparison right
so now in this case scenario now we have
or nested loops put together but it's
still you know sir you know there's at a
high level we're just iterating over the
outer table and is iterating over an
inner table but we're doing this on a
per block basis so now if we go back to
our formula instead of having little m
on on the inner part and for the inner
table now we have big out all right so
this is this is a little bit better but
still not great and of course as I said
the smaller one is always we're going to
want to put as the outer table so in
this case here it's the one with the
smaller number of pages not the smallest
number of tuples alright so again do our
formula now I got the thousand correct
okay so now if we do this and Big M plus
Big M times begin now we're doing five
hundred thousand iOS and we can computer
join at 50 seconds on a fast SSD right
this is better but we can still do
better than this right this is in this
case here we're assuming that we only
have three blocks or three buffer pages
we can use right we have one for the
outer table one for the inner table and
then one for our output right you always
need one for the output so if we have
multiple pages multiple buffers
available then we can use B minus two
pages to do the scan the outer table and
we have one page for the inner table and
then one page for our output all right
and now again the album basically looks
the same it's just now we have B minus
two pages for doing that for the topmost
for loop again now we're taking the pin
of the fact that we have a wonderful
manager that can provide us with some
extra space where we actually can start
paging in tuples or pages from our from
our table and try to read as much as we
can while it's in memory so now we use
this the fact that we have B minus two
pages for the outer table in our formula
we end up with this this cost we say Big
M plus the ceiling of M divided by B
minus two times n right if the entire
two tables so if the outer table v
entirely main memory right where b is
greater than n plus two because again we
always need two pages for the inner and
outer now we can get this down to 1,500
iOS right you still have to scan you get
to scan the entire outer table put
everything memory but now we for now you
just then just scan the inner table all
right so it's M plus n so now you can
now we're cuttings down quite a lot but
of course we saw this before when we
talked about sequential flooding this
assumes that no other query is running
but you don't care about throwing away
anything else in your in your in your
buffer pool this assumes that you can
dedicate all the Davises memory to
actually just your one query which may
or may not be the right thing depending
on on your workload so again these both
in all these examples the block nest
look joint of a simple nest Lutron at
the end of the day they're just
sequential scans right you're just
scanning through every sink tube or
every single block and just doing your
comparison that way there may be a
scenario though if we have a index
available to us right sequential Tina
sucks right we know it sucks and as we
said it's pressure on the buffer pool
memory manager that that may be taking
them away from other parts of the system
so if we have an index available to us
which is often the case if you have
foreign keys then we can use that index
to define matches and our inner table
right instead of actually doing this
crunch will scan on the inner table we
just probe the index to find the the the
one or the the small number of tuples
that we want and then we just do our
join for that so best-case scenario we
have anacs-- available to us if not we
can try and maybe build one on the fly
which is essentially what a hashed one
is doing I don't know of any system
actually well build a people stream
table on the fly everyone just does the
hash table but again at the high/low
it's the same idea so now our our four
loops look like this so for every single
tuple in the end the outer table we're
gonna against can do a probe in our
index or assuming they have an index on
a
some attributes some subset of Beatrix
for our joint King and then if we have a
match from an index then we omit them as
our output so what I'm showing here the
reason why you do the index probe then
still check to see whether they match
again because the index may only have
say the say our join key our joined is
on three attributes the index may only
have the first two so we'll go find the
matches then we go fetch the tuple then
go check to see whether the other key
matches are doing so for this the the
cost of the index probe we're going to
say is some constant C all right because
this depends on what the data structure
is depends on what the index looks like
depends on whether the thing is in
memory or not right we just say it's
some some fixed costs that'll be the
same for every single tuple we know the
case of a B plus tree it's log n we know
in the case of a hash table in best case
scenario it's a 1 right so again we just
say we just say it's C so now our cost
is going to be M big m for scanning
every single tuple in the outer table
which is unavoidable and then for every
single tuple in the outer table we do we
do one probe sorry it's it's the cost of
scanning every single page in the outer
table and then for every single tuple in
the outer table we're doing at least
we're doing exactly one probe into into
our index to find our matches so that's
why the formula comes out like this
right
so in nested loop join super simple to
understand you always try to pick the
smaller table as the outer as the outer
table and then you just do you know do a
central scan over the outer table and
you have to do is scrunch will scan or
index probe on the inner table anyone
try to put as much as the outer table in
memory as possible to be to reuse that
that data as your as you're doing your
scan on the on the inner table and if
you have an index on the inner table
then then that's great and she
definitely use that and David says my
optimizer try to try to always pick the
index
all right so any questions about about
Nestle loop join again it's the first
loop this is the first joint album and
everyone pretty much implements when
they may build a database system the
first time because it's the easiest one
Mabel man okay the next Casa joint
algorithms is called the sort merge join
so I think your textbook calls this
merge join I other textbooks call it
sort merge join they mean the same thing
and was sort of confusing about this is
like in the sort merge join you can use
the external merge sort algorithm to
sort your table so we talked about last
time
all right so but again they're all the
same so there's two phases so in the
first phase we're gonna sort both the
the inner and the outer table based on
the join keys and then when that's done
then we're gonna have these were
established these cursors at the
beginning of the two tables at the top
and then they're gonna walk down sort of
in in a proper order and doing
comparisons or wherever the cursor is
pointing at and to see whether we have a
match and begin the idea high-level idea
about this is that because we're sorting
things ahead of time when now we start
scanning the table with our cursor we
know that as the cursor moves down
because it's in sort of order we never
have to go back and look at previous
values we've examined before because we
know we know everything at that point is
is where every cursor is pointing at
everything below it or sorry everything
back above it is less or greater than
based on how you sort of it then what
we're looking at now so we never have to
go look at things we've looked at before
I'll show example what I mean by in the
second and again for the sort phase you
can use quicksort you can use heap sort
or you can use the external more sort
algorithm we talked at last class so
roughly the algorithm for the immerser
the sort merge-join looks like this so
in the first page you just sort the two
tables based on the join keys we know
how to do that from last class and then
you have these cursors on the sort of
tables that they're just going to scan
through the the two tables until either
one of them reaches the end and at the
at each age step it reached sort of
iteration through the wild up here if
the outer tapers cursor is greater than
the inner tables cursor then you
increment the inner tables cursor if the
outer tables cursor is less than the
inner tables cursor then you increment
the counter tables cursor otherwise you
check to see whether you have a match
and if so then you produce that as your
output from the join table the join
tuple and then you increment the the the
the inner tables cursor by one so again
the algorithm might be difficult to
follow up but let's look at this
visually again so these are the two
tables we want to sort for this for this
join query here so in the first phase we
do our sorting or do our sort on the on
the join key okay so this is just
running extra merge sort of quick sort
whatever you want and then we produce
our new tuples like this and then we
have two cursors start that at the top
of each of the two tables and they're
gonna again go down in in in step one by
one and do comparisons across with each
other to see whether we have a match so
in the very first step we're gonna check
to see whether and the outer tables
cursor the values pointing is the cursor
is pointing at in value of 100 the inner
tables cursor is pointing in value 100
these two are equal therefore we know we
have a match and we produce a tuple as
our output because we have a match then
we now increment the inner tables cursor
by 1 and do another comparison again we
don't move the outer table cursor here
so again now 100 equals 100 so we know
we have a match we produce our tuple in
the output table and then we increment
the inner tables cursor so now this
point we're comparing 1 100 and 200 but
since 200 is greater than 100 we know we
need to now move the outer tables cursor
by 1 and this is sort of I was saying
that we never have to backtrack so at
this point here we don't have a match
100 is not equal 200 so we know that for
the inner tables cursor we've already
looked at everything that comes before
it so now when we increment in here now
to 200 we never need to go back and look
at anything that we seen before because
it's good that everything's gonna be
less than whatever that cursor is
pointing at
so everything's gonna be less than 200
so we know there's nothing that we ever
need to compare again so I really only
have potentially examine the cursor only
looks at each tuple once it make them do
multiple persons with the tuple that
it's looking at but it never goes back
on local books to the other ones so now
we have 200 equals 200 we produce our
output we increment the inner tables
cursor now we have 200 not does not is
not equal to 400 and 200 is less than
400 so we increment the outer tables
cursor by 1 300 is less than 400 to be
incremented again and then now 400
equals 400 so we produce it with an
output increment the inner table and now
400 is equal 500 increment the outer
table 500 equals 500 we produce our
output so what happens next what happens
here what's that well he's just effect
let's say assuming this is this is this
is the entire table right he's right
this is it we're done right because we
reached the end of the inner table so it
doesn't matter that there's some some
more tuples here right
this thing will increment to nothing so
we know that there's there's nothing
else we could possibly look at because
again we don't backtrack so it doesn't
matter that we have a match here what
doesn't matter that these guys still
exist we don't care yes so he says those
two you can still match with the yes
right yes forgot about that yeah he's
right okay so this is technically wrong
so if this was 500 then this thing would
would go down and you have to increment
this one down not this one yeah so it's
letting me off if they deal with that
case yes
he's racing it was ID is a primary key
it's not b12 in this case here yeah it
is this is the primary key or it's a
unique key at least so yeah I'm getting
the cardinality so this is n 2 1 so
there's multiple tuples here from one
tuple here so if you know that then you
know that if you reach the end of this
you'll never have any other match
because you've already matched
everything right if it's end-to-end then
you would have to go to the very bottom
of this one here yeah that's the corner
case I forgot to discuss thank you
I'll fix that yes so you're back here
yeah so yeah it's question is say if
this was actually 100 not 200 right if
you if it's end and then yeah in this
case you would have to backtrack so you
have to know that all right you have to
know that all right in the value I'm
looking at this is 100 where did I stop
at same thing like where's the what's
the how far'd I have to go back to reset
to the current value so you have to say
all right there's 100 100 so I know that
if I have to reset I have to start back
up here same thing on here I like the
reset I come back it up it here so for
the basically would way work is on the
outer table for every single tuple sorry
you never backtrack on the outer table
you always backtrack on the inner table
so if I start at the outer table 100 100
I'm ash that next guy's 100 100 that
matches and then I go down to 200 and I
come down increment this by 1 and now
I'm at 100 again I have to know I have
to go back on the inner table to start
100 again and scan down again so this
Maxima meditative to maintain if you
have if you're doing end-to-end joints
but at a high level the cost is no worst
case scenario they're exactly the same
then it's just 2
scans over and over again but we'll keep
it simple eyes ever clear what I was
saying there right in this example here
we never the backtrack because we know
it's a one end joint so for every one
tuple on this table there can be
multiple tuples on this table but not
vice versa
so as we scan down we never have the
backtrack if it's n - n then you had the
backtrack on the on the inner table -
you know as you go down on the outer
table but you instead of having to
include sometimes we'll scan every
single time you can just can only
backtrack to the point where you just
you know the values that you need to do
your compare something start okay and
then get some weird you know the cost
analysis can get weird because you know
if you're if you're backtracking across
page boundaries then you're fetching in
pages again and again we're keeping
simple ignoring that all right so the
cost for this right we have the sort
cost of the outer table the surplus or
inner table and that's just the formula
we had from last class when we talked
about concerning a merge sort and then
we have our merge cost and get best case
scenario it's just going to scan on the
outer table and switch gain on the inner
table n plus n so the total cost of
these is just the combination of these
two formulas so again using our example
database and now say we have a hundred
buffer pages to do to our joins sorry do
our sorts for both R and s that means we
can sort them in just two passes so the
cost of sorting R is 3000 the cost of
sorting s is 1350 the merge cost is just
1500 so the total cost of the merge plus
sorry this sort plus the merge is 5,800
and that roughly comes out to be 59
seconds if you're doing this on an SSD
so we're getting a little bit better
right we were I forget we were had
before with the with with the other
joins but it was a roughly around a
second so now we're getting into sub
second numbers here all right so the the
worst case scenario is sort of example
we briefly talked about aware you have
to do backtracking on on the outer table
so now essentially becomes the
the you you play the cost of sorting but
then all your attributes are the same
for the two tables so you're just doing
for every single page in the outer table
you're doing completes Winchell scan on
the inner table then you backtrack on
the inner table go down to the next page
and do it all over again so in the worst
case scenario for the server's join it
be M times n plus plus your cost all
right so again we'll see this on Monday
next week we talked about query
optimization the database system tries
to maintain internal statistics about
your database about your tables to make
decisions about oh my my distribution my
values is really crappy so therefore I
don't want to do the sort merge drawing
because I know I'm just gonna be waiting
to do wasted i/o because I'm not getting
any benefit of actually sorting I would
say that this case this particular
example is super rare right because
think about what this action would be
there's be two tables that you want to
join where they have one value in this
column and they're exactly the same for
every single tuple I am I don't want say
it never happens because people do
stupid things all the time but like you
know in in you know in a real
application you I don't think you this
is B unlikely all right so when is to
sort merge-join useful well obviously
when the tables are already sorted on
your join key and if you're doing like
an index organized table then you don't
actually have any sort cost because it's
already sorted on the thing you want to
join in anyway so that that's an added
bonus right you cut that into entirely
and it's just then it's just the cost of
two sequential scans also if your if
your query requires the output to be
sorted on your join key then you're
killing two birds with one stone because
now you're do the the join and it'll
it'll produce output that's already
sorted on the thing that that's in your
order by clause so then you don't have
to do any extra sorting for the order by
it's already sorted all right so again
the optimizer the David system can
recognize oh I have an order by Clause
for my join and the order by ascending
I'm joining on so just don't do just do
sort merge and then don't do the order
by and you cut out an operator entirely
entirely from your query plan all right
so again the the the in the output so
the input for these operators could be
either on the Davidson will know I'm
getting data from this from this
operator below me in the tree and I'm
gonna know the physical properties of
that data I'll know whether it's
actually been already sorted or not so
uses that in its determination to decide
whether it wants to do assert merge-join
or another algorithm okay alright so any
questions about sort merge-join
okay so let's notice our time talk my
heroines so they said hash join is the
most portent algorithm this is where
most major analytical databases are
gonna spending most of their time
because in general this always turns out
to be the best so the basic idea is that
it's almost like the index nested loop
join where well how about we'll build a
hash table on the fly and then we use
that to probe the in the inner table to
see whether we have have a match so the
way to think about this and why this
works is that if we have if we're doing
a join on two tuples and their
attributes match alright meaning say
again we're doing equi-join just
something equal something if we men hash
those attributes that we're doing our
joint on the hash will happen produce
the same the hash function will produce
the same hash value as well so if two
values an unhatched form equal are the
same then two values in their hashed
form will have to be the same so we can
rely on this aspect of that to then do
our join so we can just do our join on
the hash attributes rather than the
actual role actors themselves so at a
high level that's essentially what we're
trying to do in a hash joint so we have
two phases so in the in the first phase
we're going to build a hash table on the
outer relation outer table using some
hash mulching it doesn't matter what it
is murmur hash murmur hash city hash
whatever whatever you want to use
and then the second phase is then we
just do a scrunchy scan over it in a
relation and for every single tuple
we're gonna hash the join key attributes
of that tuple with our same hash
function we using the first base and
that'll tell us that'll that'll point us
to some location in our hash table and
we can use that to determine whether we
have a match so just like we don't care
what hash function we use we don't
actually care what what hash table we
use we can use linear hashing cuckoo
hashing Robinhood hashing right it
doesn't matter as long as we can make
sure that we we hash something and it
jumps to a particular spot in our table
and when you find the thing that we're
looking for
so the basic hash showing album again
visually looks like this again the the
algorithm is that you just build a hash
table HTR on the outer table and then
for every single table every single
tuple an inner table you're just gonna
hash it and look up in the hash table to
see whether you have a match so again we
just do a special scan of the outer
table populate HTR and then do a special
scan on the inner table and this probe
inside the hash table to see whether
they have a match right that's it pretty
straightforward same thing almost as
like the index nested loop join except
in the index in this loop join we had
the index on the inner table where in
this case we're building that the hash
table on the outer table alright so what
do we actually put in our hash table
well again the key is just going to be
the attributes that we're doing our
joint on right it has to be it's only
works if you're doing equi-join there
are quality predicates because we want
to know where whether something equals
something if we have an inequality if we
have a less than or greater than
then the hash join doesn't work because
we can't actually do that comparison
with our in the hash table right it
always has to be an exact match and then
what we actually put in the value
portion of the payload of a hash table
can depends on the implementation and it
depends on what the what the output of
the operator should be so you can put
the entire tuple if you want and we said
that we wanted to do this because we'd
avoid having to go back and get more
data so if we build our hash
if we have our joint key piece if we if
we want to make our joint key or the
thing work hashing on be a subset of the
joint keys which you could do if you
wanted to then we still have to maintain
the rest of the joint key inside right
and inside the payload because then we
have to do a valuation inside of that
anyway we have to do that anyway
actually if we hash the entire joint key
or not because we could have collisions
and we have to go and then make sure
that we actually have an exact match the
side side of the hash table this
obviously takes up more space and it may
cause our hash table to overflow and you
know I have long chains or other things
that you know requires to allocate more
pages or we could use the tuple
identifier or the record ID all set that
we talked at the beginning which one do
materialization we said this will be
better for column stores because you're
only reading in data bit you actually
need but you may have to go fetch that
data later on up in the query plan
depending on what what you actually need
so if everything fits in memory then our
hatchling is super fast because we just
ripped through the the outer table that
our hash table then ripped through the
inner table and the hash table entirely
baby there and we just probe inside of
it and find things that we want of
course we said that this is not always
the case of in large databases so we
this is why we have a bubble manager it
allows tomato spill things out the disk
as needed but just like we don't want
the operating system to control what we
swap in and out of memory we actually
don't want the buffalo manager just to
make its own decisions but what's the
swap in and out okay because they may
end up swapping things out we don't want
to as we're doing our joint let me tell
you guys why why is that the case so
what is it about the halberd you are
saying say we put our hash table now
we're doing our probe actually both
those cases on the build side and the
probe side what is the access pattern of
our hat our hashing function looks like
it's random right because you're taking
whatever value have hashing it to some
random location of memory and it's we
can't predict this ahead of time so if
we just let the the the the buffle
manager decide oh I'll just use LRU or
clock decide what what to swap out or
vicked from my buffer pool it may end up
putting out something that the next hash
the next hashman the next key would
actually need
Mart about this and try to stage things
in smaller chunks there we can try to
get everything to fit in memory and we
don't have we don't have this problem of
things thrashing because the buffle
manager is removing things that we
actually need so the out of them we're
gonna use to handle hash joins that are
large in the matter memory that's
available to us is called the grace hash
join so it's called grace hash join
because there was a project in the 1980s
at the University of Tokyo for a
database database machine called grace
and in the the system doesn't exist
anymore and never got commercialized
but the they have a paper at the time
that describes how to do the hash join
I'm going to show you and then for
struggle purposes everyone just calls it
the grace hashed one so the basic idea
is a lot similar to what we saw in the
external merge sort we're going to break
up the in the problem to smaller chunks
that can fit in memory and then we can
do the join on those the chunks that fit
memory and not worry about fetching
other pages that will never ever match
so the basic idea is that instead of
just building a hash table for one sided
we're actually gonna hash the other side
as well and put things in partitions or
buckets and then come back and build
hash tables on just what's in those
buckets so again as I said this is the
picture of from the website I think it's
the only picture I could find online of
the the grace database machine who here
has actually ever heard of the term
database machine before nobody who here
has ever heard the term database
appliance nobody okay so the way to
think about this is a database appliance
it's like instead of the you know is say
I want to set up my sequel or Postgres
what I could do is I could go buy a
machine from supermicro or Dell or EMC
you know set it up load the operating
system then download the David system
software install the David system and
sort of set it up myself right that's
what most people do a database appliance
would be you'd buy a machine already
pre-configured and tuned for your
database you know for whatever Davises
you want to run
and it sort of you know it's sort of
yeah it's been set up for the exact
harbor that you're running it on and so
that way you don't worry about how to
set up how much but purported memory to
use or how much to tune it for the OS
and other things all that's done it's
sort of like a like a battery batteries
included database system where that
comes on its own hardware alright so a
database machine was this this sort of
movement in the 1980s where people would
sort of build like an appliance where
it's sort of like I was a pre-configured
you know one rack unit that would have
Davis isn't pre-installed but they went
a bit farther and they actually had
specialized Hardware on it not FPGA GPUs
there's no custom hardware that was that
the data system could take advantage of
right and this was thought at the time
early 1980s but this was the future of
databases that everyone's gonna have is
these these custom hardware thing
machines that the day says we could
exploit and get much better performance
and he could on commodity hardware all
right of course that didn't pan out
right because with Moore's law always
getting better and better especially in
the 1980s less so now the whatever
advantage you had by the time you
manufactured a database machine that had
specialized hardware to do whatever you
wanted to do so for example a lot of
these systems has specialized hardware
they do hash joins by the time you
actually got that in production you know
Intel came out with a better chip that
could you know outperform whatever you
could act you were doing before I say
these things never really took off least
a customized Hardware database
appliances still exist as a bunch of
different examples here of different
manufacturers that sell stuff so the
first one is IBM selling you you know
z/os machine to run db2 there was a
startup out of San Francisco called
cluster it's selling an appliance of a
tune my sequel or my sequel like
database system and of course Oracle is
probably most famous one they'll sell
you lots of hardware that's that comes
with a system already pre-configured and
running on it like Exadata is you know
hundreds there's accident bring them a
lot of money basically selling these
these appliances so again grace was not
an appliance it was it was the day
today's machine which is an appliance
plus extra stuff of course I mean nobody
nobody still uses this but everyone
still uses the grace hash join so that's
we're going to cover
so I don't know what the textbook calls
this it might call this grace hash
strong and I call it like partition hash
one basic idea is the same
I think Wikipedia might call its grace
hash run all right so as he said on the
regular hash join we would just scan the
outer table builder hash table and then
have the inner table to do a special
scan and just probe inside of that but
here we're trying to do is we're gonna
try to divide up the the outer it's out
on inner tables into buckets that can
fit into memory and then we'll build
hash tables on just those buckets just
build a hash table on the bucket all
right so we do a special scan on the
outer table again we're not building a
hash table actually least not pH to you
this should be buckets so we're gonna
nice the same thing right so it's a hash
table we're doing we're gonna build
buckets same thing on the other side and
then these things can now get swapped
out to disk but the way to think about
this is because again we're using the
same hash function on both sides we know
that it sort of at every level there
will be tuples that will match so
because you know in hash function one we
use puts things in this level here any
tuples over here with the same value
will end up in this level as well now
we'll have collisions therefore we'll
have keys that hash to the same bucket
but that's okay the main idea here is
that at a one level going across we know
that there's nothing in these other ones
that we had to examine to look for a
joint we sort of put everybody in this
in the same location the same level so
now what we do is now we do a just a
simple nested for loop over just the
buckets themselves right we said the hat
the nested loop joined was okay when
everything fit in memory so because
these buckets will put in memory then we
just iterate over to each of them and
check to see whether we have a match
right yes
he's question is is this just reducing
the range of the hash function yes in
some ways yes right yes yes sir in the
regular hash joint without without this
this step you Hashem to you no location
and then if you have a lot of collisions
you're essentially gonna be doing the
same central scan you know whether it's
a linear probing or the chain hash table
you're just doing spectral scan to see
whether you have a match it's so this is
actually do the same thing we're just
hashing both sides it's like a almost
like a divide and conquer kind of
approach hey and let's talk about
parallelization later on but you can
pair easily a paralyzes you can have one
thread do the join across each level and
again the main ideas here is that at
this level here there's nothing in these
other levels we'd have to care about
because the hash function always put us
in the right location all right so
what's potential ones potential problem
with this so this is work this works
great we say that now if our hash table
doesn't fit memory we just do these
buckets potentially swap these out the
disk and then we bring in the buckets
for each level one by one and and do our
four loops but what's the problem with
this potentially exactly what are the
buckets don't fit memory right so the
buckets don't fit memory then you have
to you have to maybe split them up a
more so this is called recursive
partitioning the idea is that again
we're just gonna keep partitioning over
and over again our buckets are smaller
smaller chunks till we get something
about fit memory and then we can do our
simple nested for loop joint so basic
idea here is that if we recognize that
one of our buckets is going to overflow
or get too big then we'll apply another
hash function on it that's not the same
as our first hash function and again
when I say different hash function it's
it's if we use murmur hash for the first
hash function it will use murmur hash
again for the second hash function what
is providing it with a different salt
key right so that it produces a
different distribution of hash hash keys
for the same values right so we're
take out bucket using another hash
function hash it all again and then
spill those out the desk and then now
when we come back and do our join we
just have to recognize that whether we
what level or how deep do we do our
recursive partitioning to determine what
hash function we should be you should be
using to find the matching tuple so
going back to our example here so again
say that we building on the outer table
we first do hashing we still rehash
everything the buckets in the first hash
table and we see that this air inter
bucket here at level one it's it's
overflowing so we're gonna go ahead and
hash it again with another hash function
to split it out even further right and
so the way to now think about in terms
of levels the the first and the last one
are still at the level they were
assigned with when they started but the
inner one here it's now you know 1 Prime
1 double prime 1 triple prime just to
saying that it began at level 1 but then
we applied a second hash function
announcements fill up even further
of course now again you may be thinking
or what happens if that if I have a
second hash function or all the
batteries that here are the same and
everything's gonna hash to the same
thing anyway so can I just you know
would I be stuck an infinite loop again
in that case there's nothing you can do
right so you just have to bite you know
bike the cost of just doing special scan
or start doing it you know the block
nests of loop join to fetch in the pages
one by one right just for this this one
level I mean data systems would
recognize this that if I hash him this
again everybody's the same so I breaking
this up even further doesn't help me
alright so now on the inner table then
we start off taking the first hash
function we split everything up into
into chunks like this right against for
the outer one and that the top one in
the bottom one we know that on the other
side they just got mapped to the same
location with the same hash function but
if we have anything that goes to level
one then we know that we need to split
this again with the second hash function
and and write it out like that
all right so then now when we do our
comparison right we're only comparing
across the same level here right this
sort of like the extendable hash table
or linear hash table we kept track of
what hash function we should use
depending on you know where the split
pointer was or how deep the the the the
local death was for a particular bucket
all right so what's the cost of this
well assuming we have enough buffers
then the cost is the essentially the
three central scans on both tables right
three times n plus n all right because
yeah the partitioning phase you have to
read both table in both tables in and
write them both out so it's to to scan
in one scan in and one write out so it's
2 M plus n then now when you do your
probing phase again it's just a simple
nested loop join like what the block
nested loop join and so it's once
question scan or every page on the outer
table and once question can moment on
the inner table again the idea here is
that for every single page on the inner
table within a level within my buckets I
only have to go look at the pages that
correspond to and the inner table at the
same bucket I don't cook the ones the
ones above me and I'll go to the ones
below me so it's just in two sequential
scans sorry this is a complete central
scan on both the inner and the outer in
the part in the probing page so let's
see now this in terms of cost so again
three times n plus n so 3 times 1500 is
4,500 iOS so we knew now scan on the
fastest is D and 0,45 seconds we're in
the sort merge-join case it was zero
point five nine seconds right so
this is why again the the the hash joint
is always going to be preferred cuz it's
always gonna be I'm sorry this almost
always gonna be faster than the the
servers join in and definitely almost
always faster than the the nested loop
join unless you have an index and you're
only joining a small number of things so
the if the database system knows the
size of the outer table then it can use
the static hash table right we can just
pick a you know linear probing hash
table which is really fast and say well
I know that I'd fit everything without
having complete wraparound with having a
large number of collisions based on what
I think I'm gonna actually get a need so
that's the best-case scenario that's
what data is I'm gonna try to do but the
issue is that this we'll see you next
class you have to estimate how many
tuples do you think you're gonna have as
your input and if you're just getting
the tape the data directly from your
access methods at the bottom of the tree
that may actually you it may not be hard
to actually compute that but if you're
doing a joint after joint after joining
up here join if you get it wrong at the
bottom that you can get really wrong at
the top so you may be under provisioning
or besides your hash table and you may
have to do you know to double the size
if you have too many collisions so this
is you could use you know the dynamic
hash table is like Stanwell hashing on
linear hashing if you don't know the
size but you're as we saw before you're
gonna pay a computational overhead to
maintain to be able to figure out you
know what buckets things should actually
be in in both of those schemes where in
the linear probing you don't have to do
that so most agencies I'm gonna try to
do a static hash table but if you get it
wrong then you know you're paid
apparently up doubling the size it's
really only for internal metadata you
use something like extendable hashing or
linear fashion like your Buffalo
management you guys been doing okay so
any questions about hash tones
pretty simple to understand the again
and from our point of view we really
only care about this guy your cost so
the recursive partitioning approach is
pretty much the only really optimization
we have available to us
we'll see the case in in the advanced
class when we do in memory joins you
start to care about where the data
actually is located like like what CPU
socket or what level in your cache right
for our purposes we don't care about
this to summarize again the cost all
these different algorithms again we said
that using our running example in the
worst case scenario the simpleness loop
join it took one point three hours we do
things and blocks were down to 50
seconds you do the in excess of join I
don't know where I got 20 seconds from
okay said log in you know right it's a
little bit better but then the sort
Maurice join and that and the hash join
is is even less than that this actually
might be wrong I don't know where I got
this from hmm because that shouldn't be
a login
all right I'll fix that later okay so
the main takeaway from all this the hash
join is almost always be better than
sorting and unless you know that the
output needs to be sorted or the data
you're feeding into it is already sorted
on what you want the a good database
system we don't have time to open up
Postgres but a good data assessment can
actually support all these different
algorithms and can try to figure out
which one is the best for your
particular workload so Postgres sequel
server oracle all the major data systems
can do sort merge nested loop join and
hashed joins and then on the fly for
each query they figure out what they
want to use and then and the day almost
always comes out to be a hash drawn
unless you have an index already my
sequel I don't know if actually supports
hash joins I thought they did and
someone tell me they did we can check
the documentation again it might be in
the a conversion aid but I don't know so
and then sequel like I said I think
sigil like my only support nested loop
joins okay so next class we're gonna
talk about you know I'm sort of looting
to this all throughout today's today's
lecture was next nights we'll talk about
how this impacts me to decide which
album wants to use per operator and I'll
get even more complicated when we talk
about joins because it's not it's more
than just saying do I want sort merge
versus
- join it's actually making decisions
about what should be the inner table
versus the outer table and how should I
order my my joint operations so a
five-way think about this type of joint
table a B and C together should I join a
and B first or B and C first or in a
later like all these kind of things can
actually make a big difference in
performance and you actually made out
overshadow the benefit you get from
using sort mergers as a hash joint right
right so no class on Wednesday I will
post the the week and then do today by
the 640 it's the real treat with your
drinking by 12 they will make sure
but sane eyes are straight so it really
don't matter