[Music]
they'd be on the jill's Nick today's
lectures now for the second part talking
about data structures and databases and
so originally I had this this this these
two next lecture is titled as order
preserving trees and I decided to rename
them as tree indexes because we're
looking to focus on today is using these
these these trees as indexes although we
can use them in in other parts like we
talked about before our primary focus is
gonna be tree indexes so this is the
same slide I showed last time when we
started talking on hash tables and we
want to talk about what are the
different parts of the database system
we can use hash tables with right so we
said it was internal metadata right you
guys are doing this in your for your
buffer pool project you have to build a
page table to map pages to frames right
that's being done as a hash table so
that's an example of an internal data
structure used for metadata we can use
this for the core storage of the system
so you can use a tree or a hash table as
the actual place where you store tuples
rights instead of having like the the
like in the hash table example we had a
key mapped to a value and the value
would be like a pointer to a tuple
instead of having the pointer we just
store the entire tuple inside of the
bucket in our hash table and we can do
the same thing in trees we can use them
for temporary data structures so when
we're when we're doing doing running a
query maybe when we want to build a tree
or hash table on the fly just for that
one query populated with the data that
we need then do whatever it is we need
to do to process that query and then
blow the whole thing away right and
that's actually in some cases much
faster than having to do sequential scan
over the table over and over again and
as I said that what we're gonna focus on
today is really using them as as table
indexes right because when you when
you're going to use a B+ tree which
should be primarily we're gonna talk
about today actually the only thing
we're gonna talk about today when you
create an index in your database you're
most almost always going to get a B+
string so we've never really defined
what would it be plus or what an index
actually is most of you probably are you
know from the first homework assignment
doing sequel some basic knowledge of
databases you might know what an index
is but now we can actually formally
define it
so a table index is going to be a
replica if you will in an auxilary data
structure that will contain a subset of
the tables columns and we're gonna
organize them in such a way that it's
gonna make it efficient for us to access
the data at those columns right again
the relational model says that tuples
can be stored pretty much in any
physical form and but for certain
queries having the right physical form
or the right ordering of our columns and
sorting of the data can make things be
more efficient so the what table indexes
are gonna provide for us the easiest
metaphor to think about to understand a
table index would be think of like your
textbook in the class right it has a
couple hundred pages if I want to find
every page where the word B+ tree is is
listed I could just look at every single
page one by one right that's equivalent
of a sequential scan until I find all
the entries that I want or I can go to
the back of the book and there's a
glossary I just find the keyword B+ tree
and then it's gonna give me a list of
the pages that contain that keyword
that's essentially what the index is
gonna do for us it's gonna make us be
more efficient to find data on
particular number of columns so it's
gonna be the database managed systems
job to make sure that the contents of
the table and the contents of the index
are always logically synced and so I'm
using where logically a purpose here
again to say that physically it may not
actually be in sync right we might
delete a key from our index and we don't
actually delete it from the active data
structure just yet but logically when I
write a query against that index or I
look in that index I don't I don't my
application doesn't see it right so it's
the job of the day between a system to
keep these two things in sync so that
you don't have spurious reads like false
negatives false positives or you see
things that you shouldn't see your sheet
or you miss things that should be there
again then the database system is gonna
manage all this for you automatically
underneath the covers sometimes you see
in in some some tutorials for the
primitive or primitive no sequel systems
that don't support sort of England
indexes is the first-class entity our
first-class component of a davia system
you see people writing application code
to maintain a separate table that
the index for you that's the next or
your application and it's up for the
applications job to keep those two
things in sync
all right that's a bad idea she let the
data system do this for us could scan it
can do it much more efficiently it can
know that when things change
what indexes should actually update and
just do it automatically for you so the
we won't talk about this today but well
this will come up later on when we talk
about query optimization of query
planning the it's up for the database
minute system to figure out which is the
best index we're going to use execute
our query so me as the application
programmer I can come along say create
index as much as I want right I can
create redundant indexes I can make
indexes on the same column right just in
different orders the database system
will pretty much let me do whatever I
tell it to do but it may not be a good
idea
right so for actually some queries some
indexes are going to be better than
others and it's up for the database
minute systems query planner or the
optimizer to figure out which index to
use for a particular query so we'll see
this later on right basically what's
gonna happen is that the data's gonna
maintain some additional statistics
about these indexes and it can know
based on what your query wants to do
what indexes has available and it can
try to figure out that's the one I want
to use and if all else fails you just go
back and do a swinter scan on the entire
table like that's always the default
option but we can do better with indexes
so there's this trade-off between having
index on every single thing we could
ever possibly need and versus the not
paying that maintenance overhead or
storage overhead to have every possible
index so again there's there's this
right so as an application designer when
I want to create my database and I
define my indexes I sort of need to be
aware of that indexes aren't free and
we'll see as we go along why they're not
free because you have to maintain them
and how it will discuss today how you
actually maintain them and so the just
because you add indexes doesn't doesn't
mean it's gonna magically make your
application run faster so this idea or
this problem of how to pick the right
indexes free application is an old
problem my advisers advisor actually
wrote one of the first papers on this in
like 1976 he's dead right so people have
been working this for a long time now in
maybe the 2000s
those brings in tools developed they can
automatically pick indexes for you and
the Microsoft and Oracle have this
feature now and their cloud services and
this is something actually we've been
looking at here at CMU and this in the
Davis Assemblyman Building with my
research group so I'm happy to talk
about how to automatically pick indexes
but for our purposes here we in this
lecture will just assume that someone
picked the right indexes for us we don't
we don't care how so today is really
gonna be focusing on B plus trees so
we'll start off with an overview of what
a B plus tree is and we'll do a simple
demo and then we'll go over the some
design decisions you have to think about
going beyond the basic B plus tree which
I talked about here at first and then
we'll finish up with some optimizations
that you can apply to actually that are
used in practice in real systems to make
these things go faster right sort of the
way to think about is the first third is
just to understand what a basic B plus
tree is the second third will be all
right here's actually if you actually
gonna build one one of the things you
need to think about and the last one
would be like alright if I might you
want to make this thing be usable and
fast what are what are some
optimizations I can apply so I'll say
for the for the second project in the
course after the buffer pool you guys
will be building your own B plus tree
and you can get by with just the first
two part of these that the third ones
are nice to have but not not necessary
for correctness okay okay I forgot to
open over the browser that's right okay
so the first thing that sort of address
is the confusing naming of these trees
so that I actually I don't remember the
textbook where their calls and B plus
trees or B trees the there's a class of
data structures called d trees and then
there's a specific data structure called
a B tree so now in 2018 people loosely
refer to B trees what the sort of
canonical definition or like the formal
definition would be is actually a B+
tree so there's a class of data
structures called P trees P plus tree is
one of them but there's also within that
category I got a call to be tree but
people are sort of loosey-goosey with
the term these days so for example you
don't look at Postgres as documentation
or you go look in the code right they
just they discuss their data structure
being a b-tree but from the best like
what I can tell I'm actually looking at
the code it's not a bee tree it's
actually B+ tree right and my sequel
refers to theirs as a B+ tree but I
think sequel server might refer to
theirs as a Petri so the main takeaway
from this is like the whenever anybody
says in a modern database system they
have a be tree they probably have almost
guaranteed to have a really be plus tree
as far as I know nobody actually
implements the real B tree but see more
confusing about this is that there's the
B+ tree defined from the 1970s but the
ones we use today actually borrows some
of these ideas from these other trees
right soon as the B tree the B+ tree
that will cover those but then there's
the B link tree which was event here at
CMU in like 1981 and then there's a B
start reading so the some elements of B
link tree in the modern B+ tree so for
our purposes we'll just safe to B plus
tree and I'll define what it is I think
the textbook which might be bit pedantic
about this as well but again just when
you go see other systems they may say
they have a be tree but they almost
always have a B+ tree
so a B+ tree is a self-balancing tree
data structure so the B in in in B and B
plus tree stands for balanced and what
it's gonna allow us to do is have
efficient searches essential accesses
and insertions and deletions
with all of our operations taking o log
n time where n is the
keys that that were storing right
contrast this with the hash table what
was the hash tables asymptotic
complexity to do a lookup anybody what's
that oh one right hash up it can I jump
to it worst-case scenario it's it's it's
N yeah
so B the the B plus trees can be always
log in and that's that's that's pretty
good that's pretty fast and so the
definition of it is there's actually no
one paper that describes the B plus tree
the one that usually everyone cites is
this is ubiquitous B tree that came out
in as a survey paper in 1979 but this is
actually not where it was invented so
this 1979 paper goes on about how great
B plus trees are our B trees are and how
every single data system is gonna be
using this because this is you know this
is the greatest data structure ever for
relational databases but at this point
here they're talking about how
ubiquitous it is this is only about 6 or
7 years after it was actually invented
so even early when people figured out
that the B plus tree was a really good
idea so in this 1979 paper they refer to
this IBM tech report from like 1973
where they seem to describe what is now
known as a B+ tree today right so again
the main takeaway here is that people
recognize early on that people she was a
really good idea for data business and
even tell even today well I will talk
about this on next class but even in
like modern in-memory databases or even
with really fast SSDs the people Street
actually does almost pretty good pretty
well it's much better actually than any
like modern lock-free data structure
right so the thing that was was super
useful and and and and made b-trees be
widely used back then was that it was
originally designed for running in
hardware where the the sequential access
to data to new reads and writes was much
faster than random access so by
organizing our nodes in these blocks
right the larger the better because you
can read more data with a single seek on
the disk we get much better performance
and this would be better than sort of a
sort of generic binary tree
we'll see in a second so again the main
takeaway here is like even though people
us trees were designed 1970's where the
harbor is much different than what we
have now they're still really awesome
now and very few things actually compete
it so more formally a B+ tree is an M
way search tree where m is the number of
number of keys we can have in a single
node and it's in had the following
properties so the first is that it can
be perfectly balanced meaning every leaf
node every node at the bottom of the
tree will always be the same number of
levels away from the root right so you
won't have a leaf node be two hops and
another one be ten hops they're always
they always have to be the same then
every inner node I wanted to find what
that is in a second but anything that's
not a leaf node essentially is gonna be
either at least half full so again we
can have M keys in a single node so it's
always gonna have either more than half
or up to my max amount and then every
internode if it has K keys will have K
plus 1
null children so every key I have I have
I have to have a pointer to two children
okay so let's look through an example so
this is a really simple three-way B plus
tree so I can have three keys per per
node and the top part is also called the
root but this is an inner node because
it's not not a leaf node the leaf nodes
are at the bottom because they don't
have any children but then I can in
addition to pointers now put from the
inner node to the leaf nodes I can also
have pointers between the the siblings
so again this is an example the original
B plus tree did not have these pointers
the B link tree does but a lot of people
actually implement B plus trees with
these pointers now all right
notice also - there's no pointers going
in the in the opposite direction
there's no pointer from the leaf node to
the the inner node or the parent now
there's nothing about the P plus tree
that says you can't do that but nobody
actually does this because this becomes
more difficult to maintain these
pointers right if you if you have
multiple threads trying to access things
yes
one slide yeah yes so if my note has K
keys then I have to have k plus 1
children so if I so go back here this
top node is Internet the rune it has 2
keys
so it has to have 2 plus 1 children it
has 3 children
right this is to ensure that's balanced
all right scan there's 2 happy sibling
pointers all right and we're gonna use
these along the leaf nodes to do certain
things like that we'll do a range scan
and find all the keys that are greater
than 3
I could use my index get down to leaf
node and then just scan across the the
leaves going from one page to the next
all right again this is what the beep
this is what makes the B plus trees be
really fast because if I without me
sibling pointers I may have to go back
up and try you know go back up traverse
now and I started doing random access
into and to my page table and disk with
a file on disk where if I'm smart about
how I lay out these leaf nodes
I can maybe prefetch a bunch of them
ahead of time because they're all gonna
be contiguous bringing them to my buffer
pool and just rip right across without
having any page faults so now the way
we're gonna do searches in the tree is
through these sort of these like
separator keys in the in the inter note
so the way it works is that for every
for every key again it's going to have
two two pointers to its children one of
the right one on the left and the the
way it works that any bought any key
that is less than the key that's in the
internode you would look for those keys
down to to look to the right side or
your left and any key a greater than the
one next to it you go down to the next
one
right so anything less than 5 you go
down here any key less than 9 you go
down here and then anything greater than
equal to 9 and goes to here so now the
this is where also things get confusing
is like maybe I think I'm following
what's in the textbook but different
textbooks do different things right you
could have this be greater than equal to
5 and then greater equal to 9 here and
then greater than 9 there it doesn't
matter right
there's nothing about the algorithms
that change whatever
[Laughter]
okay
ah
[Laughter]
Oh
[Music]
[Laughter]
you
so
[Laughter]
[Music]
now
Oh
[Laughter]
I
No
Oh
[Laughter]
but
[Music]
[Laughter]
yes
Oh
[Laughter]
[Music]
Oh
[Laughter]
you
happy
right
[Music]
[Laughter]
drinking 12 straight so it really don't
matter