[Music]
maybe sorting an aggregator so this sort
of goes without saying you know it
should be sort of obvious why we need to
sort you know the relational model has
no ordering so so the the user might say
in their sequel query give me an order
by and therefore we have to sort of bow
as I see it as we go along
there me other scenarios where certain
algorithms or operators can be
implemented more efficiently by sorting
even though the user didn't ask us to
sort so you know there was an explicit
order by clause if we sort our tuples as
we're processing them we may end up with
they may provide us an additional
benefits and some of the things we'll be
able to do are things like we're moving
duplicates doing aggregations with group
eyes and then also bulk loading bulk
loading keys into an index so why am I
even bother talk about sorting right
because everyone here is basically
taking CS 101 or whatever the clothing
is at your undergrad institution right
if everything fits in memory we can use
quicksort heapsort merge sort whatever
your favorite sword is and we're done
right there's nothing you know there's
nothing magic and a database system
that'll make one sorting algorithm for
an in-memory workload be better than
another all right the thing that we're
gonna focus on is when a doesn't fit
memory all right that's the thing that
they don't teach you in like in intro CS
class of when you have to spilt a disk
because that's now these certain
algorithms like quicksort for example is
not actually what you're gonna want to
use because quicksort is all about doing
random access assumes everything in
memory so you can swap things and who
cares right if you you know if you
assume there's no i/o
but now in a database system we need to
be mindful of this because we need may
have to spilt a disk so that's all we're
gonna focus on today and so the
particular album we're gonna focus on is
called external merge sort so this is
the most frequently used external
sorting algorithm and every single
database system the may be the exact
naming of the phases or the exact
protocol
our methods for each step may be
different per system but a high level to
all be doing basically the same thing so
it's a sort of hybrid strategy where in
the first phase we're gonna sort the
sort our input sequence of keys into
small sort of runs that can fit in
memory and then we may spill in the disk
because we may not not have enough space
and then in the merge base we start
combining these sort of runs into
progressively larger and larger file
sizes that skin could get spilled to
disk and at some point we repeat this
merging process until we have the entire
sequence sorted right again think of
like where we talked about before in
that the the database system is gonna
try to maximize the amount of scrunch
will access it can do to read and write
data because you know it's assumed that
sequential access is much faster on a
disk store system so the algorithms
gonna favor doing schedule access doing
versus random writes which is what the
quicksort would actually we do so we're
to start off talking about the the
simple example of what's called a to
wage two-way merge sort so to a would
mean there's two sort of runs we're
going to merge together so well later
generalize this to okay way schirmer's
or B we can merge K different runs
together but it's easier to start off
with just two so we're going to do is we
say our file or key sequence the things
we want to sort will be stored broken up
into n pages and that we're gonna
restrict the database system to only
have B number of fixed size buffers that
it can use to store store these sorted
pages so again think about the reputable
assignment you guys built you can't
store everything in your buffer would
you run out of space so you want to
restrict how much memory you're allowing
the system to do to do these sorting so
that it doesn't blow away the buffer
flow every single time you need to do a
sort so the high-level algum looks like
this so in past zero we're just going to
scan through all our pages every B pages
into memory and for each page we're
going to sort them just just that page
just the values in that page and we're
gonna write that out the disk right and
so these sorted pages like what we call
it runs or sort of runs so at first the
size of the of the that's the first pass
the size of the runs will be one page
because I took a page into memory did
quicksort the sort that then wrote it
out then in the subsequent passes we're
going to go back and were to recursively
merge pairs of sort of runs together
doesn't matter which which ones we we're
gonna pick right you can try to be
intelligent and we'll see an example but
in practice I don't think nobody
actually does this and we're gonna merge
them together and produce a new sort of
run that's twice as big as the input
runs that we merge together and then we
keep doing this until we know the whole
thing is sort of so for this algorithm
we're only going to need three buffer
pool pages we need one page two pages
for the input for our two runs and then
one page for the output because we have
to always write it out so again at a
high level sort of looks like this say
that we have our database on disk and we
have two two pages and they're unsorted
when I fetch the first page store it
write it back out the disk fetch the
next page sort it write it out the disk
and then we'll fetch the two pages
together and then write the first you
know combine the first combine the two
together to make a new page then combine
the second page two together and make
the second page write the high/low this
is what we're doing so it's a this is
considered a divide-and-conquer strategy
right because what we're doing is rather
than trying to merge sort everything
which is what quicksort do want to do
order some more sort smaller chunks and
then we're gonna combine it together as
we go along and being smart about how we
read and ready data it up is our input
sequence I mean a little marker here at
the end they say we have the end of file
so in the first pass we're just gonna
take each page and just run quicksort on
it and sort that and then write each of
those pages out then in the second pass
we take two adjacent pages combine them
together
and then write those out so again what
I'm saying before the we're not we don't
need to be smart and say like oh well I
know that this one starts to the three
and this one starts for the one so maybe
I want to merge these two guys together
you don't have to do that I don't know
if anybody actually does that and
practice the algorithm just works okay
as it is you can say all right just
these two guys are nexted together I'm
just gonna merge them together all right
and what will happen is the reason why
you we only need three pages to do this
is because as I as I say it start with
these two guys here as I'm scanning them
I just do a you know a comparison versus
wherever my cursor is in the first page
where my cursor is in the second page
and then whatever one is is less gets
written out and then that cursor moves
down and I never have to backtrack all
right so I never have maybe scanned down
one page and then had to go back and
fetch it again as I'm doing my
comparisons and my cursors are moving
down and I'm writing those pages out I'd
never have to go back so I only need two
pages or two pages for input one page
for output and at the the page I'm
running or is my output it gets to its
you know is full then that gets written
out the disk and I just start start a
new page continue down the third past
same thing we could bind them again and
then we get down to the bottom here and
we have our completely sorted sorted
sequence so for the two way merge sort
the the algorithm for determining the
number passes we're gonna need to do is
one plus this the ceiling of log to n so
the total IO cost the number page you
get the read and write compute this
algorithm to this this sort of sequence
it's 2 n times n of our passes right for
each pass we gotta do one for every page
we add weight to read it in and write it
out so that's why it's 2 n the first n
is for the read for the second animal is
for the right and we do this times a
number of passes that we have pretty
straightforward right yes
this question is what happens to
intermediate pages so say you're like
here and I I combine these two guys and
I sort them like again think of it like
it you have a cursor here and a cursor
there and they're saying all right
what's what's the first two keys I want
to compare across these two runs so this
one would be 2 and this one would be 4 2
is less than 4
so I write that out to my output page
then the cursor moves down by one so
then I compare 3 and 4
well 3 is less than 4 so 3 gets written
out and that cursor moves down now we
get for 4 and then you flip a coin to be
one or the other doesn't matter so
you're sort of you're populating one
output page at a time and then when it's
full it gets written out the disk and
you just start with a new fresh page and
then you can you maintain some internal
metadata to say all right for this
sorted run page one two three and four
it can be found here all right going
that sequence they may not may not be
contiguous in memory but all right so
own disk but in practice you would want
them to be yes where's the what sorry so
where's that one come from
oh there's number of passes because you
always think you always need the first
pass you always have to go through at
once that's unavoidable right like it
and this is just dividing it by you know
you're having the having the number of
sort of runs you have as you go down so
you need one one pass as always to go
through it first time question here no
okay all right so again this particular
album only requires three buffer pages
it turns out if you have more than three
buffer pages you actually not going to
get a good performance because you're
not gonna effectively be utilizing them
so I don't go into details of the the
general merge sort algorithm other than
to say that the peers what the math
looks like the basic idea is that you
instead of computing the the number of
passes based on
to you you base it on the number of runs
that you have now such of what you're
doing is for every single pass instead
of merging just tooth and runs together
now you're merging K runs together and
the algorithm says works the same way
every run you're combining together you
have a cursor you do comparison across
all of them and then which when everyone
is the smallest that gets put in the
output buffer and you move that cursor
down by one and so in general the the
formula for determining the number
passes you have to do is one plus the
ceiling of log B B minus 1 and the
ceiling over B and the total cost of
that again it's two times and rep asses
that's always gonna be the same okay
again this is almost a plug and chug
kind of thing doing a civil example I'm
not gonna go through all icky all of
this but this this will just walk you
through how the math works out okay and
I think there's a homework that it
basically does the same thing okay so we
can actually use B trees to speed things
up but we have the same distinction that
we have before whether you have a
clustered index or a none clustered
index the in general if you need to do
sorting and you have a B+ tree available
to you that is that is indexed on the
key you want to sort by then the every
dataset is always gonna try to use that
instead of doing the the external merge
sort right because the way you think
about this you're paying an upfront cost
of maintaining the indexes Internode's
to mate to sort of baked into the index
the the sort order along the leaf nodes
you're already paying that cost to
maintain that sort ordering in the index
and so that's why it's gonna be faster
to use that instead of instead of
actually computing the the sort order on
the fly with external merge sort so in
general the optimizer is gonna be smart
enough to recognize oh I have an index
on the thing I want to order by let me
use that instead of actually doing the
they were doing the merge sort manually
but again they can only do this if you
have a clustered index so this is what
we talked about before right so if the
if the records we need to read are
sorted in the order that are specified
by the index then we just jump to where
we need to based on the leaf page and
just scan across and we're good to go we
know the output is already sorted in the
order that we want alright there's not
there's no extra step we have to do in
the case of the on clustered B+ treating
like a secondary index like these sort
ordering is all over the map so we may
not doing more i/o you know then we
would have it we just did our external
merge sort so these kind of forms that
I'm showing here this is essentially
what the query optimizer is gonna do in
the database system it's gonna recognize
oh I have an index but it might might
it's it's uncluttered and I have this
amount of memory I can use from to my
sorting it can use that to make
trade-off decisions about whether it's
better to do the index scan on the
uncluttered index or just do the
external merge sort and this is the
beauty of sequel or declarative
languages this is not something you as
the programmer have to know about the
system just does it for you
automatically it's not gonna always get
it right but in general its me better
than what any human can do right so in
this example here we talked about how to
when we talked about the query
processing stuff how if I could
recognize that oh I'm gonna fetch these
pages these tuples need different pages
maybe sort them by their page ID so I'm
having you know reusing every page I
fetch fetch in but if you do that now
you ruined the the sort order
so you defecating at the maintain some
an extra metadata to put it all back in
the correct order when you're done and
at that point you might just be again
better off just doing the external merge
sort
alright so now we know how to sort what
can we do with it right obviously again
order by is easy if the user asks for
that we have to sort it so we can use
that algorithm but we can use it for
aggregations as well so how would you
use it for the aggregation it's pretty
straightforward right so say I'm doing a
distinct on the course ID here if it is
query so the query plan would first go
do a central scan on the table apply the
filter on that's in the where clause
then do a projection to remove any
column so we don't want and then now do
our sorting
to sort the keys that they want in the
output and now we just have a cursor
walk through this sort of output and
maintain the little buffer that says
what's the last value that I looked at
so that if I come across a value that
I've seen before then I know it's a
duplicate and I can just skip it and not
include it in my output here so this is
advantage again this is another example
of where sorting can be used for
something not just for order by queries
you can do it for - making eternal
operations go much much more quickly so
this is pretty common a bunch of systems
will actually support this but actually
the most common way to do aggregations
is to do hashing so if you don't care
about things being ordered then running
maybe the external merge sort algorithm
that would be just too expensive and a
cheaper thing to do is actually just do
hashing so we can use the hash table
stuff we talked about before and use
that to compute our aggregations so way
to think about this is like say in this
example here if I had an order by clause
on course ID then it'd be a no brainer
to do sorting for this because I need to
get it sorted anyway and I can just
reuse the sort order to then eliminate
the duplicates but if I don't care about
about sorting then I may want to use
hashing right hashing hashing is gonna
be is gonna add some randomness to our
output because every time we hash a key
and put it into a hash table you know
you remove all sense of ordering that
that from-from the data that it came
from so we don't care about the sort
ordering then hashing is always almost
always gonna be superior so the way
we're going to compute aggregates with
hashing is that we're gonna populate
this ephemeral hash table this in memory
hash deferred or not in memory I'm a
populate this hash table if it only
lives for the execution of that query
memory talked about data structures
earlier we said that can be used in
different ways used for table indexes
you user metadata and using transient
data structures so this is an example of
a transient data structure for our one
query we're gonna build a hash table
populate it compute our aggregate and
then throw it away and every we exit the
same query over and again we're gonna
rebuild that hash table every single
time
so we built we're gonna pop it in this
hash table and then depending on what
the aggregation we're trying to compute
we'll do different things with what the
value is restoring in the buckets so
we're doing distinct we see it we have a
match
duplicate we just throw away ignore the
weather we just put it put in we're
trying to do a group by with an
aggregation function then we can
summarize the value on the fly as we go
so again just like in sorting if
everything fits in memory then we can
use any of the hash table as we talked
about before and we're done
right the the linear leaner probational
hashing the cuckoo hashing all those
were in memory data structures so if our
data set fits in memory then we're we're
fine we're easy but it's a really large
data set that's not gonna fit in memory
then we need to be smarter just like in
the sorting case so the hashing
aggregate it's gonna have a two phases
first days we're going to partition the
tuples into buckets right there's out
the disk and in the second phase we're
gonna bring those buckets back in and
then populate an a memory hash table for
just that partition or just that bucket
and then compute whatever it is the
aggregate that we want all right again
we have to split a disk we have to do
this if we're in memory then we don't so
in the first phase when user we use one
hash function it doesn't matter what it
is remember hash a CD hash doesn't
matter and then we're gonna do our scan
or input tuples and then whatever key we
want I'm going to group by we hash that
and that tells us what partition that
we're gonna write into out on disk so
we're not writing into a hash table at
this point we're just writing into
output buffers that get written out the
disk so the idea here is by pre
partitioning is that we know that when
we come back and read things back into
memory it's computer to computer
aggregation there's never gonna be a
time where we have to go get data from
another partition to compute the
aggregate because everyone's gonna get
put into the same same location that
that had the same values so to go to our
example here right
same queries before we do our filter we
do remove the columns and then now at
this point here we're gonna go scan
through these values take our hash
function apply it and then write out
whatever the batteries are
to our buckets Here I am be a little
smart and recognize that actually in
this case here you for 4:45 there should
be duplicates you're not doing anything
smart here just taking the values just
writing them out because it may be the
case again if I have a billion tuples I
may not you know the first tuple that
goes in this bucket maybe fifteen four
forty five and then a thousand tuples
later I see another fifteen for forty
five that want to write out but I don't
know about the other one because I'm not
maintaining any metadata about what I've
seen in the past to make decisions about
what the filter out so all these buckets
now get written out right and they sort
of grouped together in partitions and
then for each of these partitions we're
gonna bring it back into memory and
we're gonna build an in-memory hash
table it can be any whatever your
favorite hash table is by extendable
linear kuku doesn't matter and then
we're to use another hash function to
hash it into the hash table and then do
whatever operation we need to do based
on what our aggregation is right if it's
a distinct we filter out duplicates if
it's a group by aggregation function
then we compute that so this we're gonna
assume that the partitions as we bring
them in will fit in memory it's not
always the case either but we'll see how
to handle that when we talk about hash
joins next class so for the way to think
about this is we're assuming that our
input data doesn't fit memory but as we
partition it then each partition will
fit in memory and is obviously assumes
that we have a uniform distribution
after hashing which is not always true
either but for simplicity we just assume
this is the case so here we're back now
in phase two these are the partitions
that we generated from the last time and
for simplicity we're just gonna combine
them into a single hash function like
this right and the Hat the keys or is
the hash keys and then since we're doing
distinct we're just maintaining the
values inside of it the hash table so as
we're scanning along if we see that we
have a duplicate alright we can just
throw it away and then the final result
we need to produce for the query it's
just the values that are stored in the
hash table itself right so again what
would happen is as we go along this
phase we hash fifteen fourteen forty
five we see that there's already a tuple
here with the same value we can just
discard it so we're doing a linear scan
inside the value list for it for that
particular key
which we know how to do crash tables for
summarization the idea is that you can
maintain a running total as you go along
and store that as as your as your value
in your hash table rather than just the
existence of the key so again the idea
is that in the second phase and when I
rehash if I do my hashing and I see that
I do a hash on the grip key I land to a
bucket and I find the entry that
corresponds to my group I key and then I
just do whatever operations need to do
to update the total for that that
function so again the same would go back
to this query a different query we're
doing a join on student enrolled and
we're getting the average GPA of the
students in the course ID for each
course ID so now when I in the rehash
phase when I build my hash table in the
value list I'm gonna have a mapping from
the group by key because we're grouping
by a course ID to some running total we
have to do to compute the function so
the the table sort of looks like this
what you actually need to maintain so if
you're doing average it's a pair of
count and some because at the end you
just take the sum divided by the count
and that gives you the average from
min/max it's sort of obvious to maintain
the largest value you've seen for exam
is just adding adding it to it count
just adding one so this is how the day's
gonna maintain inside the hash table the
aggregation function as it goes along
and then as it scans through each of
these and populates bits and then when
it's done that's the answer that it
produces as the final output so is this
clear right again pretty straightforward
but it's kind of cool that we're
building on the crap we did before right
we talked about how to build hash tables
now we can use our hash tables new
aggregations or we can do use use
sorting to build aggregations do
aggregations right sort of building the
layers of the system on top of each
other so the cost analysis for this is
essentially if you have B be buffer
blocks you can build then in the first
phase you can always fill out B minus 1
right because you always need one
partition to be or you know use the
buffer to write out two and then on the
coming back in
the total amount I owe you have to deal
with B times B minus one because for
every single paid B you have to read it
back in write it out and read it back in
so I don't talk about the fudge factor
here but the game the big assumption
we're making is that the keys are hash
uniformly so each bucket has the same
amount of data in practice that's not
always the case right there's more
people live in Pennsylvania that people
live in Alaska so if you hatch on the
state you know the the Pennsylvania
buckets gonna be overflowing we'll cover
that next class we talk about hash joins
because this is the big problem that
these guys are gonna have to deal with
in their environment of how to deal with
joins when everything isn't uniformly
distributed okay all right so the the
main takeaway when you get from this and
we'll see more about this on on Monday
next week is that then the data system
has had to maintain is trade-off making
this decision about whether you're
sorting or hashing and depends on what
index you have available what the data
looks like what your query looks like
and and then uses that to figure out
whether one choice is better than
another I love say the spoiler is for if
you take the advanced class is that
hashing those are almost always going to
be the better approach unless you have
an order by that explicitly wants your
data sorted hashing whether it's hash
one and hash aggregations is almost
always better
all right sorting is just it's just more
work there's a bunch of other
optimizations we talked about before
about prefetching and and and trying to
do as much work as you can for every IO
you have to do the main takeaway from
all this it would be that
everything all the optimizations we
focused on we're all about how to reduce
IO once I got the thing in memory I
didn't you know I don't really care you
know what
you know sorting algorithm using or you
know how how will cache friendly
approach I'm using to compute my hashes
I don't care because the disk IO is
always missed expensive thing so that's
what I want to minimize in the advanced
class or in an in-memory database disk
IO is no longer the issue so now we
start caring about things like CPU
register usage cache utilization and
other things for this and you
come up with a better hash table that
sketch friendly but for the IO is always
me the biggest problem we don't care
about that for this class okay
I so any questions about sorting or
aggregations all right cool
all right so next class again we'll be
focusing on joins so we'll start of the
basicness look joins and just get more
complicated complicated and then we have
time we'll talk about what I call exotic
Joan joins lateral joins aunty join semi
joins at the end okay 43 which are
drinking 12 they say we'll make sure
Thayne eyes are straight so it really
don't matter