[Music]
maybe all the jewels started alright
hold again any questions about the
logistics of the course or anything that
we discussed last class again I'll talk
about homework 1 at the end of the class
and then it'll be posted immediately
after the lecture is over so everyone
can start at the same time ok all right
so today's lecture is on advanced sequel
and by advanced I mean going beyond what
you may or may not already know about
basic sequel right it's it's 2018 sequel
was invented in 1973 I imagine most you
have seen some sequel throughout your
life so I don't feel it's necessary to
teach you the basics of it so I'm gonna
spend time actually talking about the
more complicated or interesting things
you can do with sequel okay so just to
pick up where we left last class we were
discussing the relational model and
relational algebra and we sort of
mentioned that the with relational
algebra sir the goal was sort of at a
high level to describe what the answer
we wanted that the database system would
compute rather than the exact steps of
actually how to do it all right so the
way to think about this is like say we
want to sort our data if we have to tell
the day system exactly what to do we
have to provide it you know with the
quick sort of bubble sort algorithm but
with a high level language or
declarative language we just say hey we
want you to sort this we don't care how
you actually do it but this is the
answer that we want and we'll see this
throughout today's lecture and then
going forward throughout later in the
semester all right this is one of the
advantage of using something like Secord
our declarative languages we don't have
to tell today's system exactly how to do
things it can figure it out own zone and
that frees it up to figure out what
there was optimal way it is to actually
execute the query that you want to
execute based on the data that you have
and and give the harbor that's available
to you so we'll see this later when we
talk about the query optimizer but the
query optimizer is this complicated
piece of machinery inside of a database
system that's
take our sequel query and convert it to
the most efficient plan and we'll cover
how they actually do this later on but I
will say is that if you if you you know
if you get involved in doing research on
query optimization or just help you know
working on Cori optimizers you can get a
job yesterday because this is the one
thing that all my friends at Davis
company companies email me about over
and over again do I have any students to
do query optimization we've had some and
they all get off go off and do awesome
jobs this is the one thing that
everybody wants because it's really hard
to do so that's not the focus here right
just in the back your mind will see
examples as we go along where a query
optimizer could try out different things
I try to come up with different plans
well we'll discuss how you actually do
query optimization later on so the the
history of sequel as I said goes back
into the early 1970s so you may notice
that I say sequel
some people say SQL write the part of
the reason I say sequel is because in
not that I was alive in 1970s but the
original name of the language was
actually spelled out as EQ UAL sequel
and this was invited by IBM as part of
the system our project right so it stood
for the structured English query
language so if you remember from the TED
Cod paper I said that Ted Cobb was a
mathematician right he devised the
relational algebra and relational model
but he didn't actually define the
programming language you would use to
write queries on it I mean you can't
write queries using relational algebra
right it's sort of you know there's
there's no it's very difficult to write
that in the keyboard to do that he did
later define or come up with his own
query language called alpha but that was
much later in 1970s so back then when
people said hey there's a relational
model idea we should actually write ooh
build a system to do this people had to
come up with their own language that
could implement relational calculus or
relational algebra so at IBM they came
out with sequel this is part of the
system our project which is a sort of
one of the first relational database
systems that people were trying to build
in the 1970s the other major one was
ingress that came out of Berkeley
so you've ever heard of Postgres right
Postgres was invented by the same guy
that did ingress so it's called Postgres
as in post
ingress the thing that came after
ingress so
the ingress guys had their own language
called quell and this was developed by
one of my advisers Mike Stormbreaker he
claims it was much better than sequel
and the IBM guys didn't know what they
were doing of course most people have
never heard a quell right right so it
didn't actually win
IBM won so back then again it was
spelled out as eqtl IBM later got sued
for I think you know a copyright
infringement trademark infringement
there was some guy in England that had
the the term sequel spelt out in the
full English word for his programming
language so it is shortened it to be sq
SQL so what happened was the reason why
we use sequel today because IBM it's not
back then IBM is and what it is now
right everyone thinks the big the big
tech companies like Microsoft Amazon and
Google back in the 1970s 1980s IBM was
was the juggernaut so essentially
whatever IBM did or said this is the way
we're gonna do it that ended up being
the standard so when IBM first released
their first commercial relational
database system db2 so they never
actually released system arm it's just
sort of a research prototype but then
then finally made db2 released that db2
supported sequel so that essentially
became the standard and the reason why
Oracle sort of took off and got as big
as it is today is they were sort of
copying what IBM was doing in the 1970s
in more ways than one we can talk about
that later and they did they had sequel
so when IBM came out with db2 and had
sequel Oracle was right at the right
place at the right time said we now
supports we know we support sequel - so
it became an ANSI standard in 1986 and
became an international standard in 1987
and now the short burden just means the
structured query language so sequel even
though it's from 1970s it's not a dead
language it's not certainly static it's
sort of like you know C++ to keep
releasing new specifications every so
often it's the same thing in sequel
every so often there's a new
specification where they add in new
features and new functionalities - to
the basic language so the the latest
standard is defined in sequel 2016 and
you can see over the years at the add
new versions they add new features right
so 2016 they added JSON polymorphic
tables
they add XML stuff and then 2003 1999
added regex and triggers typically what
happens is there's a standards body that
the members are all from the major
database companies and major database
companies come up with their own
proprietary features and extensions and
then they go in the standards body and
push to try to get their version of
certain functionality as part of the
standard right so this is although there
is a sequel standard nobody actually
follows it to the T right because
everyone sort of has their own
proprietary things that got invented
before the standard came out said this
is how you should do things so if you're
gonna claim that your database system
supports sequel the bare minimum you
need to have is actually what is defined
in the sequel 92 standard so this is
what the basic sequel that we know about
today select insert update delete create
tables transactions things like that all
that's defined in sequel 92 so again if
someone someone says their data system
supports equal chances are they that
really mean this and then the more
advanced databases both an open source
and and the commercial ones they add
they have a bunch of more features from
from from the newer Sanders and then
there's this great website here it's a
bit dated now but it's going at its some
random dude who basically looked at sort
of the top four top five database
systems and just look to see how they
differ on various sequel features and
their compares sequel functionalities
and we'll see this as we go through
today there'll be some examples where
the standard says one thing different
database systems do other things it's
usually my sequel and this is just gonna
even though there's a standard nobody
actually follows it exactly right
there's no database system that I'm
aware of that would claim that they're
you know certify for sequel 2016 right
they had bits and pieces of things so
sequel itself technically is not a
single language it's sort of a
collection of things in a particular
collection of a DML DDL and DCO
commands so DML will be would be the
data manipulation language would be the
commands like insert update delete
selects like the things that actually
manipulate the data that you can store
in your database the DDL is the way you
create tables actually
schemas to actually store things and
then the D CL is the way you sort of do
security authorization to grant you know
who's allowed to read what what datum
there's a bunch of other things like how
to define views how to define integrity
constraints referential constraints as
well as transactions
rhaggy these are all part of the
umbrella of sequel right and within that
there's these different categories of
commands so the one important thing that
I want to point out here and we'll see
this throughout today's lecture is
unlike in relational algebra which is
based on set theory or sets sequel is
actually based on bag algebra so the way
to sort of think about this you could
have like lists sets or bags so a list
can have duplicates but there's there's
a defined order so if I push something
to my list that's its position in that
list a set is unordered meaning the
elements don't have a position but you
can't have duplicates if I try to insert
the same thing into a set it just gets
over the old one gets overwritten a bag
has neither a set position or ordering
but it also allows for duplicates right
and we'll see why we've got to do this
as we go along because if we want to
actually define order on our elements or
if you want to make sure that we don't
have duplicates essentially the database
system has to do extra work to provide
that for you and so the idea is that
only if you explicitly ask the database
system to provide you ordering it
provide you to remove duplicates it
won't actually do it and this actually
make things be a be more efficient all
right so the outline for today is we're
going to cover aggregations group eyes a
bunch of operations on strings dates and
times then we do have to do output
control and then the more complicated
things would be nested queries common
table expressions and window functions
so for homework one you'll need to use
all of these except for the window
functions all right because you can be
doing homework one on sequel Lite and
only actually the latest version of
sequel Lite as of last week just added
support for window functions but
everything else sequel Lite should be
able to support
okay alright so for this the we're needs
a sample database comprised of three
tables so sort of it's a mock University
so we're gonna have a student table
where students have student IDs names
logs and GPS will have a course table
with course IDs a name and then we'll
have an enroll table where we have a
certain foreign key reference from the
student table and the course table and
along with the grade that the student
got in the class all right we'll use
this as our running example as we go
along all right so the first thing we
talk about our aggregations right and
these are pretty simple to understand
it's basically a function that you
define in the output list of your select
statement that's going to take as input
multiple tuples a set of tuples and it's
going to compute some kind of
aggregation on top of that and produced
a single result right so the sequel 92
standard defines average min max sum and
count and again think of this is like in
case of count you're gonna take a bag or
tuples as the input and you're going to
count the number of tuples that are and
that you're a produces a single output
that has that that count right again so
this is what's in the basic standard the
the later version of the standard and in
other database systems they'll have
other things like median mode standard
deviation right and the github different
aggregates and some of them actually
does it allows you to find your own
aggregations as well so let's look an
example like this right so say we want
to discount the number of students in
this student table where the login ends
with at CS I'll cover what like is means
later on but essentially it's just
looking for a wild card here right so
the first thing the most important thing
to remember about aggregations is that
the aggregation can only appear in the
output list of the Select statement
right so I have it here in the in this
the same this is I want to produce at
the output I can't have it in these in
these other parts here right cuz it
doesn't really make sense right because
you're computing aggregation after
you've sort of applied a filter to
figure out what tuples actually match
your where clause but the same point out
here is that in case account again we
just wanna count them
tuples the logon field here doesn't
actually mean anything right cuz we're
just counting the number of tuples it
doesn't matter whether you know what the
login actually is at the point after we
do the filtering so we can rewrite this
just to have a star
alright the star is a special you know
special keyword in sequel the basically
says all attributes for the tuple we can
go even further and say we can actually
replace the star with a one right count
the number of tuples by just adding one
every single time right so this is a
good example where we have three
different queries that all produce are
semantically the same to produce the
same result but the data besom could
could choose different flavours or
different variations of this in order to
derive that answer and some of them may
have different performance differences
this one's pretty simple so the most of
this will be smart to realize I don't
need a copy around the login here I can
just replace that with a one right most
of them will do that but from what
complicated things and may not always
work we actually can combine the
aggregate multiple a grits together in a
single query so say for this one we want
to get the number of students and their
average GPA where their login ends with
at CS right so now you see I've combined
it average GPA and count in my output
output list for my select statement and
then it'll produce my result like that
alright pretty straightforward I can
also add the distinct keyword to tell it
to only count the distinct elements or
values of attributes for for my tuples
so this is saying count the number of
unique students with unique logins from
the student table where the log it ends
with at CS right and so I had the
distinct inside of account now this one
is sort of nonsensical to in some ways
because presumably no two students can
have the same login you know login
account otherwise you'd have problems
but in in other cases you know you can
apply the same kind of thing for other
scenarios and it would work the way you
wanted to work right and in this case
here we produce the same result
so the one thing that now you want to
may want to try to start doing is now
that I'm start doing aggregations I want
to get additional information about my
data outside of just what I'm computing
in my aggregate right so say that I want
to I want to get the average GPA of the
students that are rolled in the course
and I want to know what that course ID
was right so in this case here I've now
added the course ID to my output list
outside of my aggregation right didn't
take a guess what would happen here
would this work or not raise your hand
you think would work raise your hand if
you think it wouldn't work see of you
why correct yes so what he said is
there's not a single course ID for all
my tuples that are competing my average
on right it's all the students are
taking all the different classes what
course I need to actually put is the
output right it's the sequel standard
say this is actually undefined and in
most systems you actually will get an
error with this we can actually test
this right
so in this never go I have three three
terminal setup all right so this is
running the machine back in my office I
have three panels the top one is
Postgres the bottom one or the middle
ones my seagull and the bottom one is
sequel light it says much easier for you
to type from this machine here so I can
log in to that right okay so the query
was we wanted to select where was it
get the average GPA of students enrolled
in each course right
so select average sgpa eCourse ID from
enrolled as a student as s where eise to
deny d equals a student ID right so
Postgres says you can't do this because
as he said the course ID and i'm
highlighting here as you can see there
so the course ID is not defined it's not
part of the aggregation right so it
doesn't know which course ID you
actually want so now if we go down and
try this in my sequel my seagull gave us
an answer right but is that correct no
right because because what course ID to
the pic i picked a random one right and
then now we can try in sequel light same
thing sequel light gave us a different
course ID so you see they both completed
the correct average but they chose a
different course ID all right
and just because I know that my single
guys watch these videos and complain I
will say that so this is running my
sequel in and so my sequel traditionally
allowed you to do loosey goosey things
like this right so this would be running
it what they would call a traditional
mode but you can set the sequel mode to
be more strict so now if I run that same
query it froze the same error that
Postgres did so by default these my
sequel 5,7 would now throw errors in
older versions they didn't do that right
okay so a way to fix this is to do group
I so with group I what's gonna happen is
now we're gonna define how we want to
essentially bucket together the tuples
in our output based on one attribute and
then now we can then compute the
aggregation on the tuples in each bucket
right
so again what I wanted to do was get the
average GPA per course if I add now in
my group by clause I add the the course
ID what will happen is when I first
execute the query this is essentially
what I would see after the join but now
with the group by clause I'll combine
together the the tuples based on the
course ID and then for each of these now
I'll compute my aggregate right and now
I can group them by course ID and that
corresponds to the buckets I generated
from before right so we have to use
group I if we want to extract
information about the aggregations we're
computing right and so just like before
any time we have a attribute that we
won't appear in our output select Clause
it has to appear in the group ID so here
the student name we're trying to throw
that in in our output Clause it won't
work because it has to be in our group
by clause now this one is sorted to get
a nonsensical a technically correct
sequel it produced a result but from a
human standpoint we know doesn't mean
anything but like what does it mean to
group by course ID and then the student
name to compute the average GPA right
the student's GPA is gonna be their GPA
okay so now you may think alright well
maybe I want to do them with some more
some additional filtering all my
aggregations so that I don't look at you
know I don't produce every single result
as part of the output so you may think
that you out want to put it
use the aggregations in your where
clause so here now I'm now I'm computing
every GPA but I'm added in my where
clause something that says filter out
anything where the GPA is is not you
know greater than 3,9 this is look only
trying to look at the courses with
average GPA is greater than 3,9 right so
this doesn't work because in our we
can't access anything in our
aggregations in our where clause because
we don't have them yet in our where
clause right so again the way to figure
out this is the where clause is
filtering tuples as we go along and
after we do our filtering then we can
actually then computer aggregation so we
can't compute we can't use an
aggregation to filter tuples because we
have a computer the aggregation yet
right so the way to get around this is
use the having clause it's essentially
like a where clause but now you can
reference anything in your output list
so I've taken my average GPA and I've
aliased it to AVG GPA and I can
represent down in here and this will
produce the answer that I want right
capice the aggregation is just like
before and then it applies additional
filtering on it so now not in this
example but there's other examples where
you can do certain optimizations in the
system based on what you know is in your
having clause again this is the great
thing about declarative language you
know everything all ahead of time what
the you know what the programmer the
person wants in their answer so you can
use hints about what you knows could
come later in the query plan to help you
do certain refinements or reduce the
amount of work you have to do as you run
the query so instead of using average
GPA say I wanted to do a count where the
number of tuples are less than some you
know first each group less than some
value so that as I'm going along as I'm
computing my aggregate if I then
recognize that oh my having Clause says
filter anything less than ten two pools
if not if I now hit tuple number eleven
for a group I know that I never need to
count anything else for that for that
two plus that come later because it'll
never pass that having falls so I can
just throw away there's tuples as I go
along because it's wasted work right if
you're writing this in a procedural
language like Python alright well you
had to write these steps but it's you
know by by yourself the you know the
Davidson is not gonna know what's gonna
come later on because it can't peek
ahead right but in a declarative
language like C code we can do that so
the next thing we want to talk about is
how to handle strings so this is a table
that sort of summarizes the the
different variations of how strings are
handled in different database systems so
the the Seacoast a nurse best says that
all strings like sub varchars chars text
fields they have to be case sensitive
and the way you declare them is with
single quotes
and most systems follow this right the
red herrings of the oddballs are both my
sequel and sequel light so in TECO light
the strings are sensitive but you can
have both single and double double
quotes - to mark them in my sequel it's
case insensitive and you can use either
single or double quotes now my problem
is that when I spur started using data
systems back in like 2000 I was using my
seagull 3 and it's like it's like you
know ingrained in my memory to just use
double quotes cuz that's what we use
back then so I'm always had to correct
myself every time I switch over another
data system to go always go back and use
single quotes my Seco again has the mode
you can say - follow the standard a bit
better and they then enforce the single
quote requirement but I think by default
you don't get that right so in the
seagull standards say you want to take
the name you want to take the you know
the name of Kanye and have it match with
Kanye with you know mixed case in in in
the sequel standard you had the upper
case using the upper you know the upper
function to make this match work in my
sequel you don't have to do that right
because all all the strings are matching
or case insensitive now I showed this
before how to do light claws but I think
really it's a lies you do the first
string matching alright so like is
basically doing you know trying to match
some wild card in your string with with
another string so for whatever reason
instead of using star like most other
things they use the print throughout %
so % means any one or more strings and
then the underscore means exactly match
one character alright so say I want to
get all the course or the course IDs
from the roll table that start with 15
to 15 for 45 7 21 I would use the the
Amber's the % like that and say if I
want to get all the students where the
the login ends with at C and then some
wild card I would use a single
underscore for that so the sequel
standard also defines a bunch of string
functions there's a again the standard
things you
expect like substring upper/lower trim
our these are all part of the sequel 92
standards and move systems will have
this but of course there's me a bunch of
other stuff that are proprietary in each
different database system so the thing
to point out unlike aggregation
functions with string functions and you
know mathematical functions and date
functions they can appear anywhere in
the in your in your queries so they can
mean the Select output list it could be
in your predicate s--
alright they don't always have to be in
the in the select portion they can be in
your having clauses so here we have you
know the first guy first query is gonna
take the name and take a substring and
just get just get the first five
characters and then the second one we
did is to be show before of doing
matching where the the uppercase version
of the student name is begins with K ka
n so again string functions are for the
most part the basic ones will be pretty
much standardized across all systems
where things get weird as when you want
to start doing a concatenation so The
Seagull standard says that you use two
double bars to concatenate two strings
together and most systems follow this in
my opinion I would say Postgres in
Oracle probably follow the sequel
standard the best out of all the systems
sequel server and db2 are probably next
sequel Lite then probably my sequels the
worst so you want to say to concatenate
the student name and add at CS to it do
use double bar in the sequel standard in
sequel server from Microsoft you use the
plus sign in my sequel they don't have a
plus sign they don't have the double bar
they only have this concat function were
you basically defined as the input
parameters the things you want to
concatenate together they have something
else that's kind of weird to where you
can actually have if you don't put
anything between two string literals
that'll concatenate them together so to
show you what I mean by that so here we
have my siegel so i can do something
like this a n dy space PA VLO right
nobody else does this as far as I know
let me double check that before I lie to
you let's try it in huh
yeah toca Paris Chris doesn't like it
sequence over doesn't like it either
right only my seagull does that all
right so now we're things get really
really bad is when you have date and
time functions right so a date basically
chicken just records the time stamp
without the time time stamp is is the
time now they vary on the granularity of
the time they may be tracking sometimes
in seconds sometimes it's a milliseconds
or something even more fine-grained than
that but where things get get wonky is
how you actually start manipulating them
and extracting them extracting
information from them right and so the
syntax for all these different systems
can can can vary wildly so for this
example we want to do is I want to show
you how to do what I consider a
seemingly easy function or easy
operation get the number days from today
to since the beginning of the year and
we'll see how to try to do this and on
these three different systems okay so
the first thing is that we want to get
maybe what the current time is now I
just kill my Wi-Fi back okay all right
so the seco standard defines a now
function can everyone see that or now in
the back guys can you see it okay cool
so you call now and it gives you the
current timestamp so we can do that in
in my sequel and we can do this in
sequel light what you can't do in a
single vibe all right
all right so there's another way to do
this they have another function called a
current timestamp right except Postgres
doesn't have it but they had the keyword
current timestamp
my sequel has the function and it has
the keyword all right see collate who
says it has the function raise your hand
some who says it says it has the keyword
alright it's mixed alright they don't
have the function they have the keyword
alright again simple thing like what's
the current time it varies
alright so now again what we want to do
is we want to count the number of days
since the since the beginning of the
year all right so as a building block
what we can try to do is maybe just get
what the number of days is from from
today so in this query what I'm doing is
I'm taking a date listed here is a
string right so I'm taking the string
for today's date and converting it into
a date and then I have the extract
function which will extract out the the
day field of the date right so as
expected you get you get 29 all right we
can try that in the and the other guys
it gives you 29 they don't have it all
right
so but now we can see that like alright
well if I can if I can cast a string for
the date into a date what happens if I
do subtract them right right I'll take
today's date and subtract the it from
the the the date from the beginning of
the year and in Postgres we get it 240
days all right
my sequel 728 I don't know what that
means right like it's not like 240 times
2 or some you know some multiple there
right it's it's a number right it ran
but it's not what we want right so now
let's try it in in sequel Lite sequel
like give us 0 ok so it works in
Postgres and now we got to figure how to
do this in my sequel well so what we can
do is we we try to extract the the the
day from so maybe we take what we can at
728 we have before right and we extract
the day from and see what that means all
right it came back with 28 so that's not
really what we want so the way to do it
actually is a bit complicated what we're
gonna do is we're going to convert the
dates into UNIX timestamp which is the
number of seconds since the unit's to
epoch which is like some January 1st
1970 right and now we're gonna have the
number of seconds from from the current
date number seconds since beginning the
day we subtract them right and that
gives us the number of seconds between
now and the beginning of the year and
then we're gonna divide that by 60
seconds times 60 minutes times 24 days
right we got 240 all right turns out
though after I did this the first time
there's actually even easier way in my
sequel they have a simple function
called date div and that produces you
know the same answer all right
single light uh-huh for Brianna I think
let me try Nicky's a little bigger there
you go in single light they don't have
date if you can't subtract the age with
each other the the way I figured out to
do it was convert the current timestamp
into the to the Julian calendar which is
the number of days since for 37 BC or
for 4370 BC and so you subtract the the
noir days since that time the number
days beginning the year and you get
roughly 240 right alright and we get we
can cast it to an int and we get 240
right so these are three super super
widely used database systems that all
differ on some basic functionality of
doing date and time right
actually quick show of hands who think
of these three ones which one do you
think is the most popular miss widely
deployed database system raise your hand
you think my sequel but about a quarter
raise your name think Postgres even less
ready Tim thinks egalit even less the
answer sequel light so a few years ago
we had Richard hippie invent our sequel
light so see the light is amazing it's
written by three dudes right there they
is he approximate that it's been
deployed on 10 billion devices everyone
here who has a cell phone right that
isn't a flip phone or an old person
phone is running sequel light on it
right now
right a lot of desktop applications like
Photoshop and illustrator they run
sequel light on the inside right sequel
light is everywhere he said that also to
every single AOL CD if you know what
that is all right back in the early
2000s when the internet was sort of new
in the u.s. there was a company called
America Online and they would every mail
everyone CDs for ten hours free on the
internet right every CD that they mailed
out you know hundreds of millions of
them had sequel light running on it
right sequel a is most widely deployed
Davis isn't
everywhere and here's the most crazy
part it's public domain he gives it away
for free right I mean Postgres and my
Segal are open-source but like hey for
my sequel Oracle owns it Orca owns the
copyright there's no copyright on sequel
white right it's an amazing piece of
software okay alright so just again the
main takeaway here was that simple
things are hard to do because there's no
stamp you know there's no standard way
to do things even though there is a
standard specification all right so now
maybe what we want to do is instead of
having the you know in my examples I had
the terminal open every time I ran a
query that the output got printed back
to me in my terminal but maybe what you
want to do is keep all the data you you
you generate from a query keep that
inside the database system so you can
use it in subsequent queries right this
is way more efficient if you're if
you're if your queries generating a lot
of output you don't have everything sim
down to your laptop and then push it
back up to do more queries on it so you
can do output redirection to tell it to
say hey don't print it out to me write
it out to this location so one thing you
can do is you can take the output or
query and you can write it into another
table right and so you in the sequel
standard you can use into and this will
actually will create the table for you
on the fly so whatever is produces the
output of the query right again this is
declarative the David isn't already
knows what the schema is of the table so
it knows in this case here what the type
is that this output is going to be so he
knows how to define a table that has
that that can handle those types right
so into basically takes the output of
select and writes it into a table and in
my sequel you have to use the create
table and then inside of it you define
your Select statement you can also have
it output data into an existing table
and for this you use insert into which
looks a lot like we create into the
create table from from before and then
set instead of having the value Clause
you actually just have a select
statement just to tell it hey get this
data aren't right into here so the
important thing about this example
versus the previous slide this is about
writing tables into tuples into tables
that already exist so that means that
whatever be whatever
the type the number attributes and their
types that are produced by the Select
statement whatever table you're writing
it into has to match that right if the
the Select statement has 44 columns and
your table you're writing into as three
the daisen will throw an air it says
like I can't write into that because it
the Astor's don't match up now where
things get weird is when you start
having constraints that are on the table
you're trying to write into and the
Select statement actually violates those
constraints so let's say that I have a
primary key on my table it says I can't
have any duplicate student IDs and then
my insert query here tries to start and
start inserting duplicates some database
system will throw an error immediately
as soon as it sees the duplicate and no
tuples get written some of them will
just keep going and ignore the ones that
that failed other ones will will insert
the ones that succeeded and just ignore
the ones that failed or me these just
crash right away right so again the
sequel standard says this is the syntax
that to use but how the systems actually
implement it will vary widely in
addition to redirection we can all sleep
output control remember I said the
beginning Seco is based on bag algebra I
mean it's unordered but there's many
times where you want the ordering in
your Apple cause and so to do this you
add the order by clause I assume is
basically specifying how to sort the
results that are being generated by by
this query so in this example here I'm
gonna sort the tuple I started sort of
the tuple main role table based on their
grade and by default even though I don't
specify whether I wanted ascending in or
descending the default in sequel is that
you get ascending right you get output
like this but I also can add additional
attributes to my order by clause do more
complicated things so in this case here
I want to do my order by by grade in
descending order and then after that I
sort them based on the student ID in
ascending order
all right and I would get output like
this now the one thing to point out here
also too is that unlike there in the
group by clause
where any attribute that I wanted my
output list had to appear in the group
by clause in order by you don't have
that restriction right it actually goes
both ways in this case here I'm sorting
by the grade but the grade isn't part of
the output right it doesn't matter right
and it knows how to how to how to find
the data that it needs as its processing
the query and do whatever sorting
operation that you want to do on it I
can also do more complicated things I
can put any arbitrary expression in my
order by Clause as well so I can do
order by 1 plus 1 right and that's still
valid it knows how to handle that
another common thing you want to do is
is limit the number of tuples that are
producing your output right and of
course there's a there's a limit clause
for this you basically specifies says I
for all the results that you of Mike my
query only and provide me back some
number of them like 10 right and this is
very common for things like you know say
like search results you'll see it show
just 10 and then you click the next
button to go see the next 10 alright
this is being controlled by it by limit
and actually all set so limit just says
limit the number of tuples all set is
going to tell you that and what all set
of the number of the tuples you're
producing as your output should you skip
before you start figuring out how many
you should limit right again if you
think of a webpage to show you 10
results you click Next to see the next
10 there using a limit with an offset to
make that work now because it's unsorted
again is no guarantee that when you
click Next if you're using offset you're
going to see you know you're definitely
gonna see different tuples because
that's another invocation of the query
and the results may be different in
different order the second time so in
this case here you would combine that
with an order by clause so that you're
guaranteed to go you know see the first
10 followed by the second 10 and so
forth right and there's optimizations
you can apply whether you're not you
have an order by Clause if you have a
limit clause so if I don't have an order
by clause and I have a limit I know that
as soon as I see sent 10 to polls I'm
done I don't need to go look at anything
else if you have an order by then you
have to sort you have to see everything
ahead of time to sort it then you can
apply your limit and your
all set ice again I considered that
somewhat basic sequel in previous years
I actually skipped all this but I I
think it's important maybe to go go over
it a little bit because you have to
understand this for the homework but now
we want to talk about more complicated
things this is what I would consider
advanced sequel so the first thing we'll
talk about is is nested queries so the
way thing about nested query it's
basically allowing you to specify
queries inside of queries right and you
can take the output of one query and use
that as the input of another query all
right so a simple example like this I'm
doing a select I want to get all the
names of the students that are enrolled
in least one course so I have my outer
query is defined based on the student
table and then the side of that I have
an inner query that's and this going to
get the student IDs from the role table
all right
so we could write this as a join this is
sort of sudden another way to actually
do this and in actuality when it comes
time to actually implement this inside
the system most query optimizer will try
to rewrite this as a join right because
it the worst way to actually execute
this is to basically have two for loops
where you loop over every single tuple
in the student table and for every
single two but you've been invoked the
same query over and over and over again
my sequel used to do this more primitive
David system you should do this but the
right way to do is actually just rewrite
this as a join all right so you can sort
of think of this inner query as like a
function that can produce some set of
tuples as your output and then you can
apply whatever predicate you want on
that in the outer query so we'll walk
through a bunch of examples of this and
see how it works
so the alright so the first example one
is maybe I want to get the names of all
the students exist in that enrolled in
15 for 45 so the way to construct a
nested query is I think is always
important to start maybe with the outer
query and think about what's the actual
answer you want to produce like what are
the actual attributes you want to see
and then you worry about how you're
actually gonna filter them and get what
you want so the outer query we know that
we want the name from the student table
and then where we get those values we'll
figure it out so in the inner query we
can write it as English is the student
ID
and the set of people about take 4:15
4:45 right so for that part we know how
to write that query pretty easily right
we just filter out all the tuples from
enroll table or the course ID he goes 15
for 45 so now the question is how do we
combine them with the the outer query
with the inner query again we can
rewrite this very easily with the join
but for our purposes here we want to see
how to do it as a nested function so for
this we can use the in operator and we
do a matching on the student student ID
so a way to now read this is that the
for every single student in the student
table
so this first student ID is matching up
with a student table I want to see
whether there's a match of that student
ID in the set of all student IDs that
are in the role table that take the
course 15 for 45 so we exit the inner
query we produce the set of all student
IDs and then for every single tuple in
the outer query we check to see whether
it exists in that set right now this
visit shows you why it's saying before
the stupid way to execute this is for
every single tuple in the outer query we
execute the inner query over and over
again like that's stupid because we only
need to produce the inner query once and
then we can reuse it for every single
tuple and in the outer query so I show
it how to in the Attic see if I used in
those other operators you can use so all
basically says that every single tuple
that's in my inner query must must
satisfy my predicate any means at least
one of them needs to alright so in is
essentially the same thing as equals any
right is there any tuple that it equals
what my predicate or about my tuple
attribute is checking and then exists
says at least one rows returned and
actually I don't care where that matches
I just care what I see whether a tuple
got produces as a result so we can
rewrite our table for getting all the
students in 15 for 45 like this by
instead of using in we say equals any so
now you read this as the student ID from
the student table check to see whether
it
any tool that exists in the set of
student IDs that are produced by from
from the enroll table right now the
energy the nested queries don't have to
only appear in the where clause they
actually can appear anywhere right so I
can rewrite the same query like this
where now I have my nested query in the
output of the Select statement so this
is a good example of this is reversing
what I did before in terms of what
tables were going to access so now the
way to read this is that for every
single tuple in the enrolled table where
the course ID equals 15 45 54 45 I'm
gonna then do a match up in the student
table where the student IDs are the same
right this is essentially doing a join
inside my output of my select statement
right because now this student ID is
being referenced here from the student
table and that student ID is being
referenced in there hey this is another
good example again I essentially
reversing the order of how I process my
tables right and they produce the exact
same result but they may have different
performance characteristics based on
what my data actually looks like it may
be the case that this is actually faster
to go through the role table first
instead of the student table and
therefore we could rewrite it if we
wanted to to choose one versus the other
and a good optimizer could do this for
you okay all right let's look at
something any more complicated now all
right say we want to find the student
record with the highest ID that enrolled
in at least one course right seems
pretty simple but let's think we
actually do this so the first
approximation would be something like
this
select the max a student ID along with
the student name from from the join and
rolled and student table where the
student ID in the role table equals the
student ID in the student table will
this work why why not
what's that yeah there's an aggregation
function without a group I and we're
referencing a column that's not in the
aggregation right so again the sequel
standard says that this shouldn't work
let's find out alright so again we have
not gonna disconnect first course at the
top so we've run our query here and
Postgres and here's the standard it says
get as exactly as he said so you have
student ID student name appears but it's
not a part of a group I so you can't use
it right in my sequel same thing it
produces that error but if we now run it
in what they call traditional mode right
so older versions of my sequel will do
this now we run this query and we get an
answer right we have the max student ID
and then we say that the name best
student is Tupac all right let's try it
in sequel light front one it produces an
answer it also produces 50 3 6 8 8 as
the next to 90 but it says the that
student belongs to Justin Bieber right
and actually I don't know what the right
answer is let's see here
so Justin Bieber is the right one right
whereas my sequel make sure I'm giving
you the same data right Tupac is
actually the lowest all right so you got
it completely wrong all right so the
right so this doesn't work in the sequel
standard it runs a single byte and and
and my SIBO if we turn off that strict
mode thing so way we can do this is a
nested function again let's build it
constructively so we know there you want
the student ID and the name as the
output but it's the where clause that
thing we have to figure out and this one
basically says that we want to get a
matching tuple that is greater than
every other student ID that that's
that's in our table right so we know the
inner query shall should be basically
the student ID from the role table we
can be the more more sophisticated maybe
put two distinct there but it's all the
same but now we need to figure out how
to match the student ID from the student
and an outer query the student ID from
from the inner query and for this we can
use greater than equal to all right it
has to be greater than equal to because
we make sure that we match ourselves the
student that actually is that does
actually have that the highest one right
you can rewrite this in other ways as
expected right we can rewrite it with
the in clause like that and actually
compute the max student ID and the inner
query right now basically this is saying
match the student ID that is the max
student ID produced from from the enroll
table right we can go even further we
can rewrite the inner God be like this
right we do an order by the student ID
and just rank them in descending order
and then do a limit one so some systems
will actually just rewrite this one to
be a max anyway just scan everything
keep track which one's the max and then
produce that's the final output
don't even bother doing sorting right
again same query rewritten in different
ways one more example we're gonna find
all the courses that have no students
enrolled in them so we take our outer
query as a Select on the courses and
then we know our inner query basically
says when a find note where they have no
tuples in the enroll table so for this
one we want to use not exists basically
says we don't want to
match anything in our inner query and
all we need to do that for the inner
queries is just just grab every single
tuple and here now we're actually
matching up the the course ID in the
inner query with the course ID from the
outer query so you can only do this in
one direction so if you're the inner
query you can represent the outer query
if you're in the outer query you can't
reference the inner query right unless
you pipe it out or redirect it to a
table so any questions about nested
queries again they're very powerful many
tens you cannot write what you want to
write in in in a single query without
using nested queries yes her question is
can you think of an inner query as a
nested for them yes but no so we'll see
for loop has a notion of like ordering
it's it's really a set right so all
those operators like in X exists any
those are just trying to say for the
entire set of tuples that are in the
inner query check to see whether any of
em matches you're not you're not really
iterating over every single one if you
think of the outer query sort of as a
for debating every single tuple but then
the set portion the evaluation of the
inner query is always at server at a bag
or set set level make sense ok window
functions so window functions are I
would say they're new but they're like
15 10 years old now so they're not like
not brand new a lot of systems don't
support them but the major ones do so a
window function is sort of like an
aggregation where you're going to
compute some some function on on tuples
but rather than doing it on you know a
subset of the tuples and collapsing them
down into a single result you sort of do
this in a incremental fashion or on a
moving fashion and then you still
produce the tuple as the output but
along with the value that it produced
the window function right so the basic
syntax is like this you have the
function name and then you have an over
clause
so the function name will be our
aggregation functions and other special
window functions we have which I'll show
the next slide and then the over the
over Clause defines how we actually want
to slice up the data right this is sort
of like combining together the
aggregation and the group by but in a
single clause so the function is like
the aggregation function the over is
like the group line so the aggregation
functions would be all the things in the
sequel standard that we talked before
min max average count some the special
wind functions could do things like
introduce a row number to the current
row so to keep track as the tuples as
being output and it marks them with what
order they they're coming out and then
rank would be the order of the position
of a tuple if we're doing sorting
alright so say what I want to do is I
want to go do a select over the enroll
table and I want to produce all the
tuples as my output but I want to just
mark them with the row number of the
output right so I have my row number a
row number function and then for my over
Clause I just leave that blank and then
what I end up with is a result that
looks like this alright I have all the
data that had before but now I had this
special column here row num that's just
again the order of the tuple that that
that it was produced in the output so
sort of like I compute my entire query
and then I do my window function to go
over the results and I and then I add in
whatever the computation that I want to
generate so just like a group are so
aggregations we can we can combine
things together or group them together
and this is what the over keyword does
for us so for this we would use
partition by to specify how we want to
group things all right so in this query
here I'm doing the same thing as before
where I want to combine them together
based on the generate the row number and
for how they produced in their output
but then I'm gonna group them together
based on the course ID all right so my
output would look like this right and so
now again it looks just like the
aviation where now I'm grouped together
based on the order
right pretty simple so let's look at
something more complicated so I can also
order by these I can order them instead
of partitioning them and this is
essentially defining how we want to do
our ordering produced to produce our
outputs if we do this ordering then we
compute whatever this the window
function is that we want to compute on
that so in this case here this is a
sense you can do the same thing I did in
the previous slide where it's going to
more or less group them based on the
course ID but this is doing this by
using ordering rather than partitioning
all right so let's say we want to
compute we're going to find the student
with the highest grade for each course
so what we have here is now we have
nested query so in the outer query we're
just going to well in the outer query is
a server in the inner query we're going
to produce some table result but now
this is a good example we're having a
nested query inside of the from clause
so I have from here and then I'm taking
the output of this inner query and I'm
gonna map that into a sort of a
temporary virtual table called ranking
that only exists for this tuple right so
stead of writing it to a table that are
exist we're writing into a temporary
table I don't say in memory because it
may actually go out the disk but a
temporary tuple table for this to this
query that then gets discarded when the
query is over so in the inner query what
we're gonna do is we're going to go over
the enrolled table and for every single
tuple
we're gonna split them up based on the
course ID that's the partition clause
and then we're gonna sort them by their
grade in ascending order and then what
we produce the window function we invoke
is rank which is the order that they
exist in the in the sort of ranking and
then we take that output write it out to
the ranking table and then in the outer
query we can then do additional
filtering based on the their rank so
this is only produced the tuples that
are that are ranked first right so this
is defining the students the highest
grade for each course
right so the thing to point out here is
I have I'm referencing in my outer query
this ranked attribute here which
actually doesn't really exist in the
database again it only exists within
this query I'm seeing a lot of blank
faces so let's maybe pop up in the
database and see we can do all right so
for this so Postgres is the only one
that actually supports this my sequel
eight supports window functions and the
newer version sequel Lite support window
functions but for simplicity
what does do my and Postgres alright so
this is the query that we had before
right let's break it up and make it and
just do the inner query first and that
way it'll be sort of easy to understand
right so we'll just go back and run this
so again what this is going to do is
going to go over the enroll table it's
going to partition each record based on
the course ID so you see that here we're
for 15 for 45 appears first then 7 21
then 8 26 and then now within each of
these partitions it's the end going to
sort the tuples based on their grade in
descending order or sorry in in
ascending order so be pump comes for see
Abe you'll come from C and then there's
nobody else taking a 26 so the bees by
itself right so that's how we got that
output in the form that we redefined so
now the rank function is gonna be
computed based on where each tuple
appears in the sorted output list so in
this case here this first tuple and
within this partition this guy came
first so he gets Rank 1 this guy came
second so he gets ranked 2 right
if I change this now to be in descending
order
it doesn't still does the same thing but
I could do an order by again and now I
want to go in descending order right
well this is this this is doing the
order by this did the order by after I
did my window function so it doesn't
make sense but the the the main thing of
the the rank is different the row number
cuz the row number two says where do you
appear in the output the rank is where
do you appear in the sorted order okay
yes say it again sorry he says if you
have a rank without an order by will
just return a random order well you'll
still get it ordered by what you have
until get them probably split by
partitions it doesn't have to be because
it's unsorted but that's what you'll get
but now here yet
so there in this case here there is no
sort ordering anymore so everyone has
the rank of one right but it still group
them up together based on what I'd find
it as my partition and that's more of an
artifact of how the database system
actually execute the query rather than
the semantics of the query itself his
question is what is the rank function do
the rank is the rank of the rank
function produces the rank of the sort
order right so if I change my window
function to be row number okay I have my
partition but but it's one to one to one
right because within each partition
that's what I read peer so I've removed
actually the partition by then it should
go through one through five right like
that if I change this now to rank
everything should be one one one right
because there is no soil order
everyone's first
yes our question is a point of view
ranked without an order by yes because
there's no there's no sort order so
there's no ranking all right cool
all right so the last thing we wanna
talk about is si si es complex table
expressions so this is Polly again Mike
this is I find this very interesting
this is probably one more complicated
things that you can do in sequel and
it's gonna look a lot like nested
queries in that you're taking the output
of a query I'm using as the input for
another query but we'll see in a second
what you can do with CT ease that you
can't do in Anessa queries yes so her
question is in the case of this is it
this particular query or it is in
general so a question is is there a
particular advantage of using rank with
a window function over using a group I
so again if you use a group by that's
not going to generate the same you're
not going to get the tuples as part of
the output anymore right
so if I go back so say I do this one
here right row number by partition by so
if I go back and I say I want to compute
now like the the max grade some enrolled
group by course ID like I no longer see
what the original tuples were because
they get collapse together in the
aggregate function the window function
still produces all the tuples that were
in your output but I can now see them as
I can still see them as the output so if
I go back here and if I this may or may
not work but let's see so maybe I try
max grade
petition my course ID yeah so here that
didn't quite work either with that stick
oh you know what it might be now they
didn't like it
there's the rank oh yeah because I'm an
idiot sorry yes it did work I was what I
wanted min yeah so the highest grade at
15 for 45 is was was it be right so I
still see my original to both I still
see one student got to see one student
got a B but the max for that group was B
so I didn't lose the original tuples now
you and your application code have to
derive meanings from this output you
know get the one field that you won but
this has allows you to get and still
keep the tuples in a way you can't with
a group I that's a good question yes
this question is can you use row number
after use an order by so something like
this right and then maybe order by oh
yeah there yeah sorry that's why there's
the as rank so let's do this row numb oh
I'm an idiot sorry no one can see this
how can you yeah sorry my screen shows
one thing this shows another and that
shows this okay we're good right right
now if we if we remove the partition by
and now we can maybe put descending
right so now we'll get 5 4 3 2 1
right the plate replace the rank with
the row number what do you mean let's do
this online because I want to get to see
two E's because he knew it for the
homework before we keep going okay we
can try it afterwards okay all right so
see T's the way basically is gonna work
is that you have introduced with his wif
claws his wif falls it's like a query
that's gonna actually before your your
regular query so we have wif and we're
defining the name or a CTE and then we
have our ask clause and whatever is
inside of the parenthesis after the as
the output of that query would then get
some maps to this are the name for a CTE
and then in the Select query that comes
below it can reference it does just as
if it was a an existing table right so
in this case here what will happen is I
see te that invokes the query select one
right so let's don't have to have a from
clause this just a pollutes this
produces a single tuple with a single
attribute with the value one and then
this other query the bottom to select
star on it and there's outputs that
single tuple so I can start doing more
complicated things I can now bind the
the name or the output columns from the
queries inside of the CTE to given names
and then I can reference them by that
name down below in my in my statement at
the bottom so this this CTE produces a
single tuple with two attributes with
the values one and two and then these
get mapped to the name column 1 column 2
and then in the Select statement below I
can just add them together right pretty
straightforward
so let's go back and try to do that
example we did before where we want to
find the name of the student with the
highest high student ID that's enrolled
at least one course so for this I have
my CTE and the side of that I'll do my
max on the student ID on the enroll
table again that produces one tuple with
that max student ID and then down below
I can do a join where I'm gonna
reference the the CTE that was generated
above me and I just combined together
the max ID that came out of this which
is defined here with my student ID and
then that produces that produces the one
tuple that I want right again this is
another example of how to do the same
query the same at a high level
semantically the same query just written
in different ways so now you may be
saying well how is this any different
than a nested query right the answer is
you can do recursion in a common table
expression that you can't do in a nested
query so bear with me here but this
query is going to produce a sequence of
numbers from from 1 to 10 like a for
loop alright so now we have with
recursive we have a keyword and then
inside of our CTE definition we're gonna
do a union between a single query that
produces the value 1 alright a single
tuple with a single attribute 1 and then
we're gonna then Union that with another
query that actually references ourselves
so that seeing here we're gonna vote on
our own CTE and then we're gonna take
whatever the counter is I've produced by
this and add one to it and produce that
as the output alright and we keep
running this until our where Clause
actually gets tripped up where we try to
go above 10 and then now we stop
producing 2 pools so now we have the
answer that we want that we can then
reference below in our CTE yes you know
it's basically a union right it's Union
with you know with duplicates Union
buddy
for Terry you need sir Union without
duplicates Union with duplicates Union
without all strips keeps duplicates
Union with with out all removes that
might be the way we can test that though
okay so let's do this in Postgres so for
the alright so this is this is the one
query that this is the query that I
showed you right and we produce the the
list of tuples right with a single value
one dn't one this hat right let me try
to kill this alright that better alright
but it be careful about CTE s with
recursive because again net because you
can essentially have infinite loose so
in this query here I no longer have that
counter where it's greater than ten or
produced check any tuples where they're
less than ten this will run actually
forever but what I did first was I
define a told Postgres to again I'm
highlighting here and you can't see it
at all post grass that any query that
runs longer than 10 seconds
automatically kill it so when I ran this
query now it no longer has the where
clause to prevent it from going you know
looking at tuples beyond 10 and so
essentially runs forever
Postgres recognizes that we're stuck in
a query that's taking too long and a go
goes head and automatically kills it yes
[Music]
so sorry so select one just does this
right so now if i do select one Union
all select one right I get like that
so if I think I remove that all yeah you
get it's a without it removes duplicates
right so you know will give me
everything so essentially what's
happening now is I'm calling my CTE say
whatever the whatever tools you have in
the current value take take the output
and then add one to it here right the
the plus one there so this is invoking
on on our our our source CTE called
source for every single to one there
take its output add one to it so in
order to get that to pool it has to go
then invoke that CTE which then produces
back one yeah it won't let you in bogey
because then he knows you're trying to
reference yourself so it's question is
what happens if you if you try to remove
the recursive calls again its sequel its
declared net we know everything you're
trying to do so you're trying to access
a CTE table that's defined by yourself
and it doesn't let you do that
recursive let you do that so let's try
it now also with let's try it by
removing the Union all and see what
happens a big all apartment and it still
produces the correct answer yes you
don't you don't need the Union all right
so in this example here again I'm
synthetically generating a two table
that has a single value of one and then
I invoke a query to get that tuple and
add one to it but then generates a new
tuple which and that can then invoke
again and add one to that and I keep
doing that until I don't produce any
more matches right because any the
recursion ends because I've reached my
limit of ten yes
this question is why why are there not
duplicates because the first time you
devoted you had one six second time you
invoke you would have one and two let's
do this offline let's walk through it
because again we have it we're out of
time all right
yes quick this question is do people use
for Krista see T's is ever a comment yes
absolutely yes so this is actually
finished up very nicely so the the
second point I'm trying to make here is
that in an ideal scenario you always
want to have to be able to compute an
entire query without having to bring any
data locally or not having to go back
and forth right so in a it also provides
by burning as a single query
although the complexity it makes it hard
to do query optimization but if you tell
the David system everything you want to
do with this sort of piece of data then
they can do a global optimization on
that so by having a CTE you're not
having to have additional logic be
somewhere salicin outside the David
system or go back and forth you're
saying here's everything I want to do so
CTS are actually very common especially
in newer applications for cursive CDs
maybe less so but definitely C T's but
again it's another way to write in it
nested query all right the other major
thing that I want to point out is that
again the language is from 1973 or 1974
but it's still widely comment you're
commonly used it's being updated all the
time and learning sequel is important
because you're gonna see this again
throughout your entire life pretty much
every single system database system that
you know it with some minor exceptions
is going to support some variant of
sequel okay so real quick homework one
media after class
I will upload it it'll now be available
basically we're giving you a sample
dataset of his bike share application
from San Francisco it has a few number
tables on it and we're asking you to
write queries on them so for this you
can view everything else galit you
everybody's laptop should already have
sequel light installed otherwise it's
free it's not hard to get so you write
all your queries with sequel light
locally and then you upload them the
grey scope and a run single light there
and do a diff to check them whether you
have the result okay guys I'll see you
Wednesday next week Monday put your
trinket 12 they say we'll make sure
Thayne eyes are straight so it really
don't matter