[Music]
maybe on the Jill's neck parallel so
missing here on the slides is that I'll
send an announcement on Piazza I've
given that we've sort of people are
struggling with this the second project
finishing that up I've bumped a bunch of
other deadlines to give you more time
for the later stuff so homework for we
do like a week or so after it's normally
do now and then same thing for project
three and four okay I'll post a some
Piazza for the for the the the the the
database updates or the Davis talks in
the next two weeks so next week or this
week we have on Thursday the guys from
blazing be be down texts are coming up
to give a Tech Talk and then bright
light is out of London or Norway I think
and they're coming on November first to
give a talk so again I'll I'll send an
announcement about that on on Piazza all
right so today we're talking securing so
everything we've talked about so far and
in the semester has has mostly focused
on single threaded operations right we
did talk about doing concurrent updates
or chrome core operations on the B+ tree
but now we want to talk about how we're
gonna actually queries in parallel what
the kind of optimizations we can give
with this so it sort of goes obvious and
goes without saying but why would you
want to actually run things in parallel
right sorry right because because we get
we get performance benefits there's the
key thing right well be able to run
queries more efficiently because we now
we can break it up across multiple cores
and multiple storage devices and what
you know get faster latency and better
response times the system would end up
being looking more responsive and we'll
see this when we talk about transactions
we have multiple threads updating the
database if you have to go get a page
from the buffer pool and the buffer pool
doesn't have it you have to stall and go
out the disk you want to let other
things keep running and and still make
forward progress all right so this is
sort of the state of the world that we
live in now Moore's Law is over our CPUs
getting more core
we're getting more storage devices like
cloud storage is cheap so think we want
to take all take advantage of all these
things inside of our database system so
the for this lecture we're going to
focus on parallel databases we'll have
two lectures at the end of semester talk
about distributed databases and I'll
cover what the difference is between
these two of them but the high level way
to think about parallel in tribute of
databases are that to the application
programmer the person writing sequel and
submitting them to the system a parallel
database or tribute database it's gonna
look like a single database instance
right like you open up the terminal and
you start writing queries to it you
don't know that the database is split up
across you know multiple cores or
multiple multiple machines right it all
looks the same to you and this is the
beauty of sequel and a declarative
language but you just say hey run this
query and it doesn't matter whether it's
on a single node or a thousand nodes the
database system could take that single
query and figure out what the best way
to execute it is for you so that's the
beauty of what we're gonna take on we
need to take advantage this now inside
of our system so the the distinction or
the difference between parallel
databases and tributed races that I like
to make is the way to think about this
is a parallel database is one where the
the nodes and I'll use the term note
loosely the nodes are physically close
to each other
write a note could be a CPU socket a
node could be a whole another machine
but the idea is that these machines are
close to each other and communicate very
efficiently and so because we're
assuming that they're close to each
other then we don't have to worry about
unreliable communication I said think of
like the most simplest parallel machine
could be a single socket CPU that has
four cores or two cores right that's a
parallel database system distributed
database typically are ones where the
nodes can be are far away from each
other so far away could be you know in
the same you know the same data center
across town or different geographical
region right and in these environments
the typically you're gonna be connecting
to them over a public network if you're
inside of Amazon's data center then it's
but but it's still not the same as like
two sockets in the same box together so
in a distributed database we're not
going to be able to ignore the
communication costs right of you know
sending data from one node to the next
and it also means that we can't assume
that the communication is reliable we'll
see this later on in the semester when
we talk about doing transactions over
over a distributed database
you know this changes how you actually
set up some of your algorithms because
you can't assume that I send a message
to somebody they're gonna get it in the
right order that I expect them to get it
and so in for today's class we're
focused on payload data is we're not
gonna we don't the word with that
problem at all the question is really
how can we take advantage of additional
resources to actuate our queries more
efficiently so the two per type of two
types of parallelism we're gonna talk
about our inner query parallelism and
intra query parallelism so inner query
inter query parallelism is essential
what most people think about in it
payload database is I can run multiple
queries at the same time and they're
gonna run on different threads or
different cords right and we do this
because we want to improve our
throughput latency we don't want to have
everyone stymied or blocked on this one
thread that's executing queries one
after another and Joker intro query
parallelism is where we're gonna take
the operations of a single query I think
of a single query plan and we're gonna
execute those operations in in parallel
this either could be and we'll see this
in a second we go closer to horizontal
parallelism where we're taking the same
operator for executing in parallel
multiple threads or vertical parallelism
where we can actually to different
operators onto different threads at the
same time and so this is be more useful
in analytical queries or long-running
queries we have to scan a lot of data
and crunch it over a lot a lot of tuples
right because because you're usually
gonna be i/o bound or CPU bound in these
in these environments so by having
additional parallelism you you get
better performance all right so to begin
we're talk about different process
models a way to design a parallel
database system then we'll actually talk
about how you execute operators in
parallel and then we'll finish off
talking about how we can
build our system ala to get Iowa
parallelism okay alright so the data
assistance process model defines how the
system is going to be designed to take
advantage of additional resources and
execute multiple requests from the
applications in parallel right and so
instead of using the term thread or
process or you know core I'm gonna try
to use the word worker right because
that can really mean either you know a
bunch of different entities executing
something in our system so the idea is
that we're gonna have some worker in our
database system that's gonna be
responsible for executing tasks and I'll
define what tasks are in a second for
our queries and we want our workers be
able to run in parallel all right so the
three ways you can architect a data
system is that you can have a single
process like an OS process per database
worker you can have a process pool where
you can dispatch work to those there's
workers and then you can have a single
thread per core database worker and
there's trade-offs for all of these so
the first one is process per worker and
again the idea is that a single OS
process corresponds to one worker
typically and it can can be a single
thread for that process and we rely on
the operating system scheduler to decide
what you know what process runs next
which one has higher priority over
another so the idea is that say this
your application you had something in
the front caught it like a dispatcher or
a coordinator or Postgres calls this the
postmaster and the application sends a
request to the dispatcher says hey I
want to execute this query tell me who's
gonna do it for me and the dispatcher
will will hand this request off to a
free worker and then the worker comes
back and tells the application hey I got
your request here's my socket if you
want to talk to me here's where you can
send me all all the requests that you
know that you want me to execute and
then now it's responsible for the worker
to interact with the database to exit
your query and then send you back
results so this was the approach that
most systems were using back in the old
days the 70s and 80s this
what IVM db2 does this Oracle does is
what ingress does this is what Postgres
does right everything I guess why this
is the most common approach in the old
days yes
he says the CPU is only one core I think
of what why would you want to do this
instead of threads let me put it that
way
think of the 1980s right was Linux
around No
did was POSIX and as prevalent as it is
now no all right so there's no you know
P threads right there wasn't a standard
threading library all these different
versions of Unix
had their own threading packages so if
you wrote a multi-threaded application
for one operating system like BSD and
then you want to run on VAX
you probably can't use the same
threading package right but the basic
concept of our process it would exist in
all these different operating systems so
this is why most of these systems in the
old the old days we're implementing this
way so an extension of this is use a
process pool and the idea is that you
still have the dispatcher you still have
something in the front but it's
responsible just handing things off to
whatever worker is free and then you can
go ahead and execute it right there's
sort of a better implementation of the
the single process a single worker per
process and this is used by IBM db2 and
it's also used as of 2015 the latest
versions of Postgres now you sort of use
this sort of model if they could have
one worker communicate with another
worker to handle handed off work
the most common approach that that is
used today and you know if you're
building a new device is from scratch
this is probably what you would use is
you just have a single process for your
database system and you'd have multiple
threads and internally you're you know
how to dispatch work to those threads
and you're scheduling and other things
that the other approaches with processes
would have to rely on the operating
system to use and everything's in the
same address space so you don't have to
worry about using shared memory to
communicate or
inter-process communication
communicating for processes you can just
write in a memory and any other thread
can can read it so as I said this is the
most common approach every single new
data system written in the last ten
years is gonna using this with the
exception of any system that's based on
Postgres because Postgres is based on
the process model so there's a lot of
systems that took Postgres hacked it up
and and put out you know you know
optimized version of it and they're
gonna inherit the the process model
from-from Postgres so we actually still
first started building our own system
here at CMU we did what everyone else
does we start with Postgres rip up the
bottom half and use the top half but we
decided that to get away from all the
the process model we actually end up
rewriting Postgres to use multi you use
multiple threads use threading model and
I have seen some posts on the Postgres
like message board people talking about
a what you know is it worth time for us
looking at switch to a multi-threaded
model because he manages the context
switch inside of our multi-threaded
application is much cheaper than going
across different processes so again the
in my opinion the multi thread approach
is the better way to do this again you
have less let's ever head from a context
which you don't have to worry about
using shared memory the obviously
downside is if you have a rogue thread
that things up and you crash that
thread crashes you take down the whole
thing whereas in a process model
approach the process per worker approach
if one worker crashes then only that
process is killed the whole thing can
still stay up so the other thing I'll
point out too is just because you have a
you know a single you use the thread
pool worker model doesn't mean that you
automatically get in truck where
parallelism all right so my sequel uses
multiple threads but they can still only
execute at least as of 5,7 still can
only execute a one query with one thread
they can't take a query and break it up
across multiple threads right and
Postgres actually uses the process model
and they actually now support intro
query parallels
so the bunch of other stuff you have to
deal with as you can imagine in when we
have a multi-threaded environment a
multi-process environment in terms of
scheduling right so there's a bunch of
other stuff we have to decide our
database system like who's you know who
to hand off tasks to how much resources
those tasks should get what cores or CPU
course we just sign workers to write all
these things are not gonna cover in this
class we'll cover in the advanced class
but the way to think about it is the
same kind of scheduling that an
operating system has to do about its
processes and it threads running in the
system we want to do the same kind of
thing of our database system because we
know what the threads were actually
doing we do we know what data they're
touching and we can be smarter about how
we organize things against the the
decent always knows more yes so this
question is for the process model what
is the advantage of the worker pool
versus the process per worker the idea
so the advantages for this one here from
one query shows up in this worker that
worker is the only thing person that can
execute it right in this one here you
could have free workers that the query
shows up to this guy here but he could
say alright well I know these other guys
are free here so let me hand off one one
piece of my work to them and they'll
execute it and then send the result back
to me all right again so that this won't
be one worker equals one query this one
could be one query it could be used
cross suit across multiple workers and
the obviously you can do the same thing
and in the thread pool the threading
model approach okay so the as I said the
two type of parallelism we can have our
inner query pills and intra query
parallelism so inner query pail ISM just
means that we're gonna have multiple
threads multiple queries better run at
the same times in our system if
everything's read only in this
environment then this is this is super
easy to do because we don't have to
worry about any of the threads
coordinating or the workers coordinated
with each other yeah this guy can run
this query I can run my query and we
have to worry about you know and then
modifying anything
it's when you have queries updating the
database at the same time that's when
trouble starts and that's where you need
something a country to a protocol which
we'll discuss next week to make sure
that each worker only reads the data
that they're supposed to be reading
right we don't wanna test you don't want
to read data from one worker before this
actually saved anything in you know in
another worker so the idea is that a
commercial protocol is gonna have allow
us to give the illusion that each worker
is running in the data is by itself even
though they're not really again this is
really hard this is the thing that
excites me the most in databases and
we'll discuss more of this next week for
Android query parallelism right the idea
is again for a single query can we break
up it's it's it's it's tasks into sort
of sub tasks and run those in parallel
the two approaches that you are
interoperate or parallelism in
interoperate apparel ISM and we'll say
is that these techniques are not not
mutually exclusive just because you're
using the first approach doesn't mean
you can't also use the second approach
well but most people actually only use
the first approach and for all the
algorithms that we talked about so far
did you join to do sorting to do scans
there are parallel versions of all of
these right basically just think about
you hash join instead of having one
thread scan the table and build the hash
table you could have different threads
scan at the same time and build the same
hash table together of course now you
need latches to protect protect them
from each other so again we'll go
through these two approaches one by one
so intraoperative parallelism is also
sometimes called horizontal parallelism
and the idea is that for a single sort
of high-level logical operator in our
query plan like scan table egg we're
gonna instantiate multiple instances of
that operator and then execute them in
parallel and then we're gonna introduced
a new type of operator called the
exchange operator that's gonna be a sort
of a barrier that checks to see whether
all the subtasks for our single operator
are completed and if so then we can then
along the the results to the next
operator in our query plan so the
exchange operator was introduced in the
late 1980s early 1990s from the same
author that did the volcano stuff we
talked about before the iterator model
said it also could be called the volcano
right this all comes in the same paper
and that's the same paper also
introduces this exchange operator and in
most parallel databases they have
something like this that that you would
use to combine things together and this
is also approach is also used in
distributed databases as well let's say
we have our query here we want to do a
joint on a and B and we have a filter or
an A and a filter on B all right so this
query plan I'm showing here this looked
the logical view of the query plan we're
not saying anything but what algorithms
are using we're not saying anything
about you know where the data is
actually stored but now we can just
answer eight multiple we just go to
execute it we can stand she ate these
different operators and parallel with
each other so take the first thing of
this scan on AIM so we can say that
we're gonna break it up to three
subtasks a 1 to 8 a 1 a 2 a 3 that are
each going to be assigned to a single
worker like a single thing of single
thread and I'm going to scan disjoint
subsets of the table and then pass them
up to the next operator in the query
plan all right but actually we can do
some pipelining here because we see that
immediately after the scan we're gonna
do our filter right we're a value is
less than 999 a value is less than 99 so
in addition to doing the scan will also
feed the output into a parallel version
of the filter who then feeds the data up
even further so now again because we
know if to join up for that each of
these guys can then build the hash table
we'll build a single global hash table
for all these threads what do you just
use latches to protect them and then now
this then gets fed up into an exchange
operator again think of this just as a
barrier there's it's just a sort of
physical construct and said write query
plan execution that has no corresponding
logical operator in relational algebra
it's just something internally we're
using to synchronize the different
threads and say we can't go pass in a
query plan until we get the result
all our subtasks I just think there's a
counter inside this thing that says I
know I have three subtasks and every
single time this guy is one of these
task complete since tells an exchange
operator hey I'm done I don't have any
more data to give you then you decrement
that counter by one then when the
counter is zero then you can take
whatever this thing is cold less
together and feed it up to the next
operator all right so we can do the same
thing for B say B is the smaller table
and so maybe we only want to give it two
cores or two workers to execute this and
they'll just can do the same thing
they'll scan and parallel do the filter
and say we're doing the grace hash join
where we want to partition this and so
we'll partition these guys into two
separate buckets and then we have an
exchange operator says hey when you're
done you know you know once all tough
tests are done then we go complete this
so when this exchange operator is done
we have a hash table when this same
exchange operator is done we have our
buckets and then in the once these two
exchange operators are done together you
can then actually now do the join and
again we do this join in parallel
because we've split the the data up over
here and we can now do our probe in a
hash table under different threads and
priests are Appling the same thing you
have exchange or operator above that as
the counter it says when my four
subtasks complete then I get my final
result so is this clear right it's just
it's a construct inside excited the
execution of this query plan that allows
us to call us the results from the sub
task when these workers so that anything
above it doesn't have to know that it
was executed in parallel it just knows
that I got all the data that I needed
right because without this then this
thread might run faster than this thread
so I might start executing things above
in my query plan before I process all
the data that I needed so I may not may
in a beginning false negatives or false
positives yes Gracie could you kids
waiting like this you could split up
this input so that be all the data that
this thing would ever have to have to
access and one of these threads up here
would be all within a single
tition so that you're only mostly
hitting the same part of the hash table
inside this so you get better cache
locality it's like the grace hash join a
variant of this it's a very double use
partitioned okay so that that's
intraoperative parallelism and the idea
is that we're taking an operator we
would normally execute on a single
thread and is breaking up across
multiple threads so with interoperative
parallelism or vertical parallelism
yeah idea here is that we're going to
execute our operator in doesn't have to
be a single thread but for our purposes
we'll say it is for each operator will
be assigned to a single worker that I'll
just be always running and it'll spit up
output to the next you know takes takes
an input does whatever computation and
once on it and then it spits it up to
the next operator when it's done and
then now we can have these different
workers running in parallel these
different operators and then make your
textbook calls this pipeline parallelism
so we just take our example from before
the same query and say we take this
joint operator we don't care what comes
below us was actually feeding data into
thus we'll just assign this to a single
worker as this can again iterate over
the inner table and the outer table
however it gets it and then when it has
a result it admits it as as the output
up above and then in another worker
we're gonna have a you know thread
spinning over and doing our projection
on any data that comes out of this so
again while one thread spin down here
another thread spin down here and
anything that gets its input it is just
the computation and it's listed as the
output all right and then again for
every single operator my query planner I
could assign them to a different worker
so what's the obvious problem with this
yes exactly says two can only go fast as
one so this top guy here he's gonna sit
and wait until he gets data to crunch on
right so we're sort of assigning a
worker to this task but it doesn't have
anything to do it's not gonna do you
know hopefully not doing a busy loop and
just burning cycles that way but it's
essentially we've allocated resources
that can't be used so as far as they
know no sir traditional relational
database minute system does vertical
parallelism right everyone always does
the the horizontal parallelism where you
see this kind of parallelism show up is
in what are called either stream
processing systems or continuous query
systems think of something like I have a
have a sequel query I gave it to my
system and it's just always running
listening on the stream of stream of
updates from some outside source like
think of like caca or something and it's
just always running and any time a new
query comes in then it run runs it
through the pipeline and process it so
you see his approach used in spark
streaming knife i cough go storm flank
and heroine it doesn't make sense in
sort of an ad-hoc query system because
the exact thing he said because you're
the operators above in the tree don't
are can have any work to do so you're
basically wasting resources but in a
continuous query system in a streaming
system there's data coming in all the
time so you're always gonna have some
something to do okay all right so the
everything we talked about so far has
been all about how do we take our query
plan and break it up into subtasks and
run those subtasks on an additional
workers additional computational
horsepower that we have available to us
but the obvious problem is gonna be that
if we had the aggregate data from disk
then it doesn't matter how many CP cores
we have the disk always gonna be the
main bottleneck because this mean way
slower than then you know then
everything else and actually in some
cases if we have a lot of threads trying
to read data
disk at the same time then we actually
get even worse performance because if we
have a mechanical drive and there's arm
dripping around these different points
in the platter and that's gonna be even
slower so we need to figure out how
parallel lies our input data or the
access methods to get data from
non-volatile storage and bring them to
our buffer pool as quickly as possible
so this is what IO parallelism is
attempting to solve the idea here is
that we're going to take our database
management system installation right not
database itself but actually the system
installation itself and split up its
data that is storing across multiple
storage devices so that we can issue
these requests in parallel as much
different ways you can approach this
right you can take a single database and
have it be stored on across multiple
disks you have one one database per disk
you could have one relation per disk or
you can split up the same relation
across this multiple disk using
partitioning or sharding alright so the
easiest way to do this without changing
any code in our data system is to do
multi-disc parallelism and this is we
just configured the hardware or the
operating system to take multiple
drawers and also disks and then have
them appear as a single logical disk to
the database system so the data set our
data system Co doesn't know that we're
doing that were when we do a write or a
read to Ardis device that it's actually
multiple use devices that could be
servicing our request just to also looks
like a single device so we can get this
through our storage appliance right if
you buy sends a box that has multiple
drives together and do this for you or
you can do this through using raid right
every everyone here should have heard of
raid before right good ok so the basic
idea raid is is is you want to make a
bunch of cheap devices or not cheap much
much of independent storage devices
appear as a single single device and the
two most common ways to do this are raid
0 which is striping where this is we
have three different devices and six
different pages and each device is just
in charge of abstruse so now what my
request shows up from a database
estimate says give me page 1
there's some controller or the operating
system knows that here's the device that
actually has the data that you want to
go get it all right the alternative is
to do raid raid 1 or mirroring where
each now device has a complete copy of
the database and so now when I want to
do a read for page 1 any one of these
three devices can service me so now if
you have you know one guys reading page
one well guys reading page two you can
have one device you hit a one request
one device Hannah or another request
again the key thing here is that this is
all transparent to the database system
we don't know anything about these
things being stored in different
locations we just know that there's this
one file or one one table heap we can
read and write from if we now start
moving each our data system and say well
what can we actually do to make things
run faster by controlling where this
data is actually stored right this is
called data as partitioning and the idea
here memory talk about the page
directory would maintain information
about for given page or a table heap
what file or what directory would that
was that data actually being stored this
is where we can start to do this you
know take advantage of different devices
at that level all right so the idea here
is that we when we go fit to page we do
some lookup and figure out what what
device actually has our page and then we
can multiplex them and be smart about
storing different data that's maybe used
together often on different pages so
that we're not trying to saturate this
single duplex there are some tricky
things we have to handle in this
environment we won't talk about logging
just just yet but now we have the
problem of say I'm modifying data on two
different storage devices where do I
actually put the log keep track of what
those changes are and there's a bunch of
are things we can cover let me talk
about logging later in the semester so
partitioning or table partitioning the
idea here is that we're going to split a
single logical table into these disjoint
subsets or segments that we can then
store and manage separately in different
locations on different disks
so again ideally we want this be
transparent to the application we don't
want that right we don't this have the
user rights equal statements that that
are designed to go to the door device
because that way we can move things
around or Neath the covers without
anything
making any changes to our application so
most the time when people like this pie
still common but a lot of times people
start off using my sequel and they hit
the limit what they can do with my
sequel in a single box so they end up
doing what is called sharding where they
have this middleware layer that can
route queries to the actual storage
device that has the data they want to my
sequel installation that has what they
want
like Facebook is the most famous one for
doing this Google used to do this as
well ideally we don't want to have to
have that application code or middleware
of write ourselves we want the data
system to do this for us automatically
right and some some systems can actually
do this other ones cannot so there's two
types of partitioning we can do again
we'll cover this more in detail when we
talk about des tributed databases but
the high level idea is still the same so
this first called vertical partitioning
is that we're gonna split the tables
attributes into different locations or
different files in different storage
devices and whenever we need to get all
the data we need to reconstruct the
tuple we know how to do fetches through
to those different locations all right
so say in this case here accurate before
is really big and the other three
attributes are small so maybe what we'll
do is have all this data here stored in
one partition and then the remaining
three attributes are stored in another
partition and then any query that I
write against this table knows how to
stitch these things back together what
does this sound like we talked about
this before columnstore right same idea
right this is actually a very common
approach actually Wikipedia uses this
right Wikipedia has the for all your
revisions you have the text the revision
you have the metadata about the
provision they actually store them and
actually separate tables and essentially
it is doing vertical partition it's sort
of like a poor man's column store what
most people think about when we talk
about partitioning is usually what is
called horizontal partitioning or if
you're coming from a no sequel system
this is what they call charting the idea
is that we're going to take all the
attributes of a single tuple and store
them in a single location but we're
going to split up what you know what
tuples are stored in what location right
so in this case here we have four tuples
we'll put two tuples in partition two
and two tuples in partition one and
then we have some additional information
inside our system when a query shows up
and says oh I want data at for this key
I know how to go to the right partition
to get that data that I want again we
can store these two different partitions
on different files on disk and different
storage devices or even different
machines right and so the way you can
split this up will come out later is you
can just do simple things like take a
single attribute and hash it and that
decides what partition you're gonna go
to you can do range partitioning or
predicate partitioning or more
complicated things different data
systems do different things and
different workloads want different
things
so for OLTP when you're doing like
single key lookups hash partitioning
works great because you just take
whatever key they're looking up hasha
and that tells you what partition of go
to for doing oh that queries then that
may not be the right thing to do ok I'm
sort of rushing for this but I think a
high-level idea it should be pretty
straightforward right so parallel
execution is important almost every
single davison will actually do this and
all the stuff I glossed over in a big
way like how to coordinate different
thread has scheduled their operations
well some of this will cover in next
week we talked about convergence retool
and some of us will cover in the
advanced class alright so next class on
Wednesday it's sort of a potpourri
lecture we'll talk about different ways
to embed logic inside our database
system to make it do more complicated
things than we can do just through
sequel so talk about stored procedures
used around function whose triggers
views are the idea here is that going to
be instead of having all the logic for
our application inside of our
application we can push some of this
inside our database system and have that
run more efficiently there because we're
closer to the data I mean we don't have
to go back and forth ok all right so in
the last three minutes I want to talk
about the extra credit assignment so yes
you're doing for extra credit is that
you can earn 10% and in your final grade
if you write an article for a online
encyclopedia that we been working on
called the databases of databases so the
idea is that we want to write a sort of
an academic style technical article
about one particular
a system pick whatever one you want and
you revise citations about you know how
to explain how it's actually implemented
what's going on on the inside all right
so I don't care about you know sort of
marketing things to say oh it's fast I
really care about how does it actually
implement converged scroll has it
actually implement logging or indexes or
buffer pool management the things we
talked about in some course that's the
kind of stuff I want in in this article
so the website is DB d DB DB IO
right so I'm currently aware of five
hundred and sixty different database
systems and there's like a search panel
to say you know show me all the
different database systems that are that
use two phase locking or use B plus
trees and then for each of them though
we an article that sort of summarizes
the major points about about their
implementation right so the way this is
going to work is I'm going to post on
Piazza a sign up page a spreadsheet on
um Google Docs pick whatever gave you
some you want to write about I'll have a
list of ones where we already have
articles from previous years so you
can't choose those and then you know if
it's I'll help you sort of guide you to
say here's here's what I expect for what
you need to fill out for a complete
article right if you pick something
super common like Oracle then there's
been a ton of information about this so
I expect the article to be very
comprehensive and complete if you pick
an obscure one that no one's ever heard
of that's defunct then you may have a
hard time finding information and that's
okay but you know we want to know this
ahead of time Savina you know set your
expectations for how much work is gonna
take you to do this so it's it's up to
you to pick whatever database system you
want right as I said I am personally
aware of five hundred and sixty
different database systems so you will
have no problem finding a database
system that a hat that will be
interesting to you right do you care
about graph databases do you care about
distributed databases do you care about
in-memory databases do you care about
databases written in China do you care
about databases that are in the US right
I try to annotate all these different
systems you can just go and pick
whatever one is actually interesting to
you okay
so if you find a Devi system that I am
not aware of please look please let me
know because we want to add it to to the
list
I spent the summer looking at old like
using like news nick posts for like
1990s to find like guys in their
basement writing a TV system and we had
them listed in the system ok so if you
can't buy a system that interest you
something's wrong with you all right all
right and again it goes without saying
please do not steal please do not
plagiarize do not take their
documentation and copy and paste it
directly into their into the article
right you have to provide citations for
all the information you add to this
right you say in this date of a sudden
use two phase locking
I need a citation to the documentation
that says they actually do this okay all
right so I'll post the signup sheet on
Piazza it's first-come first-serve for
the different aliases did you know what
daters do you want to pick and okay now
how the list of ones and you know not a
lot of pic because we've already done
them and then we will post on the
website you know further instructions
with information about how you actually
you know which should be expected in the
article and what the different
categories of features mean okay any
questions I'll play the game
homeys on the cutter y'all will goof
about drink bro quit the bus a cap on
the ice road
on the bow with a blow to the and thank
eyes when I party by the 12-pack case of
a bar six-pack for the act against the
Real ID replete with your drinking by
4:12 they say we'll make some flat out
but sane eyes are straight so it really
don't matter