[Music]
maybe on the Jill's neck to do today is
anyway gonna be bowl until they haven't
started yet
so who here is done I got 1% fifteen
twenty percent okay is there any one
thing that everyone's stuck on it's just
matter sitting through and getting
through the test I notice we would have
trouble with memory leaks right that's
that's real you got to fix those any any
other high-level things you guys are
stuck on definition of what sorry in
terms of what we need are confusion okay
um and you persist on Piazza right all
right so there's a lot of person Piazza
it would be helpful you can send me an
email exactly what the issue is and that
way we can fix it up for next year okay
if it's a combination of like the slides
don't match with what the assignment is
or the textbook doesn't match or that
the reddit doesn't match let me know
what it is when you fix it make it
better but we try to improve it this
year from the issues we had last year so
we always want to get better okay that's
right so homework two is due this Friday
at midnight and then project two will be
going out today and what we're gonna do
this time as I'll say at the end of the
class this is gonna be broken up to two
checkpoints it does in this game we this
is what we learned from last year last
year I was like oh the buffer pool is
easy the B plus tree is gonna be easy to
so people waited to the last minute try
to do it and they're like oh what
the pool or the B plus trees hard as
we'll see today and so what we're doing
is we're having
a check point that's due halfway through
so right again just make sure that you
guys are we start about it started
thinking about it and worked on it and
then there'll be a final you know final
submission where you get the full grid
and everything okay
I said what covered that bien all right
so let's jump in today's material so
today's lecture is entitled index
concurrency control and so this lecture
I actually gave last year near the end
of the semester when we after we talked
about concurrent retour protocols for
for transactions and I decided to move
it up front this year because in the
same way that you guys don't had
questions about oh how do you you know
handle updates when you're doing reads
in your B+ tree I decided to move it
forward now that way we can to talk
about it in the context of what in the
B+ tree is fresh in your mind and you're
gonna need this for the second project
so everything up until till now at least
the last three lectures and we talked
about data structures the B plus trees
the hash tables skip less and all that
for the most part we've been assuming
that we were we were building data
structures that were gonna operate
within a single threaded environment
meaning only one thread was gonna be
reading or writing to the data structure
at a time and we sort of talked a little
bit about how you could do this in a
multi-threaded environment with lock
freed skipped lists but I sort of you
know I was sort of being very hand with
you about it I didn't wanted to sort of
dwell on it because I want to talk about
how we're gonna do things correctly
today so obviously in a modern you know
a modern operating environment on modern
computers yeah you have now CPUs with a
lot of cores and you want to be able to
use all those cores means you want to
have as many threads as possible
potentially reading and writing to your
data structure at the same time and need
to protect themselves from each other so
this is what we're gonna be focusing on
today and that we say else to do it's
not just in the context of having you
know take advantage of all the
additional cores we'll see this later on
but these these concepts are talking
about today or old but from the 1970s
and back then you had sort of once one
CPU socket with one core you don't have
one sort of thread could run at any
given time but because we're a disc
Ordnung database and we said that any
time a thread could touch something
that's not in memory and therefore has
to stall because that's about the system
has to go out to disk and get it we want
to let other threads run
time right so this is why we want to
have we want to have our data show just
be protected from some of these threats
updating it and things reading and
writing at the same time the one thing
also say too is a sort of a spoiler is
that everything we're talk about today
is pretty much used in almost every
single database system one notable
extension is actually both DB doesn't do
any of the things that we're talking
about today right they actually only run
single threaded on a core and now
they're gonna have multiple cores
running each in single threaded mode but
this is gonna allow them to avoid all
the overhead of the index concurrent
role and latching stuff we're talking
about today so I like to say how they're
gonna do it but again they're coming at
the end of the semester and also explain
why they do this approach so this would
work really well for transactions and
OTD workloads not so great for OLAP and
we'll see why later all right so the way
we're going to protect our data
structures is through a concurrent
tutorial protocol so concur trio
protocols is this broad class of
algorithms or methods that software
systems can use to allow simultaneous
threads to do things they do operate on
the same object or thing at the same
time being bei what I want to when I say
anything and to ensure that they're
concurrent operations still produce a
correct result so I was too too vague a
mean bank or two parts here
the term correct and the therm the term
thing so by database thing it could be a
tuple could be a data structure it could
be a page could be a table right it
doesn't matter
and by correctness I had this one quote
because what correctness means from one
protocol to the next can depend on what
their criteria is so sort of two broad
categories of correctness could be a
logical correctness meaning can I see
the data that I'm supposed to see mean
if I if I write something into the the
index or the table if I go back and try
to read it right away and I actually
gonna see it or am I going to see the
things that transactions are threads
came behind me actually updated while
you'll see those and then the other term
of correctness is physical correctness
meaning is the internal representation
of how the the object is being stored in
memory your own disk is that considered
valid or sound and then I've at I mean
there's not gonna be a pointer to some
you know some random location in memory
that we're not supposed to be reading
right if I follow the data structure I
follow my treating pointers
I see the nodes that I should be seeing
so for this we're gonna focus on the
second one physical correctness right
how do we make sure our B+ tree is the
integrity is sound we're gonna focus
later on about logic correctness later
when we talk about transactions or
high-level transactions after the
midterm and I find this really really
fascinating my whole you know I spend a
large portion of my a grad student
career at my early time here at CMU
worried about this problem think about
this problem right this is really kind
of cool thing to say like all right I
can have they're gonna interleave
operations and anyway I want long as it
sort of comes out logically correct I
don't care how to you add you in or
leave them whereas in the physical
correctness there are certain cases
where you have to do things in a certain
order so again we'll focus on the second
one the first one will come up later on
when we talk about transactions and
control for you know higher-level
semantics alright so today's agenda
we're going to focus on different level
a ODEs and then we're primary to spend
our time talking about doing index
crabbing or lat crabbing your latch
coupling and this is what you have to
implement in in the second project and
then we'll talk about how to do leaf
scans safely and then we'll talk about a
simple optimization that was invented
here at CMU called delayed parent update
and sort of an obvious optimization but
we sort of talked about the semantics of
it okay all right so I showed this slide
earlier in the semester and to
distinguish between latches and locks in
the context of databases and I got the
impression that everyone's sort of eyes
were glazed over and what it wasn't
quite sure what I was trying to say so
I'm gonna go over this again because
we're need to understand this for what
we're talking about today so in
databases and database systems there is
a distinguished there's a dichotomy
between locks and latches so locks are
things that are going to use to protect
logical contents of the database as you
can protect the you can protect to poles
you can protect tables you can protect
entire database we're not talking an
underlying low-level things like here's
some here's some region of memory I want
to protect that's not what locks are for
and so the the locks are protect
the logical contents of our database in
this case here that were technological
contests of index and the these locks
are gonna be held for the entire
duration of a transaction I'm having to
find what a transaction is yet just
think of it as a sequence of operations
we want to do in our database I want to
update five tuple and I'm going to do
them atomically right that's essentially
what a transaction is so any lock that
I'm gonna take on an object in in in the
database I'm gonna hold that for the
entire duration of the transaction
that's not entirely true but for now we
just assume that and then the key thing
about locks is also to is that the
there's going to be this sort of
additional process or validation
mechanism that's gonna let us that's
going to decide whether we're our
transactions allowed to proceed or not
and if not write this because of some
violation of lock ordering then we have
to abort our transaction and rollback
any changes so again a really simple
example I need to update two tuples I
get the lock on the first one I update
it I get the lock on the second one but
then that fails I can't get the lock and
I have to abort my transaction so I need
to roll back the change or the first one
and there's some additional mechanisms
we have to implement to do that rollback
now the sting richness with between
latches and again if you're coming from
an operating system background this is
what they would call a lock right like
you're protecting like the underlying
physical data structure of something so
this is the latches are going to help us
protect the critical sections of our
indexes internal data structure remember
I said the distinction between logical
correctness and physical correctness the
lock is to protect the logical
correctness the latches could protect
the physical correctness this is like
the critical section you know we want to
update a pointer to another node and we
don't anyone even wait on anybody to
read that until we're actually done so
for these latches they're gonna be
they're not gonna hold them for a long
time your thread is gonna acquire latch
do whatever needs to do and then
immediately give it up right and means
you can you can even acquire and release
in choir at least the same latch
multiple times during your your
transaction the key difference also to
in the latch and lock is that we don't
need to actually roll back any changes
meaning it's sort of thing it's an
atomic operation either it happens or it
doesn't happen and we'll see it later on
but like if it doesn't happen
if I can't get the latch when I want I
can just loop back and try again right
maybe to spin on it okay so there's this
great table from the the book I
recommended you guys from Gertz graffiti
on the the B+ tree stuff where he's had
to lay it out exactly where locks and
latches are how they're using in a
database system so he says four locks
they're gonna use to be separate user
transactions right updating tuples
things like that and and there were in
there protecting the database contents
like tuples pay tuples tables databases
and we're gonna hold them for the entire
duration of the transaction and we're
have different modes for what kind of
locks we can take for now we can ignore
all this just just you just know that
there's more nodes that there's more
modes than we'll see four latches and
the way we're gonna protect against
deadlocks is to have separate detection
mechanism or resolution process using
various mechanisms like a wait for graph
or timeouts and aborts and the
information about what transaction holds
what lock we stored in a centralized
lock manager all doesn't make sense
later on but for now just again just
distinguishing each of them yes these
question is why do latches only have a
reading right mode as opposed to what
intention mode that's a real that's a
real ass ending yeah all right so again
in the database literature can
distinguishing locks and latches there's
a shared lock you can get a shared lock
on a on on a tuple you get a read latch
on the memory of that tuple
it's a way to think about all right so
the latches are gonna be use to protect
threads from each other and they're
gonna be only used to protect the in
memory data structures like the P plus
tree will be building here so that means
that we don't ever you know write in the
information out the disk about what
latches are being held because does it
make sense we come back we boot the
system back up these latches aren't
around anymore so we protect the
critical sections of our data structures
when we have two modes read and write
which we over the next slide and then
the way we're going to avoid deadlocks
or handle deadlocks is through us being
good programmers good database
developers and software engineers
there's through coding discipline so we
need to be careful out write our code to
make sure that we can't have dead locks
in a way we can avoid deadlocks is
basically if I can't get the latch that
I want I have to know it in what context
I'm trying to acquire that latch and
should I wait to acquire or should I
kill myself right away all right in the
context of a chance action with a lock
that logic is is managed by both there's
some kind of centralized coordinator
like a lock manager okay all right so
again this lecture is focused on the
latches because we're protecting the the
internal data structure of our of our b
plus treating all the locks self will
cover after the midterm in lecture 17
again I find this all of this stuff
really fascinating so sort of what his
question was about you know can you have
a read latch look I share mutex the
answer is yes we're just calling this a
read mode so a read mode latch can you
can have multiple threads acquired this
the same latch in the same mode multiple
times so if I come along and I want
acquire this latch and you hold it and
you have it in read mode and I want in
the read mode then I can also piggyback
off you and also acquire it and
internally the lack maintains a metadata
to say alright this thread has met has
me in read mode and this thread has me
in read mode and I know that one guy
releases it it's still being held by
another thread so it's not like I
released the latch entirely for the
write mode only one thread is allowed to
hold the latch in that mode at a time so
if you cut if you already had the latch
in read mode and I want to get in write
mode I can't I have to get either
blocked or wait or abort myself and if
I'm holding a reit latch and then nobody
else can acquire it at the same time
that I am right so there's a sort of
obvious compatibility matrix like this
the way to think about this is say one
side is what the latch mode currently is
in and the top the top sort of set of
columns is what latch mode somebody was
acquired in so if somebody holds it in
read mode I can acquire it in read mode
and no other mode and everything else
gets is is denied and what happens when
you denied depends on the implementation
and in what context are actually trying
to acquire that latch
all right so now using these latches we
can talk about how to do we want to do B
plus the purchased or how to build a
multi-threaded B plus tree so there's
two types of problems we need to deal
with the first problem is when we have
two threads trying to update the same
page at the same time to maybe to try to
insert or update the the key value pair
arrays inside of it right and this is
sort of obvious way to fix this right
you just take a read latch on that node
sorry you take a write latch on that
node and only one thread is allowed to
update at a time and then when you're
done updating it you release the write
latch and then somebody else can go
ahead and update it right that's that's
a no-brainer right that's we all know
that from your basic systems programming
the one that's more complicated though
is dealing with traversals because now
you could have one thread traversing
down to the tree try to get to a leaf
node and while another thread is doing
an insert or a delete that's gonna cause
me to either split or merge or remove a
sibling around and that could foul up
the other thread because now I'm moving
moving memory around I'm changing
pointers so now point to new locations
right and that becomes problematic cuz
now we could have if we have a race
condition where I copy the data to it to
a new location in memory but before
update the pointer someone follows the
pointer to the old location but maybe
I've already you reused that memory for
something else alright we're talking
microseconds here or nanoseconds but
this you know with enough you know bad
things can happen bad things can happen
bad things will happen so we have to
protect ourselves so it's like a really
simple example of what this looks like
so we set we have a simple B+ tree like
this and then what I'm doing is I'm
labeling the nodes on this side cuz I
gotta focus on the other side just one
letter so that we know what we're
talking about as we go down so say I
have one thread and they want to delete
44 it's down here at the bottom so it
just goes down one after another until
reach the bottom falling the separate
keys decide which way it wants to go but
then and then it goes has hasn't delete
this but now our node I here at the
bottom is is not less than half full
it's empty so we need to rebalance and
we'll do this by stealing 41 and and
from out from our neighbor and copying
it over
but now at the same time thread to comes
along and they want to find 41 so they
do the same thing they coming down and
they're coming along down here and they
get down to D and at this point when
they're they look at D they see the
separated key says oh well anything
between 38 and 44 is that node H so I
know I need to go there but in between
this time sorry I'm gonna fall at this
point in between this time the other
thread moves 41 over so now I go down
here and the thing that I thought should
be there is not there right so this
seems like this is sort of a logical
problem right because with like I
thought 44 was there but it's not there
it's actually a physical thing because
the data structure is telling you I'm
should go to this node age you'll find
what you want but it's no longer there
right because then after the fact the
right the D got updated with the correct
separator key and so any thread coming
behind this shirt on to I right so this
is essentially what what we need to
protect ourselves from so the way we're
gonna do this the sort of standard
technique is called lat crabbing or
latch coupling so I when I you know when
I learned databases when I was younger
they taught us the term latch crabbing
sometimes it's called latch coupling I
forget what the the textbook says but
they mean basically it's they mean
exactly the same thing so Wikipedia
might call it one versus the other
so latch crabbing is going to be a
protocol that is gonna allow multiple
threads to access and modify our B plus
tree at the same time and not have any
of these these problems and so the the
idea is pretty pretty straightforward
anytime we we want to reenter the tree
we always have to get a latch on a
parent node and then we try to get the
latch on the child node the direction we
want to go and then if we're able to get
that latch we move our thread down to
the next node and then we go ahead and
and release the parent node latch if
that node is considered safe and so if I
safe I mean that we know that based on
whatever operation we're trying to do
whether it's an insert or delete that
the node that we just moved to would not
need to be split or merged meaning it
can accommodate whatever the change is
that may be below it right so if if my
node is full
and I'm doing an insertion then I may
have to split that node my parent node
so therefore I could split the node I'm
at and therefore had to update my parent
node so therefore I don't want to
release the latch my parent node same
thing for delete if it's if it's less
than half full then I may have to do a
merge and therefore I type my parents
not safe either all right so let's see
basic how this work right first search
it's pretty straightforward right you
take real a choose all the way down
right you cry the latch on your child
the one the one that's below you if you
acquire you move down there and then you
always unreleased your parent right
because you know searches are obviously
read-only so you're never going to
modify the structure of the tree doing
is sort of delete you start the route
and go down inquire write latches all
the way down and then as you go down if
you know that the the child node you
just jump to is safe then it's you can
go ahead and release the latch for your
parent or anything above it okay let's
look an example so say that our thread
here wants to search for 38 so we
started off at the very beginning we get
the read latch on the root a then we
jump down get the real a and B and then
move down there again right and this
point here since it's read-only it's
safe for us to release the latch on a so
we go ahead and do that then move down
further the latch on D go down there get
to latch on H go down there and then
we're done I mean we can read the item
that we wanted right pretty shape word
and that's so the coupling or the
grabbing part the crowding part says be
like the way a crab walks so you're
releasing these these latches behind you
all right let's see about we want to do
a delete so we started ready to get any
one leap key 38 here at the bottom so we
start off the right latch on a and then
we get the right latch on B and then
move down now at at this point since B
is really two keys in here but this B is
half for less we don't know what's gonna
happen below us at this point right we
only know with that our current node and
the one that came behind us so at this
point here we don't know whether the if
we go down to D whether it's going to
have to do a merge because it looks less
than half full so at this point here we
can't release the latch on on a because
we may have to merge or B right
so then we get down to D and then now we
recognize that D is completely full and
we're doing a delete here so no matter
what happens below us D can absorb if
you will any change without having to
propagate it back up into the tree so at
this point here we can release the latch
on a and B our entire lineage back up to
the root so one key thing to point out
here is that we're gonna release the
latch the latches in first in first out
order that we acquired them so I'm gonna
release the latch on a first followed by
B and we take a guess why exactly yeah
so she said you want somebody to access
a as soon as possible right so there's
no correctness issue right because if I
release be here you know it's not an
issue because no one can get to it
anyway because I had the right latch on
on a on the roof so if I release the
latch on a first when we're talking
again nanoseconds or microseconds here
but it opens up a window now where
someone can come in and and and possibly
get into our tree and they may name may
not even going down the same same path
that we are then they may be going down
another path on the other side of the
tree but again everyone's always stymied
on on the root I'm blocked on that so as
soon as I can release that the better it
is alright so then I get my right latch
on on H I move down and I go ahead and I
can delete 38 and again there's no we're
out more than half full so there's no
change I need to make to anybody above
it so I didn't have to hold the latch
for that okay all right let's see now an
insertion so on insert 45 same thing I
started off I get my right latch on a ok
the right outlook speed and move down
and again at this point I can release a
because I know I have a free slot or
freaky space in B so no matter what if I
have and I have to split below I can
absorb a new a separated key at B so we
can release the latch on a then we get
down to to get the latch on I and this
point here I has room so we can release
the latch on B and D all the way
right actually in this case here 4d
going back and here I couldn't release
latch on B because I don't know what's
below me at D so I and I don't have any
more space and take another key so I
have to maintain the latch on B because
I may have to go all the way up and and
do splitting but when I get down to I I
say oh I have a free space I'm not gonna
have to do a split so therefore I can
release the bat flip the latch on B and
D okay alright so let's look one more
example inserts what you do have to do a
split so we wanna start key 25 same
thing start off one on a get delete we
get the right latch get the right latch
on B move down at this point here B's
not gonna have to a split so we release
the roulette right latch on a move down
to C same thing we have a free space so
we're not gonna have to do a split at C
so we release over like right latch on B
then we get down to F and now we see
we're gonna have to do a split so for
this we can't release the right latch on
C because we're gonna have to put
something in there alright cuz we're
doing a split on on F right so we keep
the latch on a parent node and then we
do our insertion update the separator
key and add at our new page right and
then once that all that's done we
release all the latches and now our new
key of 25 is is visible to other threads
and we're the integrity of the data
structure is still sound right so if
anybody coming behind us is doing a
lookup right they want to look in these
pages they would get blocked at this
point because they're not gonna be able
to get any latch on C yes his question
is the the criteria for judging whether
a node is safe or not I'll just say what
it is so it's it's if you're gonna if
you're doing the insert if the if the
node is not full that means that no
matter what happens below you if you do
a split that you can you gonna you could
have room to take a new separator key at
that node at your parent node so
therefore you're not going to split that
node so you don't need to to hold a
right latch on that because you're never
going to
changes propagated beyond the one you're
at right so at this point here going
back so we're here we get our right
latch on C and then we jump down and now
at this point we know we're doing an
insert so no matter what happens below
here whether we split or not or even if
we do split that we can put it in we
have room to put a space in here so that
means that we're never gonna have to
split this and therefore update B so
it's safe for us to release the latch on
on D and then when we get down here we
say oh well now we actually do a
split so now we can't release our latch
on C because we're have to update it and
we do we do our split that way yes his
question is would you need thousand of
new Texas free Street yes right buddy so
I don't wanna get into the
implementation side of things for these
you'd you do wouldn't want to use like a
like the standard standard template
library mutex which is just a linux
futex right used when he's a spin latch
I mean just you have a single atomic
like integer and you do compare-and-swap
to acquire if you can't acquire you spin
on it that's that's the fastest way to
implement a latch so now we're talking
like in each page you can do a I think
you can do 8-bit atomic latches because
we don't care about the value and that's
not true because if you if you need to
keep that are writers leaders or writers
you do have a it has to be a little
better and then way you implement that
is you could have a single counter for
the right latch and then a counter for
the the read latch at any time you
acquire you add one to the read latch
and you know the new subtract one when
you release it you can do that
atomically so we're maybe talking 64
bits per latch it's nothing all right so
I started said those are already and
when I asked I asked before what was the
first step that we did in in every
single case we were updating the the
tree what's the very first step block
the root exactly yes right and if you're
doing all these updates you're locking
and within a right latch mode so nobody
can even read it all right so this
becomes a major bottleneck because every
single time you want to do anything
you're you're locking the route and
essentially making this be a serial
single threaded data structure so this
will become a major bottleneck in a
highly parallel environment because
everybody has to go through this sort of
one contention point even if they go
down to different parts of the trees
they're always sort of starting at the
same spot so we need to we need
something better and so the this album
knows when I have a name it's sort of
it's it's to be customized named after
the people these two Germans Bayer
slotnick sometimes it's called alpha
mystical a latching algorithm right it's
an old thing as from like 1977 right but
the idea is pretty straightforward and
this is pretty much what everyone all
the this is that the very least would
every system that uses a B+ tree that
must be mostly threaded will do
something like this there's a bunch of
other optimization if we can do we're
not gonna cover but this is what every
what everyone does so this better
latching algorithm is considered an
optimistic algorithm meaning it's going
to assume that if you're doing an insert
or delete that the leaf node that you're
going to be modifying will be safe I
mean you're not gonna have to do a split
or a merge right and this sort of makes
sense right by my simple example I'm not
showing nodes with two keys but as we
said before in a real P plus tree your
your node size is going to be at least
your page size or larger so like four
kilobytes or even or potentially larger
than that at least in a disk coordinate
system so the likelihood that you're
gonna have to do a split or merge for
every single insert or delete is it's
pretty low so instead we're gonna assume
that we're not gonna have to do a split
or merge and therefore we're gonna take
real latches all the way down and and
then right before we get to the leaf
node then we take out we take the right
latch on that leaf node and then if we
find out that we are gonna have to split
or merge then we just we abort our
operation go back and retry it then take
the right latches as the normal protocol
is by the idea here is that you're in
again you're assuming your splits are
plus a rare your merges are rare so
don't take right latches give that limbs
concurrency and if your
you just go back and restart it right so
let's see how this works so we go back
and do a delete of 38 damn we start here
at the root again instead of requiring
the read latch so you said of acquiring
the latch in right mode will card in
read mode and then we just go down and
do our standard crabbing and coupling
all the way down and then here when we
get down to D we take the right latch on
H jump down here we recognize that we're
safe we can do our delete without ever
have to split we release the latch on D
the read latch go ahead it and then do
our delete right it's pretty obvious all
right so let's see now that insert on 25
so I start again the read latch on a
real Achin b traverse down release that
go to C Traverse down the lease on B
then I get down to 2f I recognize here
that I'm gonna now have to do a split so
therefore I I needed that right latch on
C but I didn't get that as I went down
because I was assuming I wasn't gonna
have to split so in this case here I'd
recognize that my leaf node is not safe
so therefore I restart everything and
take right latches all the way down so
again this is an optimistic algorithm
the surgery the surgeons are just the
same you take just do reach read read
latch coupling re-latch crowding on the
way down and then again for inserts and
deletes you set latches as as all the
way down as if you were searching with
you know in read mode and then you get
the right latch on the mote on the leaf
node you want if it's not safe you
restart and get right latches that way
you get the you get the right latches
that you need and in the tower hierarchy
with the tree going down to your leaf
node otherwise you just do it so again
this is an optimistic algorithm because
it's assuming that the be the likelihood
that you're gonna do a split or merge is
rare and therefore you're you you end up
saving they're saving work and improve
your parallelism because you make this
assumption but obviously if you're wrong
then you're actually getting being worse
off and you would have been if you
didn't actually take this optimization
because now you're actually doing sort
of almost double the work so I do my
traversal with real ashes get to the
bottom recognize that my leaf node is
not safe now I have to abort and come
back and do it all over again so that
work I did to figure out that I wasn't
safe is wasted and so there are some
optimizations you can do to provide
hints about what's below you in in the
in the in the tree you know they don't
have to be entirely accurate all the
time but you know the worst you that the
less accurate is the wrong ger the more
the more incorrect your your assumptions
or approximations are going to be and
your Android actually doing much worse
but you're wasting your wasting cycles
or wasting instructions doing work that
get the ends up getting thrown away yes
this question is do you always need to
start at the root node so yeah there are
there are some optimizations where you
can have like a hash table on the side
to say hey if you really want this key
here's the node to jump to in general
yes mates you don't have to the that's
like an extent that's like at an
advanced optimization that like people
have tried there's a literature from
like early 1980s that discuss this of
course now yeah this is what I was
trying to say also - is like you either
have to make that hash table that jump
allows to jump to a node always be in
sync or you can start update it lazily
but now you may end up guessing wrong
based on it and have to restart and
retry always going through the root
right so there's sort of this trade-off
between like alright I most the time is
gonna be right and when I'm wrong it's
not a big deal for me to go ahead and
just undo what I did
so he's quite a statement is in this
example here I can like in this case
here I I went when I went down I could
cheap track of the path I went to and
then maybe when are we starting from the
route jump to another location but again
like I need to protect that right
because by the time I come back and
restart another thread could have like
trashed this C or delete a bunch of
stuff and now I'm jumping to a bad
location and regarded so again this is
like I always say that bad approximation
is is a bad one we do this in our BW
tree which I don't talk about here that
we implemented where we if you want to
do range scans in reverse direction
because it only has sibling pointers in
one direction you could keep the stack
of how you got down there how you got to
it the reason why we do is in the beat
of a tree and it's hard to do it in this
is like to be in retreat there's a
separate mapping table says if you want
this note ID here's the memory address
in this they're like page IDs and then
the page ID mint might not be there
anymore
right because I might've got swapped out
the disk okay cool alright so the one
observation I want to make now is that
in all the examples I've shown so far
we've had our threads acquire latches in
what I call a top-down manner meaning we
start the root we get we get to left on
that root and then we the next latch
what you want to get always has to be
something that's below us that the node
that's below us we never go in the
opposite direction in our tree remember
I said earlier that although there's no
reason you couldn't have pointers from
the from a child to a parent almost
nobody actually implements it that way
so no one no one's gonna be going in
reverse direction everyone's always
going to the top down so the benefit of
this and it's sort of obvious but is
that you can never have deadlocks
because the the order in which threads
try to acquire latches are always in the
same direction
like I can't get my latch on this this
child know that I want unless I had to
latch on the parent so nobody else is
coming in the other direction trying to
get the latch on the node that I have so
this so in this case here as as we're
going down if we try to get a latch and
we can't on a node then we can just wait
because we know there could ever be a
deadlock and at some point whatever the
threat is is that how was the latch is
doing something they'll be able to
release it and then we can go ahead and
acquire it all right so again if you're
implementing implementing this as a spin
lock we just sort of spin on on the the
variable that maintains the latch and at
some point it'll change then we can we
can we can acquire it and in the week we
can continue with whatever operation we
wanted to do and does it make sense
I'll save you think about it like if I
traverse the tree and I can't get the
latch on the node that I want to go to
if I abort and restart then the
likelihood I'm just gonna come back to
the very beginning the root and come
down to the exact same location again
and just get stymied or blocked on the
latch I couldn't get before so you just
sort of spin and wait but as we people
are asking earlier I think I was last
week about these sibling pointers but
how are we actually handle the case
where we had threads down now down the
leaf nodes and they want to go left and
right because we have these sibling
pointers so let's look an example here
so we have a really simple B plus tree
we have this the keys 1 through 4 and
our thread here wants to find all the
keys that are less than 4 so we just do
the standard optimistic latch crabbing
technique we talked just talked about we
cry the reed latch on a then we jump
down get the real ash on C and then we
can our thread moves down the C so now
as we're scanning along we would we
would recognize that we still need to
read data on on this list leaf node over
here because we want to find everything
less than 4 so it's basically from 4 to
negative infinity so we want to go all
the way to the end of the tree I'm not
really talked about this here but
there's things called like fence keys or
or sibling keys where you can sort of
maintain a hint to say oh by the way if
you're jumping this direction this key
starts at 2 right there's some
needs to do like that but we can ignore
that for now okay so if I want to go now
and Traverse along my sibling to get to
B I have to do the same lat coupling or
carving technique that I did before I
can't acquire the latch on on B unless I
hold the latch on C so since I hold the
latch on see I'm up it's allowed to go
ahead and get the latch on B and then it
moves over to to this node and it's safe
for it to release C right the same
technique that we did before we're just
moving along horizontally so let's look
at more complicated example it's the
brig another thread in right yeah these
are both read-only so t1 was to find
keys less than for t2 wants to find keys
less than greater than 1 so the same
thing they both start at the same time
we acquire the read latch on on on the
root node a thread 2 gets the real a on
B moves down thread thread one gets the
read latch on C moves down and then now
they won't again but they want to both
scan and in both directions and at this
point here and since the read latches
are compatible with each other the
thread one can get the real a on B and
thread two can get the read latch on C
and then cuz that latch can be held by
both threads at the same time in the
same mode and then they they swap over
to our scan and at this point now thread
1 will release the latch on on C and
thread two releases latch on B and we're
fine right this is read-only so it's
super simple there are no dead locks
so now let's throw in some updates so
thread one wants athlete for and thread
two once the find key is greater than
one so say we start off thread 1 sorry
thread 2 gets the read last one a and
say also till we're doing on the mystic
lock coupling so we're gonna get the
real a CH on on our parent and only get
the right latch on on the root on the
leaf node so thread thread two goes down
to be with the read latch thread one
goes down to C with the right latch at
this point we released a latch on a
because we're doing a lot coupling but
now thread two once
to scan across leaf nodes and get the
real a Chauncey but it can't because
thread thread one already holds this
latch in right mode all right so what
should happen here take a guess
should it wait she's shaking her head
yes raise your head up you think I
should wait hmmm about half bridge Hana
I think it should just kill herself
raise your hand if you're a thug and
pink thread too should kill thread one
and steel is latch which is actually a
real thing does not you know maybe not
for this all right so we don't at this
point thread two doesn't know anything
about what thread one is doing right
these latches are sort of the sort of
thing that looks like dumb blocks or
knees weren't interlock with are dumb
latches right it just knows it's in
right mode I can't get a read mode latch
because that's not come out with me so I
don't know I have no idea what it's
doing so what will happen here is rather
than wait around and see whether thread
one is gonna give up that latch I'm just
gonna go ahead and kill myself right and
abort my operation and this come back
and retry it right and the reason why we
want to do this is go otherwise we could
have a deadlock because like I said
threat to doesn't know that thread one
is either you're just gonna do its
update on see and then immediately give
up the latch or it's gonna scan across
and try to get the latch on B which it
holds and therefore you would have a
deadlock so to avoid all this but how to
do anything sophisticated we just say I
can't get the latch I want I'm dead
restart right and that makes the
protocol super simple it's not the most
efficient thing right because again we
can try to be sophisticated and say oh
well I know that it's just doing you
know a single delete it'll give it up in
a few microseconds so let's say for me
to do it I don't do any of that I'd say
I can't get it
I just abort and and retry this is how
so this is how we're gonna have yes the
bat
so his question is would it be more
efficient if the writing thread thread
one would kill thread would kill the
thread - if it sees it waiting for the
the latchet holds so he says the so
threat thread - could just spin here
keep you trying to car the latch and
then if thread one wants to go over to
the B and sees that thread two is
waiting for it it'll kill it otherwise
he just lets ahead and spin it um so the
first question is where are you gonna
maintain that thread one is thread two
is is spinning for the latch on C right
you have to maintain that somewhere like
some global data structure right or you
have to you have to have your thread and
look through every single location of
every every transaction or every thread
that could be running say hey are you
waiting for the thing that I have right
you can do it but it's a bunch of extra
work and it's not worth it and this
makes coding this thing way more way
harder all right so it's just better off
just to immediately kill yourself and
then just retry it we'll see something
like this when we talk about terms like
transaction blocks but in this case here
again we want these critical sections to
be as short as possible right so it's
better off to saying I can't get it boom
don't restart then try to do something
way more complicated yes
this question is if two writers are
trying to go in in both directions if at
the exact moment they try to get the
right latch on the other direction then
yes they would both restart but you know
in if you think about in practice one's
gonna be slightly behind the other so
the the first guy would try can't get it
he kills himself the second guy would
then be able to get the latch right but
it can't happen
so again the main thing I want to
emphasize here is we don't need to be
smart we don't need to be clever to be
super simple and that's actually gonna
turn out to be the most of most
efficient way to actually implement this
and we could have you know sir the
question he was he was that the
suggestion he had was oh well I can look
to see the thread one sees that threat
to is waiting for me therefore I can
maybe kill him or give him a hint about
something I had to store that somewhere
I could store that now in my node to say
hey here's the list of threads that are
waiting for you but now I'm storing that
instead of actually well data all right
because that need to be a bearable size
because knows how many threads could be
accessing this so as far as I know
nobody does this everyone just does
something really simple yes so his
question is when I say a thread kills
himself this guy dies and he restarts is
he going to this thread going to just
maybe wait a little bit and then retry
or just try it right again depends on
the implementation right so you can do
like a standard technique would be
what's called a sort of exponential
back-off
it's like TP tcp right so I try right
away if I know that I restarted twice
the me the next time I'll wait half a
millisecond and then maybe a millisecond
two milliseconds and so forth yeah so
his statement is okay there's a
possibility your thread could get
starved that no matter how many times it
tries it can never get it done that's
solute yes again we'll see this in
transactions with logs and there's a way
to handle this by because now we have
some global information about what what
transactions are running you can do
things like give priority to the oldest
time it turns actually the oldest
timestamp like it you know this
so we I was sort of joking about like in
this case here when I decided should I
wait or should I kill myself or kill him
transactions with locking will do we'll
make those decisions in this case here
we just we don't do any coordination we
just kill ourself immediately yes
[Music]
question is say 81 is a read lock on C T
2 has a write lock on this what should
happen in read mode in write mode her
question is do do do-do-do threads I
want to get latches in write mode have
higher preference to latches in read
mode again like you you'd have to have
some kind of coordination mechanism to
make that kind of decision right because
in this case here all you know at this
point here is that this thing is in
write mode in that tit right you don't
know that this guy's trying to come over
here and get this in in read mode or
some other mode right you just say I
can't get it I just kill myself right
away the most simplest thing actually
turns out to be the best all right yes
more okay so his daemon is why is
retrying better than just waiting so the
way over the face it is not waiting
indefinitely been waiting with the time
out so you could in theory say all right
I think this guy's gonna give it up
which is probably true so maybe I'll
just spin for a millisecond and then I
if I get it great if not I restart you
could do it that way but in the end like
you can it's it's
in that case again you're deadlocked for
that one millisecond until you timeout
right your block you're not right in be
very careful you could you can wait
there could be a deadlock but you need a
timeout
you don't wait forever because again
with laches there's no like like God and
the clouds have come down and say oh you
guys are deadlocked let me fix this
right we don't have that here we had
that for transaction locks forgiven
we'll cover this later we don't have
here we have nothing all right we're
like driving a car without a seatbelt
right so we could have this guy spin on
this latch for one millisecond if he
gets it great if not abort and restart
right doubt about that would work as
well that's that's still correct but
again for that one millisecond if we
have a deadlock we're doing nothing
right and again it's more like in this
simple example it's only a two-level
tree right so there's only I only have
one latch here but like if he's
modifying bunch of crap I may hold a
bunch of right latches above me and
that's blocking everybody else so again
you could be more sophisticated and say
all right well I I'm this guy here it
has a right latch and I have like five
right latches above me and therefore I
want to go this way and I can't get it
so I thought I should abort right away
because I released a bunch of latches or
if I know I only have one right latch
then yeah who cares the nobody else is
blocked behind me so I'll wait for a
millisecond you could do that but still
it's still correct but then what
commercial systems do for this I don't
know I don't I
actually I don't know what post Christ
does either or my Siegel okay all right
so again the the the main takeaway
Howard Hanna leaf nodes is that we just
do our the the the the coupling of the
crowding along the leaf nodes but if we
can't get the latch we want we should
just kill ourselves right away right
which is different than how we got
laches going top-down going top-down we
were allowed to wait because we know
there could never be a deadlock going
left and right there could be a deadlock
so therefore to just avoid all this we
just kill ourselves right away and again
this is this is us being good
programmers good database developers and
software engineers that have to design
our data structure to be B thread safe
and protected all right it's it's hard
to do all right so the last thing we
talked about is a optimization again
that was better here at CMU for the be
linked from the bead link tree paper
which was from like 1981 or something or
maybe in the 70s by Philip Lehman who's
he's in the dean's office at SCS so can
the the the the only thing you'd really
understand about the be link tree is
that it has the pointers the sibling
pointers along the leaf nodes the
original B plus tree doesn't have that
every modern implementation has this
this aspect of the p1 tree so the
observation that they made was that any
time that I was gonna do an insert that
if I had to split my node my leaf no
because it overflowed then at meet that
I would have to update at least three
nodes in my tree or write to three nodes
so you got the right to obviously to the
node that you're splitting the need
right to the other node that you
overflowed into and write all its keys
into it and then you have to write into
your parent right to say here's the new
separator here's the new key here's the
here's the pointer to the new leaf node
that I just created you may have to go
out further in the tree but for our
purposes now we can we can ignore that
so the optimization that baby posed was
that anytime that a leaf node overflows
you can do a split just delay updating
its parent node right don't take the
right latch on it give it up right away
and this at some later point you'll go
ahead and update it as well see in a
second it still guarantees that the that
the the contents of the the B+ tree is
sound and the internal internal
representation so say I'm going to use
that example again well we want to
insert 25 so we do the optimistic alap
coupling that we showed before we take
all the way down we get down to see
again we still take the reed latch
release on B now we do the right latch
on F and now we see that we're gonna
have to do a split but instead of
restarting which actually would have to
do in this case here because yeah
instead of restarting and coming back
and getting the red latch on C we just
keep going and then what we're gonna do
now is we're gonna go ahead and do the
split on F we hold the Reed latch Tory
we hold the right latch on it so we can
go ahead and do that no one's gonna get
to us and what we're not gonna update C
because we don't hold a latch on that
alright so we we insert 25 we add the
new leaf node we connect it to our earth
or the sibling pointers and then we're
done and then now we're gonna do is
we're gonna post some information in our
data structure to say that the next time
someone comes along and takes the right
Lac on C go ahead and add separator key
that we didn't put into it right so at
this point here we've inserted 25 we
split with 31 it off and you know but it
has 31 at this point here if any threat
comes along it's looking for 25 or 30 1
it can find it even though we don't have
this pointer from C to this new node
here right if you look at this if I want
so if I'm looking for 31 I'll go from 20
I go down this way 35 go down this way
31 is greater than 23 so I go here and
then there's some little information we
can we maintain about what the the next
sibling key would be so we would say all
right well I know that if I'm skating
along here that I'm looking for 31 my
range for this node F is 23 to 25 but oh
by the way if you're looking for
something greater than from 25 but less
than 35 go over and follow this node
here so I can still find 31 if I'm
looking for it I just didn't do it
through C I just did about following
along scanning along the leaf nodes and
again I do that leaf node scan crabbing
that we talked about before so now it's
some later point some of the thread
comes along and say it wants to do an
update
and it comes down here you've read Latin
B and then it knows that there's a
pending update foresee that needs to be
applied it can go ahead and inquire see
in right right latch mode so then and
when it comes there says all right now
actually I can post my new separator key
31 and have it point to the the new page
at the other guy created right the idea
here is again that we wanted we want to
delay having your update because
otherwise we'd have to review the
restart acquire the right latch but we
can we come back the second time we can
kind of acquire the right latch on C and
actually do the update right it's pretty
obvious optimization actually I don't
know how common this is but it does
appear in the literature a lot of times
when people talk about B plus trees
please the modern variants of them okay
so any questions about latch crabbing or
coupling in D plus trees yes the back
this question is it's a late update only
on insert yes all right so hopefully I
made it sound well actually not
hopefully but hopefully I conveyed to
you that at a high level the protocol of
making a B+ tree thread save is easy to
understand but I would say in practice
it's actually very difficult to
implement and get correct now for the
guy when you guys be implementing in
project 2 you know you don't have to
implement all the various optimizations
that we talked about you can sort of do
this straightforward method and going
always top down and left to right with
you know dis aborting should be pretty
straightforward the other thing I want
to convey also too is that although we
described all these mechanisms to
protect the data structure in the
context of a B+ tree these higher high
level techniques that we're using here
are applicable to all sorts of different
types of data structures I think of
things like an oak wiring latches always
in the same order to avoid deadlocks
killing yourself right away and
restarting right all those things you
can apply to other areas or other facets
of computer science or the data
structures as well
so it's not just in yes we're doing it B
plus trees because that's the most
common thing in databases but for hash
table is for red black trees and splay
trees and other things you can do the
same kind of thing okay all right so any
questions about flashing or crabbing
permit you're all salivating for project
two okay so project two you guys be
building a thread safe B+ tree can using
the the latching and crabbing techniques
we're talking about here today so the
project has broken up to four parts the
first one is defining the page layout
then you have to build your data
structure then you have to make a
iterator class or wrapper around it and
then implement latch crap so the way
it's going to work is that we're gonna
provide you guys with again the scalp
owning the API the you guys have to
implement the same way we did for
project one and then you guys just fill
in your implementations and you're free
to add whatever additional private
classes or private data structures or or
or private methods you want inside of
your class but you the highest level you
need to implement the API that we give
you okay so the one thing we're doing
differently this year is that we're
breaking up the project up again into
two checkpoints so the first checkpoint
we do October eighth which I think is on
Monday at midnight
again you just Smit this on great scope
and it'll be the sort of the first half
of the project so you know implement the
page layouts for the internal node and
the belief nodes and you only need to
actually support unique keys or making
it much more simple you have to worry
about I think also we don't make you
support variable length keys either
everything we fix line and then you
start building out your B plus tree and
in the first checkpoint you only need to
support search and insert all right
insert you obviously need to in order to
populate it and then searches you just
needed to check whether you know things
are there that should be there so nobody
think what business you only need its
support inserts with with splitting and
not delete it in the first checkpoint
and just like before we'll provide you
with some rudimentary test cases to
evaluate your work the great scope one
will have more comprehensive tests but
you're also encouraged to write your own
you can
sort of testing firm can we give you the
first to this first checkpoint be worth
40% of the grade and then for the second
project second checkpoint that's worth
60% and that's due October 19th which is
a Friday I think the midterm is that
Wednesday the 17th so this will be do
after after two days after the midterm
so now in the second checkpoint you have
to implement deletion right with with
with merging or sibling stealing and
then you have to implement an sto index
rapper or iterate a wrapper around your
index and that means you have to do the
leaf notes can to make them thread save
actually yeah this is the second
checkpoint overall you have to make
everything be thread safe so you the
latch crabbing and coupling techniques
we're talking about here and it's up to
you to decide whether you want to use
the optimistic one or not are you wanna
do delayed updates or whether other
optimizations you want to do it's
entirely up to you guys
but then what won't we'll benchmark you
guys opponent with the leaderboard and
see who has the fastest one question
this question is can use always lock the
root of the tree well latch the root of
the tree no you can do that to start
right so you could do this for like at
this point here like like if you would
submit it with a single latch of the
entire thing I think if I remember
correctly from the test I think we have
hooks so that we can pause threads in
the tests and check to see whether you
are actually supporting concurrent
threads at the same time so we had
things like that we're like instead of
like just you know give me a key and
then it comes back we have hooks in the
in the traversal steps so that maybe we
get to like the level two and let me
pause and then try to have somebody else
come behind you and see whether you
actually support concurrent up you know
current operations right because that
way you know when threads going down a
different path and it should be allowed
if it one thread is Paul's inside of it
so that that's what we check from the
current index
alright alright some general develop
hints I would say is that the way it's
implemented is almost exactly how it's
described in the textbook
I think it's chapter 1510 like the even
like the seam down like that the method
names are exactly what's in the textbook
alright so you if you follow that follow
the semantics that that'll help you
understand things I had it one of the
TAS took the class last shared he says
like it was until I went and read the
textbook well in their discussion I'll
be plus tree and crabbing did the
project actually make sense to me so I
encourage you to go do that first before
you get started the other thing you can
do also and we have this on the project
page you're encouraged maybe to set your
nose size to be smaller than four
kilobytes no size is a page size but now
if you have that if you have it be four
kilobytes then you have to assert a lot
of stuff before it starts splitting and
merging or sorry before it starts
splitting so if you use a smaller page
size like our node size like 5 5 and 12
bytes then it doesn't take it doesn't
take very much insertions before it
starts splitting and you test that to
see whether your things working
correctly and then the last one else to
do and again this is this is in the
documentation of the project page you
want to make sure that you protect the
internal pointer for the root page in
your in your B+ tree that's the thing
that people got fouled up on last year a
lot right if I start doing splits and I
update mom my pointer to my root node
which is recognize representative
through this root page ID then when you
come back you're now pulling a garbage
ok all right so the way you're gonna do
this is that we're gonna give you a new
car ball we'll give you a simple some
you know batch command to copy in the
files from project 1 into the new tar
ball I can have some updated code and
when you submit it you only want to
submit the 10 files that you modified
plus the 6 files that from project 1 so
everything's sort of built on top of
what you've done before is it cumulative
ok
and then as always post your questions
on Piazza or come to TLS hours and then
obviously don't don't don't cheat
there are implementations of people
streets on the internet you can look at
them you follow them but but copying
them into your code is not gonna help
you
it's the API is different and don't put
anything to put any your code or
solutions on github okay
alright any questions yes they say it
again sorry yes for projects to our
project one should be today well check
this in the last day is well it's her
again so every day you're late it's 25%
off so it's yeah and you get for late
days so you can submit it at least for
late days then it's four more days after
that before you get a zero
so technically eight days to submit it
ok ok all right next class we'll
probably actually start looking how to
actually exit queries we sort of been
beating around the bush keep saying like
oh we have queries
they'll come later we read a B+ tree we
read our pages with tuples now I'll
actually talk about how to see how to do
this again building up the layers in the
system buildings have the B plus trees
built on the buffer pool manager now we
can run queries ok
yes it's the SD cricket IDE mess I make
a mess unless I can do it like a gia are
you with the G to the e to the T comes
dope I play the game where's mommy's on
the cuff of the bus a cap on the party
by the 12-pack case seven four six pack
for the egg it's the Real ID replete
with your drinking proper 12 ow
they say build nation flat out what's a
nice is straight so it really don't
matter