[Music]
they'd be on the Jill's neck so real
quick - quick announcement I want to
mention two things the first is that
everyone should be aware that that
homework one is due next week on Monday
at midnight some of you've already
started people that work try to get role
in the course they've already finished
obviously actually whoever got it first
I don't know who it is dad they weren't
even they weren't even the wait list
they were already enrolled in the course
and they beat all of you right so
whoever did that was congrats and then
the the other thing else is next week we
will be releasing the first programming
project so that'll be I think you'll be
doing two weeks after this so I'll send
out a notice about this but we've
adjusted the deadlines slightly for
these projects because last year the
feedback we got was the first project
was considered too easy and the second
project was considered really hard
except everyone thought the second
project would be like the first project
and so a lot of people end up failing
because they didn't a lot themselves
enough time so we're giving you less
time for project one more time on
project - okay the other thing to
announce is also there's a bunch of
database talks coming up in the next
week so tomorrow in CIC on the fourth
floor while having the cofounders of
Connecticut which is the gpu-accelerated
database system out of Virginia they'll
be coming giving a talk at noon again
that's open to everyone you don't have
to register for this and there will be
pizza available for that for that one
and then on Friday we'll have a talk
from Pat Helen from Salesforce Pat is a
sort of a legend in the database
research community he's not academic
he's a sort of somebody that's been
around working on databases for a long
time since the 1980s so he's gonna come
give a talk also at noon in the CIC for
four that should be Pisa this one as
well so I encourage you to come to
either one of those the first one the
Connecticut talk would be very technical
but they're gonna talk about more about
the engineering side of making database
systems run on GPUs and this is going
well beyond anything we'll talk about in
this course and then the Salesforce talk
should be a bit more lofty
or higher-level I guess Pat's much more
senior it's about you're thinking big
about distributed systems distributed
databases and then on Wednesday next
week at 4 p.m. will be having the
co-founder of relational AI come give a
talk so I don't know this person this is
actually being organized by somebody
else in Tepper but the the co-planner of
relational AI had a previous database
system startup called logic blocks which
is a bit of an esoteric system doesn't
look like didn't operate the same way
that the data systems that we're talking
on here operate but so he's sort of a
semi-famous guys he'll also be giving a
talk at at 4 p.m. so the first one will
be on YouTube the other two will not be
ok so the first two will have pizza the
second one I don't know because I'm not
I'm not running it you can plan your
meals accordingly all right any
questions any questions at homework one
ok let's jump right into it ok so where
we're at now is that we spent the first
two lectures talking about sort of
higher level things like how what the
relational model is and how you would
write queries against data stored it
stored like that and that was all sort
of lofty in in terms of high-level and
abstract right we didn't describe
anything about how we actually would
implement code that could do those
particular things so at this point of
course this is where we sort of start
jumping to now describing how you would
actually build software to execute
queries on a relational database system
and so that's really what the next
pretty much from now until Thanksgiving
the things that we were talking about
and so if you go back to the course
outline that I showed at the first class
where we sort of already covered the
first part we already covered relational
databases and now we're getting into all
the implementation details and so the
way to sort of think about this as we're
going along at a high level is that
we're essentially going to be describing
different layers of the database
management system software that we're
going to build on top of do do more
complicated things or get more
functionality out of it right so at the
storage level we're sort of starting at
the bottom right we're talking about how
we're actually going to read and write
data and what that data looks like on
and then we define an API in our disk
manager or a storage manager to say
here's how to interact with the data
that I can manage and then on top of
that we can then build our buffer pool
then on top of that we can start
building our execution engines or access
methods right so sort of going up by one
by one and to describe how you would
build each different layer what are the
trade-offs or different design decisions
you have to think about for each layer
and then once that's sort of done we can
assume that we're good to go right along
as we implement whatever that layer once
or we define what an API is we can build
other stuff on top of that so we'll see
it in a couple cases today where I'm
going to describe different ways to
organize pages or organized data in
pages and what happens above that
actually doesn't matter in some ways
right we can still use maybe the same
control schemes or the same indexing
schemes on top of this because we had
this sort of abstraction down below and
this is this is not new to databases
they're not unique to databases this is
the standard practice in putting any
large software system so again so
today's class and next class we're
focusing on the disk manager and again
this is just how we're gonna actually
the store data on disk so for the the
course I sort of mentioned this in the
beginning but I didn't really define
what I meant so I want to say that this
course is focusing on what I would call
a disk oriented database management
system architecture and so what I mean
by that is that the database management
system is designed such that it's oons
that it assumes the primary storage
location of the database is on some
non-volatile disk and I'll define what I
mean by non-volatile disk in the next
slide and therefore the the components
of the system are responsible for
figuring out how to move data back and
forth between the non-volatile disk and
and volatile memory right because you
can't operate the Devi system can't
operate data directly on disk right
there are some newer disks that can do
these kind of things because their CPUs
down there but in practice like a
commodity disk you would buy or on
Amazon or Newegg you're not gonna be
able to write run code down on there
right so you always have to bring the
data you need to operate on either read
and write into memory and then do
whatever it is that you need to do so
the database manner system is all about
managing
that movement back and forth at this
level of the architecture and this is
this is the classic von Neumann
architecture from from the 1950s so in
order to understand the implications of
this movement of data back and forth we
will first to understand what the
storage hierarchy looks like what are we
actually dealing with in our real
systems so the the way to start to think
about it is is this this sort of tree
structure like this right and and every
single layer is a different kind of
storage class device and the you can
only move data directly from one layer
to another right you can only take data
out from well that's not exactly true
buddy
you only take data out from an SSD and
put into DRAM before you can put it into
your CPU caches all right again that's
not entirely true in those cases but for
our purposes let's go with that so in a
way to sort of think about this is in
this hierarchy is the storage devices at
the top are really fast
but they have much smaller capacity and
they're also much more expensive right
and at the bottom you have larger
storage devices that have larger
capacities that are cheaper per gigabyte
or per megabyte but they're gonna be
went much much slower if you go looking
in the textbook they'll describe sort of
as hierarchy as well the one thing I'll
point out is they don't put network
storage at the bottom network store
never stored to be something like EBS or
HDFS like I just distributed file system
below this would be like tape archives I
mean I mean that's really only used for
the disaster recovery you can get that
from Amazon Amazon has the thing called
flag Amazon glacier right that's like
super super slow we're not even gonna
worry about that here so the foot in our
course the way we're going to
differentiate between these different
layers is not so much between SSDs and
nacd's it's really is it volatile or
versus non-volatile so anything above
the line is considered volatile right it
means like you if you remove power on
the machine like you pull the power cord
and then every all your data is gone
right DRAM needs power every so often or
the Refresh it sells and maintain the
charge same thing for CPU caches and CP
and so they the the way we're gonna
access the volatile data has been
different however we're gonna access it
non-volatile data so in Volvo data
support what's called a random access
API meaning we can jump to any single
byte address and get the actual data
that's there and it can be able to
support this fast random access right we
can jump around anywhere in in our
memory space and it's gonna be roughly
the same speed no matter where we go
non-volatile memory is going to be
better off for doing what's called
sequential access so that's trying to
read a lot of data that's sort of
contiguous to each other in in storage
right so you just sort of read all the
data at once you can still jump around
but it's gonna be slower and instead of
accessing a single address address line
or cache line to go get the data we need
we're gonna access the data in what are
called blocks or pages which are
typically about four kilobytes right so
in volatile storage I can say go get me
this single 64-bit memory location and
we'll read the value in a non-volatile
storage that's block addressable I have
to go get the four kilobyte block that
has the data I need and then inside of
that I can get the 64 bit value that I
want all right so the again the way to
sort of think about this is that when I
talk throughout the course
I'm not going to differentiate between
SSDs and HTTP or network storage I'm
really gonna say that anything above SSD
that's memory there started dear M that
will be considered memory and then
anything below that will be dis
considered disk right because at a high
level the algorithms we're going to use
to accessing what I'll call disk are
roughly the same whether it's an SSD a
CD or EBS so the other thing else is a
two isn't in this course we're not gonna
care about anything above DRAM right so
CPU caches like l1 l2 l3 or anything
like CPU registers because in our world
with it with a disk the disk is so slow
that all our focus is really about how
can we speed up or hide the latency of
these storage devices down here and you
know once it's in memory that's good
enough so if you take the advanced class
in the spring 15 7:21 we're gonna not
going to do disk or David systems we're
actually do memory origin or any memory
database systems so this now the disk
goes away except for logging and now it
since everything
memory now we care about the stuff at
the top right and you can actually get
pretty good speed up if you start
aligning things to the cache lines or
try to maintain as much data in CPU
registers and actual individual
registers for as long as possible but
again for our purpose here we don't care
the other thing I want to bring up too
is also there is actually a new storage
technology that that's coming out called
non-volatile memory that sort of sits in
in the in the middle here right between
SSDs and in DRAM right so this is
sometimes called persistent memory or
storage class memory the way to sort of
think about it is it's like DRAM in that
it's fast sports random access and
things are byte addressable but it's
persistent like an SSD right so meaning
if I write to non-volatile memory and I
pull the plug all my data is still there
when I come back so the last couple
years as I've been teaching this course
I always keep saying like oh yeah
non-volatile memory it exists in the lab
so you actually can't get it yet so
we're not we're looking to worry about
it here that's actually not true as of
this year so Intel announced that they
have actually non-volatile memory in
production we actually have access
access to it here at CMU my PhD student
that just graduated he's now at Georgia
Tech he his whole thesis was on
non-volatile memory databases so we're
not ready yet to throw away the entire
textbook but I think a lot of things
that we'll talk about during the
semester some of these things will go
away some of these things we get tweet
because now you're gonna have
non-volatile memory so I think Intel's
announcing it's going to come out in
later later this year supposedly I think
they're calling it 3d crosspoint or
octane memory there's a bunch of
marketing terms for it right now but the
high level it works like this it looks
like DRAM but it's persistent like an
SSD all right so to give an idea of why
we're gonna spend a lot of work to move
data back and forth between DRAM and
disk we have to understand what it takes
to actually get data at a disk and bring
it into memory so there's a bunch of
different tables on the internet that
roughly had the same information this
were like this so the exact numbers
might be slightly different but the
magnitude of the differences are roughly
the same so to read data from a single
cache line
in l1 which is the the closest cash you
can have to write about CP registers it
takes about half a nanosecond you got to
read from l2 it's seven nanoseconds DRAM
is 100 nanoseconds and so forth and so
forth right so when you show numbers
like this with nanoseconds people don't
really know how to like put that in
perspective of like real world clock
time so instead of saying that maybe for
this case here that l1 cache reference
takes half a nanosecond well we say if
it takes a second right now you can I
can see why reading from these these
slower devices is so bad right
so we say l1 cache is this cache miss as
a as a second half a second then reading
from l2 cache seven seconds DRAM is 100
seconds reading from an SSD is one point
seven days reading from a spinning disk
magnetic hard drive is sixteen weeks
reading from network stores a TBS is a
months and then reading from a tape
drive is 31 years the other certain
metaphor people like to use is say I
want to read a book I want to read a
page in a book right reading from my CTO
caches it's like the book is right in
front of me reading it from maybe DRAM
is like walking across the room to get
it meeting from SSDs are walking down to
the library and getting it but like
reading it from a tape drive is like
flying to Pluto to read the book and
then flying back right I say these are
orders of magnitude slower and again
this is why we're gonna be tough to be
smart about how we keep our data in DRAM
as much as possible to avoid ever having
to go to disk now in some cases we can't
avoid this right we have to actually
write data to disk to make sure things
are durable but we can be smart about
how we actually want to do this so our
system design goals for actually how
we're gonna build a data system is at a
higher level what we essentially want to
do is we want to have the provide a
software system that has the illusion
that the entire database fits in DRAM
even though it doesn't right and we're
to be careful about how we move data
back and forth and we want to do it in
such a way that we avoid large stalls
because we have to fetch something from
disk and we don't want to have have that
slowed down everything else again it's
unavoidable the data is not in memory
you've got to go get a disk and get it
but ideally you want to have the data
system be able to do other things
while you're going fetching that data
let me be up processing other queries of
course now we'll see this later on when
we talk about transactions and
concurrency control but if you have
multiple threads doing multiple things
at the same time because maybe one
thread stalled to go out there disk now
you make sure that you order their
operations correctly so they don't you
know read data that they shouldn't be
reading ok we'll worry about that later
for our purpose here we're just trying
to say how can we deal with reading
writing dated from disk and how we're
gonna organize things so the I mentioned
this before when we talked about the the
difference between non vult on volatile
memory because just to bring it up again
the big also difference we're gonna see
is and how we design these components is
dealing with the fact that sequential
access on non-volatile storage is much
faster than random access so that means
that we're gonna try to maximize our
ability to read and write data
sequentially meaning reading large
blocks of data at a time to get things
that we need all right if you have to go
jump around say you have a spinning disk
hard drive it has a mechanical arm that
jumps around on the platter right you
have to jump it around for every single
time you want to read a single tuple
then that's gonna be really slow but if
you can read you know plop the arm down
and let it read a large segment of data
then bring that in memory then that's me
much faster because again there's this
fewer fewer movements of the physical
arm so the operating systems usually
support the ability to allocate multiple
pages or blocks in a row right these are
calls at extents I said you can say I
want to allocate one megabyte extent or
one gigabyte extent and then the OS will
try to
contiguous in the in the actual storage
device itself so as I said like in my
design goals we try to want to make we
want to have our database system provide
the illusion that it has more memory
than it actually has
right if we have one gigabyte of RAM and
we have a 10 gigabyte database we want
to make it appear that the entire
database fits in fits in memory so what
does that sound like
who here is taken operating system
course what's that I heard it virtual
memory exactly right so this is
essential what virtual memory does right
virtual memory set the operating system
says all right here's my address space
but then I have this little swap section
where I can write out pages when I run
out of space in memory and it looks to
the application it looks like
everything's actually a memory when it's
not you don't the right change your code
in any way to deal with the fact that
the page you want to read is that is the
operative hides all that for you so now
really saying well if I this is what I
want in my database system I want the
ability to have it appear that I have
more memory than I actually have and the
operating system already can do this in
virtual memory why not just use the
operating system for this so the way you
would actually write this is through a
syscall called M map who here has heard
of M map to in the back okay three right
so M map means memory map file and
debated way to basically think about
this is like you have a file on disk and
you tell the operating system um map it
you load it in and it's basically going
to map the the physical pages of the of
the file on disk into virtual memory
addresses in inside of you know the OS
and then from your application
standpoint you can jump to any location
in that file in your memory address and
underneath the coverage the operating
system will page things in and out as
needed
right so the L the operation is
essentially responsible moving data in
and out so just to give a quick example
looks like this say this is our this is
our file on disk and it has four pages
right one two three four and then in
memory and the operating system we're
gonna have our virtual memory so we a
map it in so we have the four pages in
memory but at this point at the very
beginning there's no there's nothing in
there eight empty because we haven't
gone to disk to get anything and then we
only have actually two pages of space in
physical memory so now if my process
comes along and it wants to read the
first page I'll get a page fault which
is it interrupts the operating system
stalls my process wall goes down to the
disk fetches the the page that I want
puts it in physical memory and then maps
the virtual memory to point to that
physical page right again if I access
page three same thing I get a page fault
the OS stalls my process and then it
goes fetches that what I need right the
stalling the process actually means that
you're blocking your thread because
you're now you're down in the kernel and
the operating system knows not to have
its schedule schedule scared of you for
a quantum to actually run because you
can't do anything because you're blocked
waiting for for this page all right
of course now we have this problem of
well we want to access this page here
it's not memory we don't have any more
free space in physical memory so what do
we actually do right we need to evict
one and and make space for it but now
there might be other threads or other
processes doing the same thing so we may
have a long stall right so this is bad
from our point of view member I said
earlier that ideally when we ever have
to go to disks and get something we
don't want to stall the entire database
system we want to have something else
keep running and maybe make for progress
on their queries while we go fetch the
thing that we need but in in in this
case here at the operating system using
M map it doesn't do that because the the
operation prop stalls our thread now if
we have other threads they can do other
things but that's gonna cause problems
right so we have multiple threads to
access the same and that file the same
time to hide these page fault stalls now
we got to deal with problems of what
happens if they're reading and writing
to different pages and how to make sure
things get you get written out just
correctly so I want to go to the details
of how a map sucks this has been a
long-standing beef that I have with end
map if you want to call it that I will
say also underneath the covers I mean
for if you call malloc it's essentially
doing a map right but it's not actually
being backed by disk writes is backed by
just physical memory that's always there
it could get swapped out but that's
that's the virtual memory in the OS so
and that works really great or
reasonably great for read-only workloads
but when you have writers then you have
problems so the way it started handle
this is that you the OS does provide you
some hints to overcome this right these
3 cysts calls em advise and the lock and
sink and these are basically telling the
operating system how you how that your
process your database system is actually
going to access the pages that um mapped
right so em advise can say that like I
plan on reading these certain pages now
or how how I plan on reading them and
block and tell the operating
whatever you do don't swap this out to
disk because I'm always gonna do
something to it and then NSYNC allows
you to it to flush things so there are
some systems actually use em map the
ones I'm aware of in terms of full usage
would be mone DB and OLM DB the LM DB
doesn't like me because I don't like em
map that's another story
mo DB Mon a DB is a analytical system
that's highly read-only so this is like
fine but when you actually wanted to
start doing writes that's when you have
problems and map now there are some
systems that also also use partial use
and map so MongoDB the original engine
that actually it actually uses was based
on a map it was so bad that they threw
it away and actually built a sort of
what I'll call correct storage manager
called wired Tiger that does the things
that we're talking about in this class
mem sequel uses Men map for the column
store for sort of read-only things same
with the influx DB and then sequel light
has different engines you can use and
what I think one of them is ml so the
bottom line I want to get out of this
and we'll see this later on we talked
about the buffer pool stuff the buffer
pool manager in two lectures but the
reoccurring theme throughout this course
also will be that the database managed
system can always do a better job than
the operating system because it knows
exactly what's happening right it knows
what the queries is executing it knows
what the data looks like it knows how
it's going to access that data so
therefore it can always do a much better
job at scheduling these things then then
the operating system right and there's
certain precautions you have to take to
make sure that you write things out in
the correct order which are actually
difficult to do and not really portable
with the nmap syscall so if I die you
put two things my tombstone
one is the operating system is not your
friend it's like a frenemy right you
need it to survive but like it kind of
gets in the way and the second one is
never use a map but your database
management system right now I'll send
one else out this but this has been a
long-standing beef the there's a some
really good researchers in Germany that
try to use mmm for their database system
they gave up on it and we want to write
a paper to prove that finally a map is a
bad idea from a database system so if
you're interested in this and you want
you know ruffle some feathers email me
and we can talk about it
alright so again we'll see is a couple
of times
the semester where it seems like what
I'm describing to you is functionality
that the database system our ticket or
sorry the operating system can already
provide over having implemented
ourselves and every major commercial
database system does this right because
they can always get much better
performance and have much better control
and guarantee correctness and safety of
data in ways that it may not always be
possible with the operating system right
so again what I'm describing for this
class will seem like a lot of ways like
oh we're betting a little mini operating
system yes that's because we can we want
to do things ourselves and then you know
what if we go do this at a company they
pay us a lot to do it cuz it's hard
alright there's always a good thing all
right so what are the do problems
empathy with Davis storage so the first
is that how we're gonna actually
represent the data in files on disk
right and the second one is how we
actually to manage this movement of
memory back and forth pages between the
disk and memory back and forth so for
this class and the next class we're
gonna focus on this problem here right
so we're not gonna worry about however
actually you know if we have these pages
when we copy the memory what do we how
do we actually manage that we'll cover
that when we talk about the buffer pool
stuff and then that that's what you'll
do in the first project we're really
focused on this problem here of like we
have these files on disk how do we
actually do have you actually represent
the data that's stored in them so for
today's agenda we talked about three
parts and you sort of see again what I
said before how we're going to build
these layers up and do something more
complicated things so we're gonna start
with how we actually gonna maintain
these files on disk and then we'll build
up from that talk about how we actually
organized the pages in those files and
then from that we can then talk about
how we actually organize the tuples
inside of those pages right so again
well both these one-by-one sort of see
how these things build on top of each
other so in the most basic form the
database minute system is essentially
just going to store the database as
files on disk right there's no magic to
it I just went to files you in your file
system right there they are some systems
will store a single file sequel light
does this right if you if you create a
database a sequel light it creates a
single dot DB file for you which is nice
because it's portable you can move it
anywhere but typically the the the
bigger systems actually store multiple
files in embarrass hierarchies but I see
if you have Postgres installed in your
system go in its UNIX go look at slash
var slash / quest QL they're gonna have
them in all these directories where
they'll have different directors for
tables different directories for indexes
different directories for it for
metadata and each is inside of those
will be these different database files
so these files typically are in a
proprietary format that is specific to
the database minute system so it's not
like you can open up a text editor and
actually see any data right it's gonna
be some binary form that only that
database management system can read and
write to now we'll see this one and the
cloud systems later on but there are
sort of now these sort of universal file
database file formats things like or
Corp RK or Aereo right these are things
that are designed to be usable orange
estable by different database systems
but in general usually the actual raw
files and cells are what can only on be
understood by that the davis isn't that
made it so because they're just files on
disk the operating system doesn't know
anything about them right doesn't know
that they're special right there's no
that their database files so all sort of
the standard file protection mechanisms
that you get from from regular files in
the OS that's the always before that
provide that for you as well
right you can just run your database
system on top of ext4 txt three you know
whatever in Windows provides right and
the upper levels of the the system for
the most part maybe don't care I would
say in the early 1980s there was a sort
of a moment or a trend where the the
database vendors decided that all the
file systems were crap and that they
wanted to actually implement their own
database if ik says the duck file system
so what that means it's like you just
take the role blocks on the extra
storage device and then the data system
knew how to build a file system on top
of it and it's read and write to the
role blocks as far as I know nobody
actually does that anymore
I personally sorry you wouldn't build a
new system today and start doing that
there's conventional wisdom is that you
really only get maybe look at 10 or 15
set 15% speed-up in performance if
you've run your own file system over
something like ext4 and for that kind of
speed up it's just not worth the
engineering effort right and also makes
your
it makes her you know database isn't
less portable so in general the the most
major data systems are just gonna run on
existing file systems and that you know
and that's good enough for us it's not
great but it's good so now this the same
reverse first need to build is what
we'll call the Storage Manager and this
is essentially responsible for the the
maintaining the database files whether
it's one or multiple ones but the
storage manager is responsible we're
saying here's here's my files and I know
how to get pages in and out of them so
the files are going to be organized as a
collection of pages right you sort of
take the file and you split it up to
different chunks and each of these
chunks to be called a page and so the
storage manager to keep track of what
data needs to read and write to pages
how much free space are is in pages if
you want to do compaction maybe remove
empty empty pages that are being used
and used less space like this is what
the storage manager provides for you so
now a database case as I said is a fixed
size block of data and it can contain
anything that that relates to our
database right so it contains tuples
that contain a metadata about the tuples
it contain indexes and log records it
can contain intermediate results from a
query as we're running it because we
have to fill out the disk so we don't
have enough memory right for our
purposes in this class we'll just assume
that we're only dealing with pages that
contain tuples typically you also don't
mix the type of data you store it in a
page so you're not gonna have a single
page that'll have some you know to have
index data and tuple data right from us
this is done mostly for myself for
engineering standpoint you want to have
each page only stored data for a
specific class or specific type now some
systems actually required pages
activities self-contained and what I
mean by that is all the data you need to
know about how to read and interpret the
data that's stored inside that page has
to be stored in that page so an example
with this be let's say I'm doing like
dictionary compression right dictionary
compression is you take a string that
occurs a lot and instead of storing the
actual raw characters we just stored an
integer to say here's what here's the
placeholder for that original string so
you need a dictionary to say here's how
to map that integer to the actual
original string so if you store that
dictionary
one page and then store the database
that's encoded with that dictionary on
another page if that dictionary page
gets trashed right now you can't
unencoded the original page so some
systems like Oracle they they're worried
about disaster recovery they actually
say oh no they did everything you need
to know to actually interpret the data
has to be on stored on that page so that
way if for whatever reason that that
page gets trashed the damage is only
isolated to that single page right so
that is actually specific to Oracle I
don't think anybody else actually does
this but I think it's actually a really
good idea but and it if it causes them
to make certain other design decisions
that may be seen inefficient from a
performance standpoint but from a you
know never losing data I think it's a
good idea so now every page is going to
have a unique identifier we'll call it
the page ID B now the basin's gonna have
to maintain some kind of indirection map
that allows you to figure out how to
take a page ID because that's what a
that's what the upper levels of the
system are going to access or ask for it
are the upper levels of the system is
gonna say give me page one two three and
now the storage manager needs to have a
some kind of mapping layer to take that
page number and find the file and the
offset of where can go get that
particular page and then put give the
bytes back up to whoever asked for it so
they also - I think say the reason why
we want to keep it fixed size is that
that way in our file if we say oh we
want page one to three and we know it's
in this file at offset 100 we know
exactly how to calculate where to go in
that jump in that file to get the data
that we need if we have variable length
pages then when you have to have an
indirection layer at the top to say oh
you want page 100 it's at this all set
and now you've you maintain that thing
and now you're pro the problems if you
delete a page that may be variable size
now you have a hole that you maybe can't
fill back up so pages are always gonna
be fixed sized and just makes everything
much easier and we'll see how we do
handle this with tuples that can be
variable length within a page so one
thing I confess is that as I go along
sometimes I'll say page and sometimes
I'll say block right there the words are
in some ways inter interchangeable but
I'll try to use page as much as often
and there's different concepts of pages
in our system that we have to be mindful
as well so at the lowest point you have
what's called a harbor page this is what
the actual storage device itself
provides to you right into the operating
system when you ask to read and write a
particular block a particular page right
different storage devices have different
page sizes but in general they're
usually four kilobytes then now in the
operating system again it's going to be
providing this notion of pages as well
and these pages are usually four
kilobytes by default in Linux with Linux
and windows are four kilobytes but
there's ways to in turn turn on what's
called huge pages where you can have it
actually organize memory as in you know
up to one gigabyte pages I need you this
because this reduces the size of the
page directory of your TLB and that fits
more than the cache and you have fewer
cache misses on that but in our world
again we care about the database page
and is essentially the way to think
about this is like we're going to
organize in our database the you know
our own pages but in those pages one
should get mapped to OS sized pages and
the OSI pages get mapped to physical
pages right so you think would be always
four kilobytes because that's what the
harbor once and it's the OS one but in
practice it varies a lot right so at one
in the spectrum you have sequel Lite
that has one kilobyte pages and this
makes sense because they're you know
sequel is designed to run on really
small embedded devices that may not have
four kilobyte pages db2 and Oracle
support for Cabaye pages Post Crescent
sequel server or AQI pages and then my
sequel in uncompressed form is 16
kilobyte pages I actually don't know why
they do this I have a hunch because they
want to do ink that's organized tables
which we'll talk about later on but when
you do compression they also can store
pages and smaller sizes as well
well we're not gonna talk about it here
what I'll say though is that the harbor
page size is sort of what it can
guarantee as what I call a fail-safe
write meaning it can guarantee that if
you tell it to write for well kilobyte
pages and it says I wrote for clout
pages like that-like or you tell it to
write a page and that page size is 4
kilobytes on the hardware it'll
guarantee that it neither all 4
kilobytes get written or none of them
get written right so that means that if
you have larger database pages and you
flushed him out the disk you may have to
do extra extra work extra protection
mechanisms to make sure that you don't
have torn up dates right if you have a
16 kilobyte page on my sequel and the
harbor can only provide four kilobyte
atomic writes you don't want to write
the first you know eight kilobytes and
then crash and come back and have you
know in half of your update so we'll see
this when we talk about logging recovery
systems like my sequel have to do extra
work to make sure that you know they're
writing their data out safely and they
know it's been staged and all everything
is always there all right so now we need
every we have these pages and we know
where a bunch of files and they're going
split up into pages now we need a
mechanism to figure out how to actually
find where the page that we want right
can the upper levels of the system are
gonna say gimme page one two three and
now we need to go figure out where that
page one two three is or we want to
order the system could say hey I want to
write this amount of data gave me a page
that has a free slot and now our storage
layer has to figure out how to how to
find that so there's a couple different
ways to actually do this I'm gonna focus
on the first one
because this is the most common the
sequential and sort of file organization
we'll see this when we talk about
indexes this is typically how you
implement clustering indexes right well
basically the heap file is unsorted
sequential or sort of files are sorted
and you need index to make that happen
and we'll talk about that later
and then hashing file organization is
just an easy extension to the heap file
one so I'll focus on the first one the
other thing I'll say also at this point
is that we don't really care what's
inside of our pages at this point again
we're only trying to say give me a page
or give me a free slot within a page we
don't care what's actually stored in
that right and that makes this what our
job a bit more easier here because we
don't care about finding an exact you
know exact things we can let the upper
levels of the system do that for us so a
database heap or a heap file is a
unorganized collection of pages where
the two books can be stored in random
order or the data that were storing can
be sorted random border right we have a
chunk of data we want to write to a page
we don't care if it's we're using heat
Bob we don't care where that actually
goes as long as it goes somewhere
so the basic API we need to be a support
in a
file or a database heap a storage
manager is the ability to get and delete
a page as well as to iterate over every
possible page right so I if I have 100
pages I want a way to say here's you
know here's the the chunks of memory to
that for each of those 100 pages now
we're gonna need to maintain some
metadata to keep track of what pages
exist obviously and when you keep track
of where do we have free space because
again we may want to say get a page that
has a free space that we can store this
amount of data so now there's two ways
to organize this the first is a linked
list and the friend the second is a page
directory and sort of a spoiler is
everyone does the page rectory approach
but it's good to understand what the
link list one is because it's sort of
see why you need to use a page directory
so the linked list approach is you have
a single header page that only contains
two pointers and the pointer is going to
point to two different linked lists so
the first link list will be the free
page list so these are pages that have
at least some free space where you can
actually store data and then the second
linked list is the data page these are
pages there that there are there is no
more free space right so what will
happen is if you want to say get me page
one two three you actually have to
traverse these linked lists and figure
out where the page it is that you want
or if you need say I want to insert a
new record and I need to find space you
only have to you don't have to follow
along the the free page list all right
and this is because there's an
additional metadata that we need that
we're not actually going to track inside
of the the header page right about like
what free space we actually have all
that's going to be stored directly
inside the pages themselves right
there's no reason we couldn't it's just
this is sort of a strawman
implementation we don't actually do this
all right the other thing we have
problem is that say we want to get page
one to three we end up having to do
basically a sequential scan on both of
these until we find the one that we want
right so a better approach and whatever
much pretty much everyone does is to use
the page directory where this is now
you're gonna have a special directory
page it's usually at the beginning of
the file so c-cold like
first page is always this directory and
just tells you here's all the pages that
I have at different different locations
in my database files and here's
information about how many how much free
space they actually have so now you can
easily traverse to every single page cuz
you just look in the directory and you
say you want to get page 1 2 3 can you
look in the directory it tells you
exactly where it is and you want to find
a page with free space then the
directory can can maintain this as for
as well so of course now you have to
make sure that the directory page is
always in sync with the actual data
pages themselves right because if the
data page has free space and the
directory page thinks it doesn't and
you're never actually gonna use that
space alright so you always have to make
sure that you you flush out the dirty
page anytime you you add new pages or
modify these things so what what
happened in this case here if the the
directory page is trashed are we screwed
hey check ahead no why exactly so if the
first page gets blown away for whatever
reason hey we can always go back and
scan through and look at every single
page and reconstruct it right small
files no big deal if I have a one
petabyte database that's that's problem
right because it's gonna take me days to
actually do this so there's extra
protection mechanisms we can have in our
system by writing out to the log all the
updates we have to our directory page to
avoid having to recreate everything
alright so this this approach is
resilient to ferrars even if the
directory page fails even though again
remember I said that some systems don't
like to have data you need to
reconstruct you know for a single page
spread across multiple pages in this
case here we can always make sure we can
always go back and recreate the
directory page ideally it'd be nice if
we didn't have to but we always have
that sort of fail back mechanism okay
so at this point we know about files we
know about how we're gonna split the
files up into pages and then now we have
a directory page directory component
that allows us to find the pages that we
want so now the next question is how do
we act what are having actually organize
the data inside of these pages and this
was the page layout is so every page is
containing a header right regards what
size it is
and this header is going to contain
metadata about the that particular page
right things like how much free space
there is it can also maintain check sums
right so when you write out the file you
take a checksum of it and that way our
server out the page took a checksum of
it when you write it out and that way
when you read it back into the page
something the checksum doesn't match you
know the page got corrupted in some way
you'll also often want to maintain the
the version number of the data center
system that created the the page so that
way if you change your page layout and
you load in an old database file you
know it's not you know you know what
layout to expect we'll talk about this
later on for control information but
sometimes you contain transaction
visibility information about the data
that's on this page so that you know
whether a transaction that's active is
actually couldn't be able to see any of
the tuples or any data inside this page
it's compression information like the
dictionary encoding that we talked about
before right so all this is gonna be
stored in the header and as I mentioned
some systems will actually require the
pages to be self-contained so now within
a page right every page has a header now
we're gonna talk about what actually the
data block looks like what are we
actually storing so for this we're just
going to focus on tuples we'll see this
later when we talk about indexes or
other things or log records these are
also going to be stored in pages but for
our purposes here we just care about how
we're actually gonna represent two polls
inside of these pages so for this
there's essentially two two broad
approaches the first is a tuple
warrington approach we're actually
storing the data for actually individual
tuples and the second one is a log
structured approach I'll go through both
of them okay so having a store pages in
a table so I first want to propose a
strawman like a bad idea and then we'll
see how she had to make this better
right so let's say that in our page all
we really have in our in our header the
simple thing we need to keep track of is
the number of tuples that we have in our
in our page and for this we're gonna
assume that all our troubles are fixed
length size I mean they're always gonna
be you know 100 100 bytes or you know
some some some number like that all
right so what's the easiest thing we can
do to insert a new to Plymouth's
well I heard it yeah so I want to
certainly much new tuples I just I know
where my header stops in my page and I
just I just start appending to poles one
by one until you know jog run out of
space right simple and then let's say
I'm gonna update my my header to say I
have three tuples so that way when I
come back if I want to write a fourth
people I know how to jump to that
location all right what's the problem
with this approach right what happens if
I if I delete a tuple all right so I
sleep the middle guy here I have two
tuples now if I keep it pending I'm
gonna miss that
so maybe what I need to do is actually
start from the beginning and keep
scanning until I find tuple that are
tuple slob that's actually used right
what's another obvious problem with this
right I said it was fixed length right
what happens in is variable length does
this work no right so how would actually
store a very linked data in this if I
say I want to search the next tuple how
do I figure out where to where to put it
I either had something in the in the
header that says here's where every
tuple here is worth all set every tuple
is or I sequentially scan - I find a
free spot then had to figure out when
the next tuple starts because I then
figure out where actually I can start
storing data all right so this is what
the slotted page architecture or layout
fix fixes so what I'll say is that it's
a lot of pages are essentially how every
disk database system promotes the
majority of them actually are
implemented the exact details may be
slightly different but a high level they
work all the same way so what's gonna
happen now is our header we're gonna
have this thing called a slot array all
right so we have a header information
the things we talked about before now we
have a slot array that's going to
contain a mapping of all sets for tuples
at different positions to their their
starting location in in the actual data
space and so down below we have our
fixed length and verbling tuples - all
stored in line with each other
and then these these offsets point to
where they start all right so this is
sort of adding another indirection layer
inside of our page so we can say things
like
at a high level give me page one two
three and give me to pool five in that
inside that page and I go look at my
slot array and that'll tell me where I
can find page five right and the way
we're gonna add new tuples is that the
slot array is always gonna grow from
from beginning to the end and then the
fixed length the actual data of the
tuples themselves are going to grow from
the end to the beginning and at some
point the two meet and I can't store
anything anything else and then the page
is considered full right again this is
another indirection layer that allows us
to reorganize the pages without having
to modify or change anything up above in
our system so maybe the case let's say I
delete tuple 3 and now I have a bunch of
free space here and I can actually
compact and slide over tuple four to be
contiguous with tuple two and all that I
do is update my slot array to say where
tuple for now it starts and everything
else in the system doesn't know doesn't
care right it's sort of like doing
compaction in the page level as you
write it out the disk so as I said this
is the most common approach how they
actually organize the slot array could
be slightly different but put additional
metadata they store for the slaughter
array could be different but at a high
level everybody works like this so
another different architecture instead
of storing actually tuples in pages is
to do what's called a log structured
page layout a log structure organization
so last year I presented this in the
same the same material here in the same
lecture but just in a different part I
I'm never quite sure when actually to
discuss log structured files with all
shifted page layouts because it's sorted
it's a combination of a bunch of
different things I think this is the
right point but we'll see how it goes
the the way to sort of think about these
log structured file organization is that
instead of actually storing tuples
inside of pages we're gonna store log
records so we haven't discussed what
logging actually is but basically think
about it's like a you know it's like a
record of the changes that you made to
the database so if I updated Indies to
boil I made my salary go from $1 to $2 I
would have a log worker that says update
and each tuple from $1 or $2 and I can
always replay that log and recreate the
actual
itself so in a log structure database
system you actually don't store any
tuples at all you only store the log
records of the changes that transaction
the returns eight changes that queries
make alright so now in a single page
what I'm gonna have is I'm just gonna
keep appending log entries from
beginning to end that correspond to the
changes that that that the queries made
and sort of think of this as going in
contiguously in time right I never go
back and delete any log record inside of
a page so I'm never gonna have any holes
alright and these can be variable and
because my updates can have very length
data but I just keep it pending into my
page until I run out of space and then
the page are considered full
all right so these loggers won't if I do
an insert it just contains the entire
tuple if I do a delete I have some way
to mark that and tuple got deleted and
if I do an update it's just the Delta of
the change that got made that made right
so what's the tricky thing about log
structured pages
what's slower exactly read
reads are slow right updates are easy
just I find a page that has a free slot
and boom I append to the end I'm done if
I'm doing read now I need to go back
potentially and look to the page and
reconstruct the tuple into its original
form based on its log records so do new
reads I have to go in reverse order
right so that mean that's so that's so
that's a problem
and so now again this is within the
concept of a single page but you know in
a real vulture catholocism these are
still you know or a log structured
database these are strewn across
multiple pages so I made to go read
through multiple pages in order to
reconstruct the tuple back to the form
that I need for the read so the way to
avoid having to read everything is that
you can build indexes up above basically
say you know if you need to buy B 1 2 3
here's where to go get it right at these
different locations so log structured
systems are loyal structured databases
are not new they can't go date back to
the 1989 teen 80s early 1990s but
they're actually really in vogue now
there's a much more systems actually
implement this things like leveldb rocks
D because
Ondra HBase and this is partly because
they're running on things like HDFS
which are append-only file systems are
pending only storage all right so you
can only write blocks in HDFS you can't
go back and update things and that works
perfectly for a log structural system
like this so the second time I'm going
to have in addition to actually maybe
reading a lot it to avoid the problem
they're having to read everything we can
try to be clever and maybe do compaction
and recognize that instead of having to
replay the log every single for every
single log record we can take a chunk of
it and compress it back down to just so
that the the single records that
correspond to the changes actually got
made right so if I update my salary of
good from $1 or $2 and then the next day
I need to get another raise and go from
$2 or $3 instead of having to read those
2 log records I can just compress that
down and compact that down into a single
log record and now reads are much faster
right and again these are the systems
that are you actually using this so
what's the problem with compaction so
now for every sing to you were right
I penned my log record and then at some
later point I'm a compact these these
pages are compact the log records them I
send my page and I'm writing it out
again right this is called write
amplification if I do a write to a
record you know by transaction committer
my queries done I did my right it's in
my database but in the background I made
you be doing compaction and rewriting
that same log record over and over again
right in the tuple oriented pages that I
talked about for the most part if I
write to my page I write to my tuple
it's done
right once it's on disk I'm never to go
back and maybe write it out again I
different systems do different things
but in general that's the case
so with compaction the problem is that
we end up you know we end up writing up
the same record over and over again and
we amplify the amount of writes we do it
if using SSDs to have a limited number
of white right before they wear down the
cells you could burn this out you know
in a year or print out your device in a
year depending on how how many writes
this supports so there's different
levels of compaction or different sorry
different types of compaction you can do
I want to talk about two methods that
are used in rocks DB so
you might have heard a leveldb from
google leveldb is an M map database that
does log structured log structure
storage Facebook got a hold of it
renames and rocks TV got rid of em map
and then made it much much better so if
you want a log structured embedded
database you want to use rocks DB not
level DB and so rocks DB supports two
types of compaction the first is called
level compaction where the basic idea is
that all your rights first end up in
these sort of log files and then at some
point in the first level when you write
say to certain certain number files you
want to compact them and combine them
into a single larger sorted log log file
and put that into the next level you
keep doing this you keep doing this and
in the first level right you keep making
log records and they get too big you
move them down to the second level and
at some point the second level gets too
big and then you move them down into
giant files in the in the next level and
this is what I was me my write
amplification right I can do a single
write into the level zero but then as I
do compaction in the different levels I
end up writing that thing out over and
over again because I'm gonna read it
from one one page combine it with
another page and write it back out the
other type of compaction you knew
Universal compaction with this sort of
there's a single level and basically
what you do you just take two different
pages that are contiguous to each other
in space and then you combine them to a
single single single page or a single
file like this so we can talk about more
about rocks TB and leveldb maybe next
class but at a high level this is this
is what they're doing their log
structure page layouts and there's upper
levels of the systems know how to replay
the log records to put the data put the
page the two books back from the correct
form alright so the last thing I wanna
talk about is the tuple layout so again
we have files files up pages and within
those pages we can organize our data
that can contain tuples or critique log
records now we want to understand what
these actual tuples look like so a tuple
in our world is essentially a sequence
of bytes right that's all we're really
doing and it's the upper levels of the
systems that know how to then break
those bytes off into attributes put the
different types and expose them in a
more programmatic way to the to the
application so it's essentially the job
at the data system to indeed 'enter
prett those bytes interpret those values
in the manner that the program described
or defined for the for that table so now
within every single page we have tuples
again this is this is assumed we're
doing a tuple or the page layout not the
log structure stuff but every tuple is
gonna have a header and the header is
gonna take metadata about the tuple
itself right so it can contain more
visibility information about what
transactions read and wrote to that
tuple it contain a bitmap for which
attributes are consider null it usually
doesn't contain anything about what the
data actually looks like meaning we're
not gonna store any metadata about the
schema or the tuple all that is sort of
handled separately by other parts of the
system I said that means we don't to be
redundant least or the same information
about every single tuple over and over
again right so it sort of looks like
this right you have a you have a byte
array for your tuple you have your
header and then you're gonna have a
contiguous list of attributes that a
store just as a byte array right so
typically what happens is in those
database systems however you define the
the the ordering of the columns when you
call when you call create table that's
how it's gonna be written out to to disk
right so inside the page if I have my
five attributes ABCDE
I will have a Ashford's ABCDE lined up
in that order inside the tuple itself
now there's nothing about the relational
model that says you have to do that
right that's the beauty of the
abstraction between the logical and
physical so at the physical layer we can
reorganize these these these anyway we
want and at the logical layer you would
still see them and always in the correct
order now
as far as I know in dis based systems
except for the column store stuff which
we'll talk about next class pretty much
everyone always writes the data out and
the order that you define it that's just
done for simplicity reasons in the
advanced class we'll talk about in
memory databases where you actually do
want to reorganize how how you layout
data in memory because that that matters
for getting word
lines and you can get much better
performance that way but on disk again
we said we're just reading four kilobyte
pages from disk the
inside these pages actually doesn't
matter right that's always been the main
bottleneck
the other thing we can do also with with
with tuples is instead of just storing
all the data for a single single table
inside of a tuple we actually can
combine data from other tables inside of
our tuples inside our own page so
typically every page will have a for
doing tuple storage every page will only
contain data for one table so that I
have table foo then they'll be pages for
table foo but there's another technique
you can do to actually combine data from
different tables inside of a single page
to help you possibly speed up
performance so this is called Dino
denormalization so I didn't do a lecture
on normal forms and function
dependencies this year because it's you
really long and people always hate it
people start bleeding because it's
boring the only thing you really need to
know about normal forms is that they
exist in the textbook but nobody
actually does it in the real world the
way they start to think about it at a
high level it's a way to combine tables
or break tables apart and he's sure to
give this naturally if you have foreign
key dependencies right remember I talked
about artists and albums right you could
combine that into a single table but
then you're duplicating everything so
the normal forms to say actually split
them up so that you have you know single
records for thao for albums on single
records for artists right that's the
gist of normal forms do all that you
really need to know so with
denormalization it's it's instead of
splitting it apart it's putting it back
together so the user can define our
tables in the proper normal form with
separate you know separate tables but
underneath the covers inside of our
pages we actually can combine these
things to get better performance and
again it's completely transparent to the
actual application so I have two tables
here I have foo and bar and bar has a
foreign key dependency on actually a so
again if I'm destroying these things as
every page has its own tuples then I
would have a tuple for foo and one page
and then the tuples for bar and another
page so physical denormalization
essentially like doing a pre join since
I know there's a foreign key to
dependencies between these two tuples
so I'm likely to join them and together
all the time in queries so what I can
sted do
is actually in line all the values for
the bar table that relate to this
particular tuple inside that that tuple
so inside the tuple I have my actors ABC
its Rab but then I'm gonna have this
list of all the attributes see that
correspond to the bar table so now when
I when I won't run and run these run a
query I know how to sorry I know how to
come I know what portion of the tuple
belongs to foo and I know to it belongs
to bar and depending what the query once
I may actually read one or the other
right so again this piece of joins
because now instead of having to go get
one page fetch for foo one page fetch
for bar if I'm joining them together on
the foreign key it's one page fetch to
go get all deer that I need so I will
say that or this makes the Reapers
potentially faster but it can make
updates more expensive because if I run
out of space for putting advocacy in
then I need to reorganize my pages so as
in all cases in databases what seems
like a cool idea or a new idea is not
new and it's almost like that South Park
episode where they always say the
Simpsons did it right so in databases
it's always IBM did it so IBM did this
way back in 1970s with system R which is
the first relational database that they
built it turned out to be really
difficult to maintain and they abandoned
the idea when they went off and build
db2 right as I said doing updates it
becomes more expensive because you have
to reorganize things but now thirty
forty years later now a bunch of
companies are actually trying to do this
because it makes joins go faster so
Google does this in spanner for storing
protocol buffer data right they actually
in line the the the dependence the
dependent values for one sort of table
inside of another table so again you
reduce the number of page fetches you
have to go get there was a startup
called a key bond from up ten years ago
that was doing this for my sequel they
got bought up by a foundation DB which
then got bought out by Apple as far as
they know they end up abandoning this
this technique actually looks a lot also
too a lot like what the JSON or document
database is like rethink DB or MongoDB
or couch couch pays how they work right
because you don't really define tables
you define a JSON documents
and you can pre join related table or
related information inside that document
right so that you don't have to do
separate fetches to go get this at a
high level this is the same thing as
physical demineralization so it's the
same technique that IBM did in the 1970s
all right we have a few minutes left so
I want to about one last thing is how
we're gonna keep track of what what our
tuples are right right so again we said
every page has a page ID and there's a
page directory that says if you want
page 1 2 3 there's some directory
information that says where to go get it
now for tuples will talk about indexes
to go find them later on but internally
different data systems could represent
you know individual tuples in different
ways and these are usually called record
IDs so the most common approach where a
record ID is that it will be the page ID
plus an offset or a slot inside that
page right never I said if I want page 1
2 3 and give me the v tuple I know what
I've got and I look my slot array and
that tells you where to jump inside the
page to find that individual tuple so
some systems actually expose the
information to you at the application
level so in Postgres it's called the CT
ID and they store this has 44 bytes in
single byte they store this as a row ID
which is 8 bytes and then Oracle store
has their own row idea that stores this
in 10 bytes the reason why the Oracle
one is bigger is because they are
storing additional metadata information
about at what table what file this the
the tube election came from but in
practice it's sort of like this logical
number or that you're not really
supposed to using your application
because it can change at any time so I
want to give a quick demo of this so you
actually see them mmm right so this one
I'm gonna do Postgres at the top and and
seek a light at the bottom so I have two
tables actually have one table I just
made a simple table called R right so
post-course at the top has three tuples
1 0 1 1 0 2 1 2 3 and same thing that's
equal light at the bottom
so as I said Postgres is gonna store
what's called the CT ID and again this
is this is this is an internal thing
that you're not really supposed to using
your application because it can change
at any time so inside my query here I
can say r dot CT ID and Postgres knows
that I'm referring to its internal
identifier and you can see that
represent this as a pair of two numbers
right the first number is the page this
the second number is the offset in that
page right so now let's say if I do a if
I do a delete I go back right and it's
gone and you know the that's what used
to be the third tuple is is is still at
position zero two zero three because he
didn't reorganize things all right let's
say now I insert another tuple are you
married again and then you see Postgres
decided to rather than using position to
where the two budgets delete it was
stored they put it in the fourth
position
right so it's appending it to the the
end of the slot array so we won't talk
about the vacuum just now but the vac
can you think of the vacuum as doing
like garbage collection in in the JVM
right it's gonna go through and
reorganize every page and compact them
to free up any space that's not being
used anymore so now when I go back and
look at my table again remember I had
zero one zero three zero four right now
I have zero one zero two zero three
because it reorganizes the the layout of
the paper the tuples inside the slotted
page and then wrote that back out the
disk and now my CT IDs are different all
right so last year somebody had a
question whether I can do this can I
actually go to the table and say where a
CT ID equals something and Postgres is
amazing huh and let you do it right but
you're not supposed to do this right
you're not supposed to use the CT ID in
any way in your application form because
as I showed it can change at any time
all right so in sequel light
down below see the lights at a CCID they
call it a row ID right and you can see
it's just storing it as one two three I
said it's not a it's not like the page
ID and all set it's just this internal
sequence that Postgres maintains so now
if I do a delete right go back the the
second guy's gone and I do a new insert
and it didn't it didn't fill in the slot
it just used you know just depending to
the end right again I think in actually
secretly I don't know whether they
guarantee that's I think actually I
think it's sequel like they guarantee
that this is always always be always
increasing and they always stay with the
tuple let's say so if I delete every
single tuple right there's nothing there
now go insert back that same tuple yeah
I started off with one okay
so yeah I don't want to use it as a good
could change right yes so this question
is in the case of Postgres all right
this thing called the vacuum his
question is does this have to be done
manually newer versions of post-crisis
you know you do not do this man like
this look will cover this when we talk
about multi-version concurrency toll
basically post chris is doing is any
single time you update a tuple it
doesn't actually overwrite the existing
tuple it makes a new one and it
maintains an internal list internal like
link list I say here's go here's how to
go get the version that you ability that
you want right so if I go back here so
the back can be the way to go and prune
out the the older version that no one
can see anymore look we see that again
so if I go here I have three tuples so
I'd say I do update update are set vow
equal Y by Y where ID equals one or
three actually meeting to do this first
before I do that
let's go see what the c-jes RCT II's so
now I'll run that query all right so
we're gonna update the the the second
table I do my update is that correct
yeah and then it took that it took me
actually this is a good example of like
how the relation wall is ever so before
the update when I did a select it put
the second tuple in the second position
after my update it now became the third
tuple right because again the relational
model is unordered so what happened was
I did my update and I appended the new
change for this tuple that was here now
at 0 to now at 0 for so now as I'm doing
my scan I'm just reading them in based
on the offsets so the tuple in the last
all set and it's showing up as the last
one in my my output alright cuz again
the relational model isn't organized and
there's note there's no notion of
ordering in this case here right so same
thing I mean the point I wanted to make
here is that it was at position 0 2
after the update as now at 0 4 in the
background Postgres knows that it has to
run the vacuum I think it runs it's a
combination of either I've changed the
table so much or I'm running out of
space or it's it's a different periods
right again this is what a database
penetrator can do for you if the vacuum
can be expensive operation because
they're essentially reading everything
every page that has got changed since
the last time you ran the vacuum which
means reading them in reorganizing and
running back out you may not want to do
that during the day because you're
trying to you know keep up with the
workload so maybe want to do less
vacuuming during the day more vacuuming
it at night hey this is something that
they administrator can control all right
any questions about row IDs so the some
of them will actually store them
directly in the tuple I think C code
lights doing this Oracle does this all
those systems like Postgres don't
actually store the the record ID or the
row ID in the tuple itself right cuz
it's a waste of space I believe and
arrived at based on the page ID and all
set
all right so what we covered today we
covered how to organize the database and
pages we covered how to actually track
those pages so that when upper-level
system says give me a particular page it
knows how to go find that we didn't look
two different ways actually store those
pages we talked about how to actually
organize the tools inside of those pages
right so next class we'll talk about
sort of more more complicated things
that don't deviate from what we've
talked about here but it's sort of game
building upon what we've done so we'll
talk about how you have you back
actually represent the values inside of
the tuples themselves by going even
further inside the page and then we'll
talk about different storage models so a
storage model is a way to actually
organize the data within a table and so
what I'll say is everything I've showed
here today is called a roast or meaning
like the for every single tuple it's
sort of organized in contiguously across
all the attributes that one tuple
doesn't begin until the next one
finishes another way to do this is
actually organize these things as
columns for all the values for a single
column across multiple tuples or stored
contiguously right I mean the page
layout stuff doesn't change so the way
we're organizing our pages with
directories doesn't change just how
we're actually representing the data
inside this pages changes okay
[Music]
I wanna party by the 12-pack case of a
boy six-pack 40 actor gets the real I
dream please put your drinking proper 12
ow they say bill makes your flat but
saying eyes is straight so it really
don't matter