[Music]
today's lecture is gonna be on puff pool
right this is the how we're gonna manage
memory inside of our database system so
Before we jump into the material uh turn
this on on today okay the two upcoming
database talks that I think are
interesting you guys want to check out
so there's a talk today in the 8th floor
and gates from the co-founder of
relational AI I actually don't know what
they're doing I know who the person is I
don't know what the new companies doing
but so he's a semi-famous dude so this
this should should be an interesting
talk to this be I think sort of
databases meets machine learning and
machine learning needs it meets
databases and then Thursday next week
we'll have the second session in our
seminar series on Hardware accelerate
databases with the co-founder of map D
map D is a another GPU database system
so that'll be on Thursday on the fourth
floor
in the CIC building right whether you
come out of the elevators you go right
well left pretending what elevator but
there's these glass doors go inside that
and the talk will be in there ok ok so
as we said last class the last two
lectures were all about organizing
database files on disk right how we're
gonna lay out the the the files and
decide then we have pages and instead of
the pages we lay out our data and then
we sort of punted on this this idea of
how are we actually gonna bring this
into memory and manage that right
because we said we can't have our data
system operate directly on files on disk
everything blows it has to be brought in
memory before we can even read and write
to it so that's what today's lecture is
about right the second part of how we're
gonna actually make make decisions on on
where to bring in the pages into memory
and then how do you make decisions to
evict them when we run out of space
right because the the size of our
database is most often gonna be much
larger than the amount of memory that we
have so we can't keep everything in
memory
so the another way to think about the
problem is is discussing this this sort
of this trade-off between sort of
spatial and temporal control of data so
spatial control is what we've talked
about so far it's right it's basically
how we're gonna write files to disk
we're gonna like lay out our pages on
disk right and the goal of this was as
we said is that since discs are faster
at doing salento access definitely we're
spinning disk hard drive because it's a
mechanical arm it has to jump around on
the platter and read and we read the
tracks but even the SSDs as well if we
can have the data that we know is gonna
be accessed together in a query
physically located next to each other
inside of our disks then we'll have will
have faster access right cuz they're now
again thinking of the worst case
scenario of the spinning spinning disk
our drive the arm has to jump around all
over the platter every single time I
need to read a single page that's gonna
be really slow or if I'm to plop the arm
down in one location and then read
sequentially a bunch of pages that's
gonna be much faster so now what we're
talking about today is the second issue
of thinking about the temporality of the
data we're accessing right and this
means how we're actually going to
control when do we read pages into
memory and when do we write the map back
out the disk if necessary right so we're
not discussing where we're gonna write
these things a disk we'll talk a little
bit where we actually store them in
memory but overall it's it's you know
whether the pages are next to each other
in memory for our purposes here doesn't
actually matter in real systems if
you're in memory it does but for our
purposes here we ignore that so it's
really about been deciding how we're
actually going to when we actually want
to move data back and forth and the goal
here obviously since this was so much
slower than then mandi ram and memory we
want to minimize the number of stalls
that will incur because we had to read
data from disk right it's in some ways
just unavoidable as I said because the
databases we larger than total matter
memory that we have but if we're smart
about how we stage things and time our
accesses and write backs we can we can
minimize this impact right way to think
about this is I know I'm gonna see read
the same page over and over and over
again
maybe I don't want to write that out
that disk and I always keep that in
memory but if I read something once and
I'll never read it again then I want to
go ahead and maybe evict it and throw it
away so these are the kind of things
that we're gonna discuss today and this
providing in this overyou diagram that I
showed last class we've covered the
bottom part we know how to lay up pages
in the files and now it's the second
part above this write the buffer pool
alright the buffer pool is gonna be the
in memory cache that the the database
systems going to maintain all the pages
that it read from the files on disk and
we said before that this looks a lot
like virtual memory from the operating
system but the operating system as we'll
see it was go along it's not gonna do as
a good job as our database system
because we fully not fully but we have a
better understanding of exactly what
queries want to do and therefore we can
prepare ourselves and read and write
data from disk into memory accordingly
in a way that the operating system can't
do because the operating system only
sees like the reads and white sort of
granular level just sees the reads and
sees the writes on a page doesn't
understand anything about how the extra
queries are accessing those pages
because the OS treats all pages is the
same where as well see as we go along
inside our database system some pages
correspond to indexes some pages
correspond to inmate it results of
queries and not all of them are the same
it should not always be treated the same
but the OS doesn't know this so it can't
do as good a job as we can so for
today's agenda we're gonna first sort of
talk about the the bubble manager right
at a high level pretty easy to implement
the basic the basic concept of it but
we'll see the more complicated things
you can do in the actual policies you
maintain inside of this and for
replacement and allocation and then
we'll talk briefly about what are the
other memory pools look like inside the
database system okay so at a high level
the barber pole is just a large region
of memory that the database is going to
manage in its own address space and it's
gonna use this to again copy pages that
the queries want to access from the disk
and put them into the buffer pool all
right so you sort of think this duffel
is just some large memory region like a
giant a byte array and then it's gonna
split up the byte array into what are
called frames
and these will be this the same size
size as your pages everything was a
question last time whether the size of a
page for you know the the large overflow
pages are they different than the the
rather tuple pages everything's always
be the same page size because they need
to fit into these frames right and
that's how it's gonna figure out you
know where the next we're the stopping
starting point for every pages because
otherwise you have to have an
indirection layer to figure out you know
help the length of things at their
verbal length so we call these these
open spaces frames
alright the slot where you can actually
write data in I'll try to use frame as
much as possible but you can sort of see
how the same concept at a high level
just has to have different names in the
database system right so we have a file
you have pages and set of pages we can
have slots and the slots and where we
can store tuples and then instead of our
buffer pool what we may want to call
slots or to call frames writes the space
where we can write a page so what
happens is when when the davison when a
query wants to read a page we're just
going to go down on disk and make an
exact copy of this in our in our in our
buffer pool right so the query wants to
read page one there's an exact copy of
that page in that in a frame in our
buffer pool right so there's no
transformation there's no marshalling or
serialization process of copying the
data from from the disk into the page
it's an exact byte for byte copy if you
bring in compression that complicates
things slightly but for our purposes
here how it's being stored on disk is
exactly how it's been gonna be stored in
memory and our database has knows how to
operate on that structure right now it
was about slot of page layouts that
knows how to operate on the tuples
inside of them no windows I do not want
to upgrade okay so the for this purpose
here again I might show my example
before I talk about how the execution
engine wants to say I want page number
two and then there had to be something
that says well here's the here's the
frame in my buffer pool where you can go
find a copy of page two and this is
called the page table insert sense you
just think of this as a hash map that
map's page IDs to a frame a where can
you store it right and so if I want to
do my look up and say you know I want
page two I go my page table either
tells me it's there and where and what
frame it's in in my buffer pool or it's
gonna tell me it's not there in which
case I have to go to my page directory
and find where that location is on disk
and then decide you know where I can
copy that frame into this so now we want
to talk a little bit about you know
thread safety in this because you know
if you're if it's single threaded then
this this hash people doesn't need to be
protected right you just you just go in
just find the entry one and then just
read it but because we're on disk and
because modern systems have a lot of CPU
cores we're gonna have multiple threads
multiple queries running at the same
time all accessing this this page table
so what we don't want to happen is we
don't want to maybe access a page all
right we go to the page table we find
out actually where it is and then we
start reading it and then some other
thread comes along says why I'm taking
this page away and goes and replaces
replaces it so what we're gonna do is
anytime we want to access a page we're
gonna have to pin it in the page table
right think of this like a simple
reference counter it's just you know a
counter that says the number of active
queries that are accessing this page
right right now okay and we stored this
in the page table and not inside the
page themselves because we don't
actually need to make this this
reference counter adorable right so when
the page gets evicted the reference
counter doesn't need to be stored as
well right so we're gonna store
everything in the in memory and in marry
page table and so I'm gonna pages pin
anybody else mate can still come and go
find page three in this case here and
still read it it's just the buffer pool
manager is not allowed to evict it
because it knows somebody is actually
accessing right now so now I'll say I
come along and another thread comes
along and wants to read a page that's
not either one and three and it's not in
there so then it's gonna go ahead and
actually take up pick up a lock on this
location right so I want to read this
page I know that it's not there I'll
find a slot night and iframe and my page
table there I know a I want to store
this and so I take a take a latch and
then I go ahead and then fetch the data
that I need and update the page entry
right so this is the weight again I
I want to I want to read a page that's
not there so then I have to find a place
where I can store the reference to that
page in my page table so I take a latch
on that on that location then in the
background go fetch it and then update
the page table right and then at this
point I released my latch because I've
done whatever I wanted to do if I just
had to read it then I don't need to pin
it if I'm gonna modify it then I want it
then I want to pit it okay actually
sorry that's not true I mean you know
Claire if I'm gonna read it I pin it
even though I'm gonna write to it I pin
it but I don't need to maintain any
additional information if I'm just
reading it as soon as I'm done reading
it I can throw the pin away if I'm
writing to it I have to maintain a dirty
bit dirty flag says I modified this
thing and this is prevent the database
system from writing it back out to disk
or just throwing it away because it
knows that some other query modified the
page when it was when it went access to
it and therefore we have to make sure
that those changes eventually make it
back to disk so that's the dirty flag
does for us so the one thing I need to
discuss is the distinction between locks
and latches if you're coming from an
operating system background right you
may have you know you may just refer to
everything you know as logs in a
database system least in the database
world locks are different than latches
so if your operating system world a lock
is basically what we would call latch
here like you think of like a mutex
would be up what we're calling a latch
so latch is going to be used to protect
the internal data structures of the
database system so my example I showed
before I want to write to my hash table
I set a latch to prevent anybody else
from modifying that location because I
want to write into it and that latch can
be implemented as a mutex it can also be
implemented as a spin lock which is an
unfortunate name because that muddies
the story here in the database where a
lock will see later on this has to be a
higher-level construct or a logical
construct that we're going to use to
protect database entities so I can take
a lock on a tuple write or I can take a
lock on on a on a on a database or a
table
but I can't take a latch on this because
that's the underlying data structure so
when I take a lock I would have to take
a latch to update the lock table so this
clear locks are for high level
constructs and we'll see this later on
when we talk about you know concurrency
control the latches that we're going to
use to protect the internal data
structures so in sequel I can take locks
I can't take latches latches are
actually how the Davis isms actually
implemented okay and as I said this if
you're coming from an OS background you
would call latch a lock but in databases
we use the term latch okay the other
thing we don't talk about is the
distinction between the page table and
the page directory so the page directory
is the on disk information about where
to find pages for a given page ID so as
I said like the the if our data is
broken across multiple files the page
directory could say Oh page 1 2 3 is in
this file that's all set page 4 5 6 4 5
6 is in another file at this all set so
any changes we make to the page
directory when we bring it into memory
has to then get written out to disk cuz
when we if we restart the system come
back we need to know where our pages are
the page table is the in-memory data
structure that we're going to use to
figure out inside of our buffer pool how
to map B page IDs to a frame if it's
been copied in and so for this we don't
need to write this out to disk at all
because if we crash to come back we
don't care we don't care what the buffer
pool looks like the last time we crash
because we're going to repopulate it as
query start executing and reading start
reading data so the page directory again
is on disk it's mapping page IDs to
locations on files the page table is in
memory and it's mapping page IDs to
slots in the buffer pool and we don't
need to make that durable okay
all right so the as I said anytime we
want to go into the page table and do a
lookup we always have to take a latch to
make sure that nobody swaps out the
thing we're trying to read as we're
trying to read it right but this becomes
a contention point because now if you
have a lot of threads aulac trying to
access the page table at the same time
and there may be taking latches you know
do something really coarse-grained I got
latch for the entire page table or you
take latches for you know individual
elements or buckets but regardless if
you have a lot of threads and everyone's
trying to do the same thing at the same
time then this is going to become a
major bottleneck in our system so one
way to alleviate this problem is
actually to have multiple buffer pools
so my example I just showed I had a
single page table in single buffer pool
there's no reason the data system
couldn't have multiple ones and that way
it's a basically what happen is your if
you if your query comes along and says I
want page one to three you can just hash
that one to three and that will map you
to a buffer pool instance and then
inside of that buffer pool instance then
it has its own page table and its own
region of memory right this is sort of
way to partition the the workload across
multiple multiple instances so that
everyone's not trying to acquire the
same latches at the same time so much of
different ways you can implement this
you just sort of say the database
instance itself or the debasement system
instance two can have multiple buffer
pools and they're allocated you know
they're split evenly for the total
amount of memory you want to allocate
for your buffer pool you can have a
buffer pool per database you have a
buffer pool per page type so you could
say here's my buffer pool for index
pages here's my buffer pool for data
pages or tuple pages so these are bunch
of systems that support this my sequel
db2 oracle sybase and see what server
Informix so with the exception of my
sequel although my sequel is really good
I would call these other ones below it
enterprise databases right these are
like what traditional old companies
would actually use but my Siegel is
super common it's used everywhere now
though so in the case of my sequel as
far as I know at least for version 5 I
haven't checked version 8 you can only
declare that you have multiple buffer
pool instances in the commercial systems
they have way more knobs that you can
you can change and tune and they support
all these different variations in the
back yes
so your question is if you have multiple
instances how do you map what sorry both
the second part its question so if I
have multiple buffer pool instances how
do I map a page ID how do I take a page
ID and know what instance I should look
in yeah so it's easiest way to use it's
just hashing right I have I have five
buffer pool instances for a given page
ID I hash it mod five and that'll tell
me you know which instance I go to right
and that me and that's immutable right
so no matter what you know the same page
ID is always gonna match to the same
page buffer pool instance you can do
something real simple too like you can
do range partitioning but that's I don't
think anybody actually does this right
you could say anyway anything would pay
to be zero to a thousand goes to this
one one thousand one to two thousand
those of this one the hashing wants more
common because that handles the case
where that if the database is always
growing your your range of page IDs
increases you don't have to reshuffle
things around okay and again the reason
why we want to do this because will
reduce contention on the latches as we
as we go into our page table and we can
actually improve our locality so if we
know that we see certain queries are
doing have certain access patterns
having a buffle instance for maybe
indexes versus the tuples we can sort of
isolate the two buffer pool instances to
two different replacement policies or
allocation policies for each of those
different access patterns all right and
what we'll see examples as examples of
this in a second so so the again the the
context are talking about here again
these are the things that the operating
system can't do for you because it
doesn't know what you're actually trying
to do right so again because we know
what our pages actually mean in some
ways might be know whether this index
versus data we can allocate different
buffer pool instances like this another
thing we can do that that's right no
clutter that the OS can't always do
correctly is to do prefetching so
prefetching is basically
says that I know I'm gonna go ahead and
read read subsequent pages given what my
queries trying to do so rather than
waiting for me to then try to access
that page in the page table see that
there's no entry you know get it get a
page fault while I go have to go fetch
the page that I need I can go ahead and
start prefetching pages ahead of time
because I know my queries gonna need it
in the future so let's say on a simple
query that's key one that's doing
sequential scan across the entire table
right now my page is 0 to 5 and my
buffer pool is empty so in the first
case I repaid 0 it's not there so go
ahead and fetch it in and I do this as I
scan along but if I recognize that my
query is essentially gonna read every
page then maybe at some point I
recognize that oh I know I'm gonna read
page 2 &amp; 3 so while I'm accessing page 1
or I'm retrieving page 1 and putting my
buffer pool let me go ahead and prefetch
2 &amp; 3 put that into my buffer pool and
then that way when now my query keeps on
going I don't have to stall because the
the next pages I need are already there
right so the operating system can do
this in some cases right it can
recognize that when you're doing so much
to scan across a large file it'll
essentially do the same thing it'll
start trying to prefetch prefetch your
your pages and this example here the
obvious it could probably do this or can
do this because we're accessing a file
sequentially
but not every access pattern of the
database system is going to be
sequential like this right so a very
common case is to do index scans or
index range scans so again so say we
have an index here and we're gonna run
it we want to run a range scan where
we're gonna traverse the tree doesn't
matter whether it's a B+ tree or
whatever data structure just it's a tree
and we're going to traverse the tree get
to some leaf page and then scan along
the leaf leaf pages to find all the data
that we need so the very first thing we
have to do a query starts we have to
read the the index page right because we
have to know you know with the to know
where our entry point into the index is
so therefore this when we go ahead and
pet fetch page page index page 0 bring
that into our buffer pool then we jump
down maybe to this side of the tree
and we went index page one together and
get that but now we're gonna go down
this too
to the other side of the tree and start
scanning across the the lead pages like
that so now we're gonna read page three
and page five
but the OS may think that oh well I
think you're actually going to read page
two and let me go ahead and prefetch
that bat for you which is not actually
one right so we want page three and five
so we the database system could
recognize oh well I didn't go to page
two I want to go to page three and then
the next leaf page that I'm gonna scan
across is page five so not page four so
let me go ahead and prefetch those two
guys all right
the OS can't do this because it doesn't
know what's inside these pages right we
know in their database ISM that you know
because we where the one X you built
this data structure we built the tree we
know what pages are there we know what
the queries trying to do right cuz we
have the sequel we have the query plan
so we can then infer from that what
pages we think you're gonna need now
this does mean we have to do some extra
work like you know maintain symmetric
metadata possibly in the index to know
what our neighbor page is right so then
go ahead and prefetch if they have rules
to recognize that I think we're doing a
special scan of along the lead pages or
index again and luckily pages have
recognized with it you know that's an
opportunity for us to prefetch it's more
work but the benefit can be quite
substantial and this is actually a very
common access pattern do range scans
along an index like this the next kind
of optimization we can do is called scan
sharing so with scan sharing the basic
idea is that if we have queries that are
running at the same time and they're
accessing the same data rather than
treating every every query as in its own
island by itself and just making
decisions about what pages are fetching
in and out you know for each individual
query the data system can recognize that
the queries are trying to do the
basically the same thing or they're
trying to read the same data it may not
be the exact same query but there have
to read the same data and then we can
just have the the queries sort of
piggyback off each other and reuse the
data that we've already pulled into our
buffer pool to avoid having to us
things out unnecessarily and incurred
more disk rights right so the way it is
sort of that again think about this is
that if I'm doing so much on scans I
have my one query starts the second
quarter comes behind it and start a
little bit later I maybe want to pick up
whether the the first guy is already
running and reused the data that it's
already pulled in rather than starting
everything from scratch
alright the way the way we're gonna
implement these scans we'll see this
when we talk about query processing it's
essentially a cursor for each query that
keeps track of what pages it's read as
it goes along the the table scan and it
knows what you know how far it's got to
go and what pages that it's missing
right so the this is supported again as
far as I know only in the major
commercial systems right so this be a
reoccurring theme throughout the
semester we'll see that the very
expensive enterprise databases do way
more sophisticated things than the open
source ones just because they've had a
lot of money and a lot of people
spending time to fix these things you
know make these things work as well good
as possible so as far as they know for
those scan sharing which we'll see in
the next slide this is fully supported
in IBM db2 and sequel server oracle only
supports what are called cursor sharing
if you actually run the exact same query
at the exact same time right if there's
any sort of minor deviation in the where
clause or even like that what the Select
output is it doesn't think that this
they can read the same data and it
treats them as separate 7-piece so to do
scan sharing basically for the the first
query starts it has its cursor at
scanning through and then the second
queries cursor will will recognize I can
I can run along with them with the first
guy and just keep track of what data it
has missed from not starting at the
beginning so that it can loop back
around and pick everything that it
missed so a simple example will be like
this today I have query one and it's
doing special scan it's going to read
every page to compute the the sum on the
value so when it starts it's at the
beginning there's nothing nothing in our
buffer pool so we go ahead and fetch
page zero and we just keep going down
and to get the second page here now we
want to read page three and then we have
to we only have three frames and our
buffer bolus we have to victim a so
assuming
a simple replacement policy we just
picked the page that was last accessed
that would be page zero so you want to
go ahead and throw that away so that we
can put in page three the next page that
we need but now during this time query
two starts and it basically wants to
execute this new it's not the exact same
query it's computing an average instead
of a sum but it's still going to read
all the same pages so if we started from
the beginning what's the problem the
first page that this this query needs is
page zero but that was actually the last
page we just evicted so now what would
happen is we'd have to go back in our
buffer pool and figure out all right
well you know I need to make space let
me go Victor page right and it sucks
because we just we just fetch that you
know we just we just had it in memory
and we lost it so we now we have to pay
another another disk read so instead
with scan sharing you can recognize that
these these two queries that need to
read the same data in the same pages so
cue to just hops along with q1 it reads
the same same same pages right some one
disk read brings it to the buffer pool
and the sort of a notification system
that says all right you two guys need
these pages it's now ready
so then q1 finishes because it reaches
all the pages and then q2 recognizes oh
well I need to go back and get the other
two pages that I missed right so again
this this by being smarter about what we
know queries want to do we can avoid
having unnecessary disk reads in a way
that would be difficult to do with if
you don't know anything about what the
queries are actually trying to do
another optimization is be what's called
buffer pool bypass so we'll see this in
a second but these special scans are
problematic because they're gonna
pollute our cache with data that we
actually don't may not need again in the
future so in my last example in the last
slide I did was I was doing scratch to
scan on the table so as I read a page I
brought into my buffer pool I did you
know dip whatever query processing I
wanted to own it and then I just went on
to the next next page
but now the that page I just read is
probably not gonna be needed and again
in the future but it's the last thing I
just put in my buffer pool so and then
it may be evicting data that actually
you want to keep in there but I had to
do that cuz I didn't make space for all
these pages I'm reading as I'm doing the
scan so with buffer pool bypass the
basic idea is that the database system
can say all right I'm gonna do a central
scan and I know that this data is
probably not to be neat about anybody
else so rather than going paying the
overhead of
updating the page table and putting it
in a frame in the buffer pool I'll just
keep it a local copy in my private
memory for my query and then when I'm
done with it I just throw it away
right so this avoids having to go to
update the page table update the buffer
pool I update my own local copy of it
all right so in inform X these are
called Lite scans in Postgres we'll see
in a second they basically have our own
private buffer for queries as well if
you're doing sequential scan I actually
don't know whether it actually goes to
the buffalo manager I just know that it
maintains a zone a little private buffer
for every query so another thing we need
to talk about now is the the OS page
cache so the operating system is gonna
maintain for the file system its own
cache of pages that it reads right if
you ever look on H top on Linux but
you'll see how much the how much
remember your processes are using you
know on the heap but then there's also
going to be the OS page cache of copies
of pages that it's read from from the
file system so if you don't do anything
special when you open up a file in your
in your program and read a bunch of data
in the OS is gonna copy make copies of
that and the certain file system a page
cache alright this is different than
virtual memory but now the problem is if
we do this then now every time I read a
page in my buffer pool my database
system the OS is gonna make a copy of it
and then I'm have another copy of it in
my in my in my database system so it's
it's doubled amount of memory for
reading the same data so most database
systems turn off this page cache and the
way you do it is you pass the Oh direct
flag in Lib C when you open up a file
and say I don't want this file to be
backed by the the file system cache I'm
gonna manage manage it myself so this
avoids having
again these were done in copies of pages
it allows you to have begin full control
over the eviction policies of how things
are evicted out of memory right as far
as I know most major database systems
with except from one tells you to turn
off the page cache in the operating
system because they want to manage
memory itself the major system that I
know that does use it is actually
Postgres Postgres actually uses the
theirs page cache and they argue that
the this is not a significant problem
for them because the the OS it still has
its own buffer pool but it's but it
still relies on the OS page cache and
just by having that sort of an extra
layer it's one less thing that they have
to manage and they it's a minimal impact
on performance so let's let's see how
actually how this works all right so
this is Postgres running on machine back
in my office and connect to it here so
the first thing I want to show you is
what the page cache actually looks like
one again if you run H top it's kind of
hard to see there and I'm a laser
pointer right so this is the matter of
memory that the system is using right so
this green bar here that's the resident
memory of the processes running on the
system then all of this yellow stuff
here is the the OS file system cache
right so this machine has 32 gigs of ram
the resident set size of the processes
running on my shoot machine is only 5
gigs and the rest is being used by the
OS page cache right so we can flush this
if you pass in this command here sink
echo three and you pass it to this
special location in the proc file system
this will flush all the page caches in
for my system so now if I go back and
look at each top again right now my
resident set size is still five gigs but
my but my total matter memory systems
using is is now exactly five gigs
because the OS file system cache is gone
so let's go into post read so we're
gonna use the same two tables that I
used last time to show you the district
between decimals and reals right I think
is like ten million entries so we're
gonna do is we're gonna turn off
parallel workers right again this this
is a it's only one query running at a
time so what we're gonna do is we can
execute a query that will just just do
that same summation that we have before
so now I'm gonna pass in I'm gonna use
explain and I'm gonna explain analyze
which actually runs the query throughs
use the query plan but I'm gonna pass in
this extra flag called buffers that's
going to show you what percentage of the
data that or pages we read actually this
query will be either in the buffer pool
cache or in the or had to read it
actually on disk okay so let me know so
let me restart Postgres to so it there's
nothing in the file system cache sorry
there's nothing in its buffer pool cache
so this point I flushed the file system
buffers and I restarted Postgres there's
nothing in memory that I can use
everything's always gonna have to go to
disk so now yeah execute this query
right so he did though
it did the parallel scan but that's okay
actually me restart this
blow that away blow that away come back
here
turn off parallel workers good okay same
query right so this part here this told
you that for to do this special scale on
this table that it had to read 400 for
forty four thousand pages right so this
is saying that there's nothing there's
nothing in the cache that it actually
was able to reuse so now if I come back
and execute the same query again now it
says that um can I highlight this yeah
here now says hit 32 I'll explain what
that is in a second right this is
actually the private cache for the for
the for this query it's always gonna be
32 32 pages right but then the the the
number of pages we read from disk went
down by 32 because we we had 32 in our
and our buffer pool alright so we can
force the database system to fetch
everything into into its buffer pool so
it has this thing called PG warm right
it says it's a special extension for
Postgres that comes with when you stall
post graph this tells it basically
pre-war my buffer pool by reading
everything right so we execute that and
it's gonna come back and tell us that it
read for that 44,000 pages and into our
buffer pool right so now when I go back
and run that same query
my hit ratio went up or right the number
of hits went up I still had to read some
data from desk right everything guess
what's the issue here why did why wasn't
everything in the buffer pool it's not
large enough exactly right
so you set when you when you set the
data system up you say how much remember
you want to use for the buffer pool
right the data system has to be told
that because otherwise it just takes
everything right so that's why we only
had we had we didn't wasn't everything
wasn't always we didn't all of our page
reads all of our pages we want to access
work in our buffer pool so what we can
do now is go back to the Postgres
configuration alright Postgres has this
flag has something called shared buffers
all right so we want to set this to be
the right size so for this if we go back
here we know we had to read we had to
read this number of pages right Postgres
pages are 8 kilobytes so what we're
going to want to do is we're going to
store it we want to have set our buffer
pool size to be 8 kilobytes times 4 4 -
8 4 so that'll be 4 4 - 8 4 times 8 all
right so about 350 5 megabytes so now we
go back to this guy let's round up 356
right so now again we're setting the
buffer pool size to be 300 356 megabytes
we got our restart Postgres to tell it
to take that in effect all right
then we go back here where you connect
to our database I'm going to pre-warm
the table and then now when I run my
query
there you go the hit went to exactly
what we wanted sorry hello my cursor is
there yeah right there see so to do this
we didn't have to read anything from
bump from from the database I'm sorry
read anything from disk everything was
in our buffer pool all right the reason
I like using Postgres is like and omus
is a textbook implantation of a database
system yes so his question is is is the
is the buffer pool allocated where sorry
in the in the yeah so this question is I
showed this version H not before and I
said the green bar from memory was the
resident memory of processes and this
question is where's the buffer pool is
it is it in this resident memory or is
it in the file system cache it is in the
resident memory it's literally calling
malloc inside of the process and that
shows up in in part of the green bars
here
it doesn't have any control over the
file system cache that is all managed by
the operating system at the subsequent
bars so that so the file system decides
the file I started the operating system
decides how much I wants to allocate or
split up the memory for the fosston cash
versus the memory for processes right
post-christmas doesn't have any control
over that they always just does whatever
wants to do so I want to show you how we
know that the the database system is
hitting the file system cache in case of
Postgres so if I go back to I say this
query took me it takes about 12
milliseconds so this is run it or take
700 milliseconds right so I run it
multiple times it's always gonna take
the same amount roughly that's actually
going faster
all right guys all right so fluctuates
so in this case here now if I restart
Postgres this will blow away the buffer
pool right from the process if I now go
back here turn timing back on make sure
I'm connected
turn off parallel threads so at this
point I've restarted the database the
buffer pool is gone there's nothing in
the buffer pool I'm not gonna run PG
warm I'm just gonna run the query and
see how how fast it is and if it's the
same speed as this seven hundred seven
hundred forty milliseconds if it's the
same speed as that then we know it's
hitting the fossum cache right it's it's
a little bit slower right so if I was if
I blow away the faucet in cache
I actually did this in beginning I was
roughly about one point two seconds now
I'm 700 millisecond there was nothing in
the buffer pool but the thought the
operating system has it cached so the
davidon can go ahead and read that so
again this is specific to Postgres most
data systems do not rely on the page
cache of the operating system because
they want to manage all memory
themselves
okay so is this clear and again we can
use explain explain analyze with put the
buffers and it'll tell us what
percentage of the queries are hitting
the butter pool in this case here
because I didn't run PG warm it still
has to read a lot of things from from
the from the file system actually that
exigent time is pretty slow
and I will do that later but maybe
because we're running analyze now okay
alright so these demos are sort of
expose to you or show you that like the
things I'm talking about here you can
actually see in some ways without
reading the postcode you can see the
behavior that matches up with with the
policies that were described all right
so the next thing we want to talk about
is how do we actually make decisions on
what frames or what pages to remove from
our buffer pool right it's super easy
when everything's and we have enough
memory because we just fetch the pages
in and we don't worry about you know
making new space but obviously again we
our database may be larger than the
amount of memory we have so we have to
make decisions about how to make a room
for new pages we want to fetch and and
and victim our buffer pool to put the
new one in so the there's a couple sort
of trade-offs or things we're gonna care
about and our replacement policy all
right one is obviously correctness and
by correctness I mean that we don't want
to write up you know we don't want to
throw away data that a transaction just
updated or query just updated before
actually making out the disk right
because then we lose everything we want
our replacement policy to be accurate in
that we don't want to do the dumbest
thing and like a Vick the most important
page because you know we're gonna need
it right away we want to have a good
estimation of making decisions about
pages that we know we think we're not
gonna need so we go ahead and throw them
away we want this be fast because as I
said when I do a lookup into the page
table and like my page is not there and
then I need to decide what page to
remove I have to figure out what page I
want to take out and put a latch there
so I'm holding a latch while I'm running
this for placement policy and if my
proposed policy is like you know NP
complete and takes days to run then
that's bad because I'm holding that
latch during that entire time so you
want this thing to be as fast as
possible and of course we want to have a
low metadata overhead
cuz we don't want to at the store you
know a ton of extra data then maybe
larger than the echo page itself just to
figure out what page we want to remove
so this cached replacement policy of
buffer placement policy this is like one
of the oldest problems in CS the
literature goes back to like the 1950s
1960s there are some things that that we
can that we can apply from newer systems
and newer would be like 1990s that we
can do smarter things than sort of the
general approach that everyone uses but
we'll just go over high levels what
these other better ways to implement is
the better way the abilities things are
so the the most commonly used policy is
LRU or least recently used and all we
really do here is just mainly maintain a
timestamp of when a page was accessed by
a query and then when we have to select
a page to a bit from our buffer pool we
just choose the one with the the oldest
timestamp right pretty easy to speed
things up and what maybe what we can do
in our in our page table or our buffer
pool list frames we can maybe sort them
ahead of time by the by their timestamp
and just always pop things out and move
it to the end as every time their access
so that way when it comes time to evict
something we just look at the head of
that list and is those the pages we want
to go ahead and remove another approach
that's commonly used is called clock you
think clock is just an approximation of
LRU I know this is used in a couple
systems there's actually used also in
Linux roughly for their page page
replacement policy so the basic idea is
that you're gonna maintain a simple bit
for every single page that tells you
whether it has been accessed since the
last time you checked it and then every
time you do access it you just set that
bit to one and then there's gonna be
this clock hand that's going to go
around and the circular buffer and just
checks every you know every page to see
whether it was accessed the last time it
was the clock hand went around so say we
have four buffers like this or pages
like this 1 2 3 4 every page is gonna
have a reference yet and initially it's
always set to 0 so when I start off if I
if I
QWERTY access to this page I just go
ahead and flip a bit to one and then now
there's this clock hand that gets moves
around in a circular fashion every
single time I need to go a Bic to page
it just you know looks at the next one
and decides whether the bid is zero if
yes it can be evicted if it's one then
it keeps it but it resets it resets it
to zero so the very beginning the clock
says I need to fix something so I'm
pointing to the first guy I said it's
set the one so I know I don't want to
throw it away but I'll go ahead and set
it to zero so then I come down to the
next guy his reference counter is zero
so I know it's not been it has not been
accessed since the last time I came
around so it's safe for me to go ahead
and indict this and I can replace it
with with another page then I keep going
around the clock like this I say page
three and four have been accessed so I'm
gonna come around I keep that key page
three keep key page four but page one
has not been accessed since the lesson I
checked so then go ahead and throw that
away right it's an approximation to LRU
because it's essentially giving you the
same thing but instead of saying what's
the global timestamps of how how things
are accessed it's just a approximation
of whether was access since the last
time but I checked all right let's
metadata less overhead of maintaining
the link lists a lot of systems do this
because it's pretty easy
the problem with LRU and clock is that
they are susceptible to the to the issue
of what's called sequential flooding so
this is the examples I was showing
before where if we were doing a
sequential scan over it over over the
entire table the pages I just read in to
you know as I was scanning down is
actually the most useless page that I
actually need and now if I have a bunch
of other pages that the may being
accessed a lot by other queries the
semental scan is going to go through and
blow the air all those pages away
because it's gonna fetch in a bunch of
pages and then not need them anymore
right your since you're polluting the
buffer pool with pages that you need
once and then you don't need to ever
again
so in this case here LRU is actually the
exact opposite of what you want the
policy you really want is the most
recently used least in the case of the
structural scan right so to sort of
illustrate this I have one query when
students when shil skynyrd I have one
query a sort of a one query that's going
to access a single tuple all right and
say that's in page one I go ahead and
fetch it and make them into my buffer
pool and I'm done
page one it goes away now I started xre
query one goes away queries two starts
executing and it does the sequential
scan and again it's gonna fill up the
bumper pool with all the pages that it
reads so now I get to page three I need
to decide what page I want a victim
using LRU or clock it'll be page zero
because that's the one that was last the
least recently used I go ahead and evict
that but now another query comes along
but does the exact same thing that the
first guy did and it once
page page zero but that just got evicted
so it'll choose page one choose
something else so again I have to do an
additional read for something that I
just threw away so the ways to avoid
this is to sort of special case the
scruncho scan and recognize that it's
doing the scruncher scan and it's
unlikely to read that data again now
what other query comes along there's the
same special scan that's unavoidable
we'll have to go fetch those things in
but if I'm not doing these through if I
have a skewed workload where I'm always
trying to maybe access the first page or
for small number of pages I don't want
to evict those guys so three different
ways to handle this or through LRU Kay
private priorities and localization so
LRU K is it's basically like LRU but and
then rather than just keeping a single
timestamp of when the tuple was last
accessed I'm actually gonna keep a
history of all these accesses and then
from the history I can then compute the
intervals of the time from when the
tuple was accessed the first you know at
one point and then how long it took
before it was accessed again and now the
idea here is I can use this history to
estimate what's the likelihood that this
tuples can be accessed in the near
future and if that at that time
greater than all the other times then
that's the one I actually want a bit
right so my my example I showed in the
last slide the the the first tuple is
want all those query the first the first
and third query were accessing the first
page so if I recognize at a history of
that oh I'm gonna access this page over
and over again and I know how long in
between I'm gonna access those things
then that first page we actually would
be considered more important and should
stay in memory whereas the other ones
were used for the torrential scan and
it'll be a long time before they're
accessed again so I can go ahead and
indict those right and so the K and L
are UK basically says how much of a
history do you want to maintain right
because you could keep infinite history
of this but then that's again that's a
but the large storage overhead so
typically typically K equals one is it's
a very common approach for people to I
do this right and it works reasonably
well another way to handle this it's
called localization where you you rather
than having the the central scan access
the global buffer pool and pollute it
with the pages I want to read you can
actually just keep the pages that it
reads you can keep you can sort of
confine the query to a subset of the
buffer pool and don't let it pollute the
entire thing so my example I shared in
Postgres remember I showed that the
number of reads versus hits the number
of hits was only 32
this is because Postgres when a first
execute essential scan it only gives you
a 32-page local buffer for you to put
your essential scan pages in there and
that again that avoids polluting the
entire Buffalo space the the way some
systems in the case of Informix will
have a private memory that's not in the
buffer pool
I think post ghost actually backs them
with pages that are in the purple as
well right
and not one ways not better than other
the avoiding had to go the patient
obviously is faster because you don't
take latches but at a high level the how
it affects the proper pool is is it
roughly the same whether it's local or
global the last approach to use priority
hints and this is where you tell the
buffer pools something about the context
about how the pages were access are what
actually was inside of them so we saw a
little bit already when we talked about
having different buffer pool instances
that were allocated for either data
pages or index pages I began going more
fine-grained than that and say well how
you know it may be an index page or but
how is it actually gonna be accessed
again in the future right and then this
allows the poppable manager to then make
decisions about whether you know whether
one page should be evicted versus
another so let's say that we have an
index and gave me a we have index pages
for our nodes if we have a query that
wants to do an insert and say that we're
doing insert with a primary key that's
that's that's Auto incremented or it's
monotonically increasing so every single
tuple has ID one the next one has ID too
and so what we always count all right so
when we do these inserts what's going to
happen is we're gonna end up always
inserting to this side of the tree
because if it's based on ID then all the
new entries always end up on this side
so what we can do is we can may provide
hints to the buffer pool manager and say
we know that these pages are always the
ones that are going to access every time
I do an in new insert because they're
always on this side of the tree so they
should have higher priority then maybe
then some other pages in the index right
again this avoids having the problem up
again but since I always know I'm gonna
go down the side I don't have to a page
fetch every single time I do an insert
another thing you can do also too is say
I have queries that are just doing a
random key lookup anywhere in the tree
in that case maybe all the nodes will be
accessed uniformly but there's always me
one note or subset of nodes that I know
I'm always in access every single time I
do this lookup right and that's gonna be
the root cause because I can't get in
the index any other way so we
essentially tell the the buffer pool
manager that this page
don't even bother recording how often
its access I know that this thing should
always be in memory because every time I
do a lookup I'm always gonna go to it
then you can actually do even more
complicated things you can
that I have 5 indexes but everyone's
always going to this one so then this
one should have higher priority than all
the other indexes so this is what the
commercial systems do so the commercial
systems have all sorts of you know extra
hooks and extra information that divided
their bubble managers then allow them to
make better decisions than the open
source guys right this is sort what
separates the the sort of expensive
enterprise systems from the open source
ones open source ones like post custom
Icicle is still very good but the the
bubble manager policies in the
commercial ones are much more
sophisticated much more complex the next
thing I want to talk about that we've
sort of have been ignoring this entire
time is how do we deal with pages that
have been modified they've been dirty so
everything I'm sharing so far I just
assumed yeah I need to read a page I
need I need to make space I'll fix
another one I just throw it away right
that the page in the buffer pool that I
wanna replace I don't need to worry
about it about storing anything I just
drop it and go ahead and take its frame
but in real systems obviously we're
gonna update data means we're updating
data and in the pages and that means we
have to write them back out the disk so
there's this again this is another
example of the trade-offs we have to
make and our replacement policy because
the easiest thing to do would be just
only choose pages that are that are not
dirty and drop them right but then at
some point you're a bunch of pages that
are gonna be dirty you have to make a
decision or there may be pages like the
root of the index I'm gonna read all the
time and they never I may not actually
update it a lot but I I don't want to
drop it because I'm gonna have to go
through the index that way so there's
this trade-off between deciding do I
when I picked a page do I do the fast
thing this drop a page that's that's
clean or do I actually need to write
back a page that's dirty and be more
expensive but maybe a page that I know
I'm not gonna need in the future right
so cuz again if I choose a page that's
dirty
I have to write it out now there's a
whole other issue with the deal with
about logging and and making sure we
write pages at the right time but we'll
cover that later in the semester so one
way to preemptively take care of this
problem so that you know when we need to
evict a page we don't they medially
write it back is that we can do
background writing where we
periodically walk through the page table
find any dirty pages and they make a
decision about whether we want to go
ahead and write them out the disk ahead
of time so now when we do that we can
decide whether we want to evict it right
then and there or we keep it in memory
and we just flip it to be from the dirty
bit to be clean so that when the
eviction policy runs again it now has a
clean page that it knows it can throw
away all right so Postgres does this I
don't my sequel does this but a bunch of
the commercial systems do sort of the
same thing the issue we're going to talk
about later went about logging recovery
is that we can't write out a dirty page
to disk until the log that the law of
the corresponds to the change that was
made to that page is written out so disk
right and there's a whole process of
figuring out what pages are safe to
write based on what would you've written
to the log and of course there's this
contention issue now where I may be
trying to write data out there to the
log as fast as possible and I don't want
the background writer to interfere with
this but I want my background writer to
go ahead and write out 30 pages because
that'll free up slots or free up frames
in memory alright so how you balance all
these things is really tricky and
there's no there's no magical way to do
this people sort of have these default
settings and you can tune them a little
bit but it's it's it's very application
specific it's very difficult to get
right alright to finish up the last few
things to talk about or allocation
policies and the different types of
memory pools you can have so for
allocation policy is basically how do we
make decisions about how much memory to
give to different threads or different
different queries and do make decisions
about doing this for the entire system
or do we have localized policies that
say you know for this for this given
transaction the seventh query it's
allowed this amount of memory and we
don't care about anybody else so again
there's there's this kin trade-off of
trying to make decisions that will
maximize performance without having to
you know punish any one query that the
most and again there's no magic way to
do this it's sort of these things that
mean back into mind when you make
decisions about how you actually
implement your Buffalo manager
and the last piece to talk about is the
other memory pools that better running
inside the system so everything we
talked about here before today is just I
need to read a tuple it's not a page I
go bring that into my buffer pool but
there's all those other stuff we have to
maintain a memory that may or may not be
back by pages on disk that we now have
to consider as well so when we do query
processing we'll see this when we do
sorting and joins those things need the
memory obviously and we have to decide
where actually to put that memory so
some things will just be allocated on
the heap usually like in a memory pool
or an arena for a given query or thread
but other things you actually want to
back behind the buffer pool so that if
you need more memory to run your query
than it's actually available to you then
you can have them of a pool swap those
things out the disk so a lot of times
you'll see systems talk about you know I
run a query and I run out of memory it's
usually because the queries not backed
by the intermediate results are not
backed by the buffer pool and it can't
write those things out the disk so in
Postgres some things will be back by
disk like for doing cash joins but
there's other cases where if you we see
an exact query to show you right now
what we have ways of like concatenating
bunch of strings together and I'll just
run out of memory because it's not
backing this by the buffer pool it's
just stored in the heap so the the main
takeaway from this is that different
systems do different things sometimes
all these different types of memory
pools that you need will just be in the
heap and sometimes it actually backed by
the buffer pool ideally well there's no
one way that's better than another
because again if it's backed by the
buffer pool then you have to update a
page table we have to update all that
extra information if you just malloc on
the heap that's super fast but then you
can you don't have full control of the
amount of memory you may be actually be
using okay so the main takeaway from
this is that the database systems always
gonna do a much better job than the the
operating system for managing memory you
don't want to use em map you don't want
to rely on virtual memory you want to do
everything yourself because this doesn't
allow you to have to leverage the
information that you know about the
queries you're executing
to learn make better decisions on
on their policies about how you move
data back and forth okay and with the
exception of Postgres most data systems
do not rely on the file system cache
they do everything themselves
okay so given this lecture this is a
nice segue now into what the first touch
beers so the first project is you guys
got a bit of buffer pool alright so the
project is gonna be going out today I'll
post it online immediately after class
you're gonna have three parts you have
to build a hash table replacement policy
and the actual manager themselves so
this year all the products were based on
sequel light we looked at trying to make
use Postgres or it was just sort of more
complicated we do have enough time to do
this but basically C code lights gonna
be the front end to your to your the
database sort of engine you're building
as it what's called a virtual table so
you want to happen as your startup's
equal light and you say create me a
table using my cervix virtual table
extension and then any reads and writes
won't go to your to the engine that
you're building so for the first project
you don't actually need to use any
sequel light you don't need actually
even look at the internals on a single
light throughout the entire semester
where we're hiding all that from you you
just you work on your own C++ code base
so the project we do in two weeks on
September 26 you'll submit this on on
grade scope well again we'll turn all
this on later today at least get started
so the first task is that you have to
build an extendable hash table so I'll
explain what it what a symbol hash table
is next class but this is this is your
me end up using this as your page table
so it's a hash table that can grow so
that way as you insert new data and you
make new pages your hash table can grow
with it to keep track of these things so
for this you don't need to support
shrinking because that's actually harder
to do but you knew you need to support
growing and the basic extendable hash
table algorithm will do that for you
you're allowed to use some of the things
that are in the STL so this be all SS
C++ 11 so you can use sed hash as your
hash function you can use sed mutex
protect this right this needs to be
thread safe you can't just use a STD map
right use you have to build your own
hash map
once you try to do that later don't
don't do that
the next thing get a build is the
replacement policy so you don't have to
build LRU and you don't have to worry
about the weight way we sort of
extracted out the api's you know
actually actually to worry about whether
it's it's it's pinned not you just know
that these are the pages that that are
free and I have to make a decision about
which ones I actually want to evict
sometime this this part should be pretty
straightforward and then you put the the
LRU management policy that you
implemented plus your extendable hash
table and actually build now your own
buffer pool manager so we will take care
of reading the writing data from from
disk
I believe I'd you an API to say give me
this page from disk and knows where to
go get it Tom but you have to make a
copy of the page and you into your hash
map or your turn data structure and then
map any page IDs to it all right so the
tricky thing about this that that sort
of fowls up students is that you want to
make sure you get the operations correct
when you do pinning right if you know
you don't want to go look up it's not
there then try to pin something to take
out take a slot take a frame you have to
always set the pin first because another
third could come in and take take your
take your location yeah this part this I
mean this part is is this part is a more
complicated part of all this is sort of
putting everything together um but in it
we're only giving you two weeks because
it is actually not that bad in my
opinion so the way to get started is
that when we post it online today
download the source code will give you a
tarball
that'll have a bunch of stub files that
that you can run or you can implement
your actual code so the code when you
download it should be be able to you
should be able to compile it right you
should test that right away they'll
we've and we have API if you have
functions you actually have to implement
with documentation inside them the tests
will fail because obviously you haven't
written any of your code but you should
be able to compile it you should do that
right away and check your your
development environment so we've tested
all the andrew machines that are in
gates they everything should compile on
that there's no sort of
crazy dependencies to make this all work
we know it works on OSX we know it works
on Linux although I have a Windows
laptop I don't use it for anything other
than PowerPoint I don't know whether it
actually compiles on Windows 10 with the
Ubuntu package I think a student last
year got to work but I don't know what
you know I don't know what whether
worked out of the box if you can't if
you don't have access to a Linux machine
or machine you can actually use the
compiled in this email me we can give
you like a virtual machine image that
that if you want to run it that way but
everyone should access that should have
access to the engine machine if you're a
student here and it should work there
alright so the instructions will lay out
exactly what files you need to modify
you should not modify any other files in
the so the tarball we give you because
when when you run your tests right when
you upload the grade-school we're gonna
pick out those six files if we ask you
to modify and we're to overlay them into
our sort of clean cook codebase so if
you might there is something you have to
modify to make your thing to work that
aren't in the six files it will fail
when we actually run it because we're
not gonna copy those things at all right
the other thing to say - - is that the
four projects in the class are all
cumulative so you need to get this thing
working before you can do the subsequent
things so you can't build an index
unless you have a buffer pool and you
can't do control unless you have an
index so we would not be providing
solutions because of this in the case in
cases last year with some kids had
problems due to medical reasons we can
give you a you know an obfuscated turbo
obfuscated binary that'll implement some
of the files that you may be missing and
so that way you you can keep keep up
right but for the most part we set these
deadlines such that you you sort of keep
implementing things and you you'll have
enough time to do them in order to get
started on the next project okay so if
you have questions about about basic
things or the high level ideas or where
to find certain things in the code post
them on Piazza do not post on Piazza
like I get a segfault I don't understand
why all right we're not gonna help you
debug theirs we have tutorials online
that will send you guys how to use gdb
right how to do basic things with C
closed eleven but we're not gonna come
sit and look at your code with you okay
the last thing I'll say is - is that
please do not plagiarize we will run the
most detector
please also do not post your thing
publicly on github because again we
don't want other people just taking your
code right if you said a private repo if
you want and I realize a lot of you want
to be able to show your to your
employers you here's the project
projects I've done that actually doesn't
matter all right
they don't care good no cos because
you're all implementing the same thing
it's not only gonna have this magical
breakthrough right in the little code
you're writing for our projects okay so
don't personally because of github don't
cheat don't copy from each other if you
have questions email me and then next
hash tables okay put the butter cap on
Bushwick on the bow with a blow to the I
would indeed that's me rolling with one
parking south-central teeth and thank
eyes when I party by the 12-pack case of
a boy six-pack for the act against the
real I'm three please put your drinking
proper 12 ow
they say Filmation flat but sane eyes is
straight so it really don't matter