[Music]
maybe on the Jill's Nick I'm not there's
nothing so well do this
I decided person Piazza I canceled my
office hours if I pass out here while
I'm lecturing please don't steal my
wallet because they do that last year I
did not appreciate that okay I some
administrative things project two as
everyone is aware of is already out and
the first checkpoint is next week
someone posted in Piazza about making
checkpoint two tests available we'll try
to take care of that this week as well
they're also trying going to try to
expose the project one test cases so you
can go back and test yourself as well
ten you are we're doing that already or
now were you running the putter what
will take care of it the midterm exam
believe it or not it's October first we
got start with the midterm midterm exam
will be here in class on two weeks from
now on September except October 17th 3
an hour and 20 minute exam and it'll be
here and I'll cover everything up to
whatever the lecture before the that
Monday that money's lecture will not be
covered on the Wednesday exam would be
everything before then okay and I said
they just sent the email saying we have
our final exam on Sunday morning at 8:30
a.m.
yeah is what it is okay this week we
have another day visitor coming so these
guys are screamed again there another
GPU database out of Israel
so scream mat be and kinetic are so the
three most well-funded players in the
space so they're coming on again on
Thursday the pizza in CIC to talk about
their system okay now I'll post a
reminder on this on the awesome alright
so as I said last class now at the point
we want to start talking about actually
executing queries yeah we're building up
the layers in the system we know how to
store pages we had to have a bubble
manager we know how to build indexes on
top of that now we're gonna talk about
right how do we
run queries that's sort of the whole
point of a dative assessment right I
want to be able to put data in and then
ask questions about it so when we talked
about relational algebra before I sort
of said in the beginning that the way it
works is that the you give it sequel and
it converts the sequel into a query plan
comprised of relational operators and so
initially these relational operators
would just be logical equivalents to
what we know what we learned in
relational algebra like projections and
filters and and and and and joins and
now at this point in the lecture we now
we start talking about how to actually
to generate physical operators these
logical operators to actually execute
the thing that they represent right so
how are we actually going to execute a
join right what algorithm are we gonna
use so the way to sort of think about a
query plan is that it's just a tree and
that the the operators have these these
these edges that show you where the data
is flowing inside the tree inside the
query plan so at the very bottom here
for this particular queries you know
doing a select and joining a and B
together at the root of the tree we have
the scan operators the things that's
going to actually access the data
whether it's an index or a or the actual
heat with the table itself and then
there to feed that data up into the next
operator then computes whatever it wants
to do and then passes it on to the next
one
so what the waiting about this is when
I'm showing here and when I'm describing
is how it works at a logical level what
we'll see in today's class is physically
this is not always the way you're gonna
execute things right you may not be
passing a single tube will be baby
passing a block of tuples or the entire
output of an operator and then at the
very top is always going to be the root
root node and that sort of implicitly
has an arrow coming out of this and
that's the result that goes back to ever
ask for the query right so we can have
data up go from here to here here to
here and then this thing says all right
whoever invoked this query here's a
result and that can be you at the
terminal it could be an internal query
it could be a straw procedure right it
doesn't matter it just it goes out where
it needs to go so today's class we're
going to talk about three three
three three-point things so first off
with how the data systems going to
process the query plan how it's gonna
organize the execution of the operators
and move data around and then we'll talk
about the access methods of how the data
system will actually get to data whether
it's a sequential scan or a or index
scan and then we'll finish up talking
about how do you actually evaluate the
predicates in your where clause and
other expressions alright and again
we're just building one layer on top of
each other so a database system
processing model specifies especially
how the system is architected or
organized to to execute a query and at a
high level the approach is either a top
bound or top to bottom or bottom the top
approach right how you actually gonna
invoke these operators and this is sort
of at the engineering level or the
physical level of the system so the
processing model also specifies what
kind of data is gonna get moved from one
Operator to next is it a single tuple is
it a batch of tuple tuples or is it be
you know a single column or all the data
that the operator is ever going to look
at does it shove it up to the next guy
and the reason why there's different
these different processing models is
that as we'll talk about today there's
advantages and disadvantages for for
each of them so certain systems like you
want to focus on OLAP queries they'll do
it the you know usually the vector is a
batch model but if you're doing ot
workloads transactional workloads that
don't actually touch a lot of data per
operator then the the materialisation
model might be might be a better
approach so again there's trade-offs to
how we're going to engineer the system
to execute these queries and one
approach is better than another for
different classes of workloads so the
the jack-of-all-trades generic a basic
approach to processing queries it's
called the iterator model so the this is
another example where different people
call the same thing different names so I
think in the our textbook it calls it
the iterator model you might call it the
volcano model and volcano was a system
in the a very influential academic
system in the late 1980s early 1990s
that sort of described how to do the
iterator model in parallel
buddy I'll sometimes also called the
pipeline model I matter what it is it's
all essentially the same thing so the
basic idea is that the physical
operators in a query plan are each gonna
implement they are expose in their API
this next function and the idea is every
time you invoke next to own an operator
it's gonna give you back the next tuple
that it processed and then wants you to
process are you started think of a for
loop you iterate through and say next
next next on an operator and it's gonna
keep giving you out to pose one by one
then at some point when you run out of
tuples I can you scan the entire table
you reach the very end you just return
back a null say you asked me for more I
don't have any more so don't don't ask
me again so this is an example of what's
called top-down or top-to-bottom
processing because we're going to start
at the root and the routes gonna say all
right I need to do I'm gonna need to
compute whatever operator I represent I
need to compute it but I need to 'pls to
do this and I'm gonna have children in
my query plan and I go at invoke next on
my children and I ask them to give me
the next tuple that they have and then
they might not have anything so they
need to go down and you know in traverse
the tree to reach the very bottom and
you reach your access methods the things
are actually scanning scanning of the
data so let's look at a real high
example like this so normally I don't
like to show code in any lecture or talk
but for this I think it's sort of the
only way because it's sort of it'll
convey the the idea pretty clearly so
and this is that query we had before
we're doing a join on a and B and then
we have a simple filter where values
greater than 100 and so this would be
the the query plan that the data system
will generate for this sequel so a way
to think about this now in the iterator
model is that for each of these
operators you're gonna have essentially
a for loop and so the for loop is going
to iterate over its children and call
next on its children to get the next
tool that it wants to process so
starting at the root right so you sort
of organize these starting at the root
this guy is going to loop through it's
gonna have a single child so it's this
one here so it's on this join operator
so it calls next to the next operator
because it wants to you know wants to do
the projection but doesn't have any
tuples right it depends on its child so
calls next goes down to the next guy to
the join operator here same thing so
this has two children left and right so
it's going to call left on its child
which is then going to go down here and
now here this we're at this a here so
now we're just gonna scan over a and
there's there's this omit function that
basically says like a like a yield
clause in Python or iterator model in
Python where you just have a for loop
and you say all right someone's Avoca me
here's the next thing that you asked
before so it's gonna MIT that tuple here
and that gets shoved up to to the next
guy or up above it right and so the top
guy is going to do this operator to
doing the join on the left it's gonna
keep doing this until this thing comes
back says I don't have anything and then
it switches down to the next for loop on
its right child and same thing it's
gonna vote next on the right child and
this thing band invokes next on its
parent I'm sorry it's child
well now we're doing the scan on table B
alright so again it's going from the top
yes we called next next to the next
going down till we reach the very bottom
and at some point we'll reach something
that knows how to get tuples either from
an index or either from the table and it
shoves them up to the next operator the
next operator can do whatever processing
it wants to do and then maybe omit it
back up to the the next operator so the
key thing to point out here is play
reason why it's called the pipeline
approach is for this path in the query
plan we have a pipeline meaning we can
take one tuple and we can actually pass
it through a pipeline of multiple
operators before we have to go back and
get the next one so in this case here
we're doing the doing the loop over the
right child calls next we go down here
it's going to do an iteration over its
child calls next here and at this point
as we're scanning B it emits a tuple and
then immediately we can evaluate the
predicate and if it passes then we call
a bit and then it gets passed up here
so we don't have a context wishing it's
not the right word but get the basic
idea we're not switching to it the next
tuple when we get the tuple here we do
whatever processing we need to do on it
then pass it up to the next guy this is
why this approach is widely used in disk
based systems because if I bring I have
a tuple in memory I want to do as much
work as I can while it's in memory
before I go back and get the next one
because I may have not I may not have
enough memory to put mine to all my
intermediate results in memory and I may
have to spill to disk so the worst case
scenario would be I I need a tuple I
fetch it from disk I made it up here and
then I process it and then before I pass
it up here I go back and get the next
one but now at all in that space that's
the store the tuple that just I just got
so that gets swapped out the disk and
now I fetch another page to get the next
one but then when now when I get back up
here I got to go back to the tears can
get all the other ones I get all the
ones that pass I had him in memory here
but then I swapped them out so the
pipeline approach again try to do as
much work on a single tuple for as long
as you can while it's in memory so they
said this this approach is the most
widely used processing model in almost
every single database system so this is
a small smattering of systems that are
out there it's pretty much everyone
these are the ones I can verify based on
the documentation and what and what I
know about how they work so again the
idea is to generate query plans that can
allow you to have these long pipelines
or keeping things in memory as much as
possible but at some point you hit what
are called pipeline breakers where you
can't keep going up the query plan with
a tuple you're processing you have to go
back and get more so these would be any
time you need to get see all the data on
one side of the tree before you can go
down through the next one so the most
obvious one is a joined right so this
case here I need to see all the tuples
from a but and do my and do my bill my
hash table before I can put anything up
to here right and I need to do the join
here before after in this case you have
to do the join you'd match you can push
it up here but this side of the tree you
have to see everything before you can go
down the other side
so right as I said joins sub-queries
order by these are things going where
you have to see everything before you
can make a final decision of what you're
going to spit out to to your parent the
other nice thing about this is that it
makes it really easy to use limits and
control the size of your output because
now you'll all you have to do is as you
call if I call next and I get you know
only 110 tuples if I call next and I get
10 to poles I'm done right I can just
stop at the at the you know whatever
whatever point of the tree that says all
right I know there's a limit here I
don't have to worry about you know
processing more data than I actually
need we'll see this later in a few weeks
when we talk about parallelization but
this approach is also very easy to
paralyze as well and that's what the
volcano model was originally briefly
proposed a way to have these little next
guys run in separate threads and then
coalesce the results at some later point
in the tree but we'll worry about that
later
all right the next processing model is
called the materialization model and
this is sort of a bottom-up approach
where instead of having this next
function that a parent calls on child
you start at the bottom and you have the
operators do whatever it is computation
they want to do on the data that they're
reading and only when they when they
have everything done they've computed
the entire answer that they're going to
ever answer you know that they want to
generate then you show up data to to the
next operator and you never go back and
invoke that operator again because at
that point it's it's it's done all the
work that it needs to do all right so
we'll see this in the next slide the
tricky thing about this as I said before
in the iterator model it's really good
to do it's really easy to do limits
because you just stop calling next when
you got all the data that you need in
this case here you main the limit may be
in the upper parts of the tree and you
may not know that oh I'm gonna scan a
billion two poles but I only really need
10 so if you materialize the all the
entire billion tubos and shove that up
the tree you may not know until much
later that oh I had a limit that said
I'll need ten of them
so the way to get around this is to just
embed logic in these lower operators to
say do a scam but only give me ten
things I start inlining one operators
have another all right so again same
query we had before and now it's
different is that inside of our the
inside of each operator implementation
now we have these little output buffers
and what will happen is we say we start
at the very bottom here on the scan on a
we're just going to scan through it look
at every single tuple and just put it in
our output buffer and then when we're
done we we shove it up to the - to the
our parent so then we come back down
here and do the same thing on B scan
through all that materialize the entire
output into our output buffer shove that
into three which then does the predicate
the predicate valuation shove it up into
four what we then finally do the join
all right
so right and he goes all the top so I
started already say this in the
beginning but does this just make sure
you understand what's going on what kind
of work would this be bad for this
approach oh-ohlow TP or OLAP
transactional or analytical what did the
queries look like in transactional
workloads yeah like so transaction
workloads would be like reading a single
tuple you'll all go to Amazon right it's
Andy's account Amazon you just look at
that it's like no one to boy than all my
orders right or if I put something my
card I'm adding one record into my cart
I see you're not touching a lot of data
forever query and analytical were close
I want to do things like compute the
average you know stock price of
Microsoft over a you know 10 week window
or something like that so I'm scanning a
lots of data and I have to move a lot of
data from one Operator to the next so
the materialization approach is better
for transactional workloads because
they're not touching a lot of data so
the size your output buffer going from
one operated to the next is going to be
small
in the case of oh that queries its
unless you try to push as much logics
you pin down into the lower parts of the
plan you're gonna end up moving more
data than maybe you need to all right
so volt BB does this which is again both
of you is the academic predecessor or
sorry
both the iver the system code aged or a
shirt uses the materialization model
both DB is the commercial version of
each door and as far as I can know from
least a year to or less than I looked
they still do it the same way that we
did it originally and when we wrote the
system in the university of doing the
materialization model because this is
the right way to do this in a teepee
environment because when everything is
in memory calling Nexus actually becomes
expensive and so you want to avoid that
as much as possible
Monay DB is an academic OLAP system but
they still use materialization model I
haven't looked at the doc petition to
see why it high-rise was another
academic OLAP system that yeah I think
they were doing materialization model
but then they threw away all the code
and started rewriting it but I haven't
looked to see what they're actually
doing so you sort of see this trade-off
between like how much data I want to
move around and how much overhead I have
of calling next and and you're going
from top top-down versus the bottom-up
the last model we're talk about it's
vectorization model is a sort of a
hybrid of the two
so like the iterator model we're still
gonna have an X function so we're
calling next next snacks going down the
tree but instead of passing a single
tuple in our emit function we're
actually gonna pass a vector tuples sort
think of this like a mini batch as we go
along and then what's going to happen is
the internal loop was going to know how
to process this mini batch in an
efficient manner you know using
vectorization or cindy or things like
that all right so let's let's see what
it looks like so now what I've done is
it looks it looks sort of likely to be
the materialization model sorry it's a
combination materialization model and
the iterator model I now have my output
buffers but inside my output buffers I I
check to see whether
I've reached a certain when its region a
certain size that usually depends on
what the harbor looks like I then
emitted up to whoever needs it and
implicitly when I call it he wrote my
output buffers I'm clearing it out so
the next time I come back in the loop I
start with a fresh step all right and
goes a like this so again this approach
is idea for OLAP queries it sort of
seems obvious but the first systems that
really didn't start end up doing it
until much later and like late 2000s
vector wise are sort of the first one
this is the approach that we were
originally doing in peloton I we're
still working in the new ones and I'm
not sure what we're doing
presto does this with Facebook and then
sequel server Oracle and IBM all have
these sort of quick column base or
vectorized based accelerators for in
memory data sets and they all use the
vectors in vector as approach okay yes
this one here there for disk based
systems this is probably the best for a
memory system that will cover that next
semester there's another approach but
this is this is probably good for this
in this common one okay again this is
just a summary of different models we
talked about by iterative volcano is
basically sort of this general approach
it you know people use 400 to me and
OLAP together vectorize is a top-down
approach and this is good for OLAP
queries and then virtualization is is a
bottom-up approach that's good for OTP
queries okay all right so as I said
before the inner query plan the the
nodes of the bottom of the query plan
the operative the bottom are access
methods these are the ways that the
system is going to actually access data
that's stored in their table so there's
not really a existing there's no
equivalent in the relational algebra for
an access method right it's just sort of
something you have to do right it's a
physical thing in order to get data out
of a tuple or data out of a
of a index so at a high level there's
basically two types of exxon methods you
can have you can have a sequential scan
and you can have an index scan and then
there are ways to combine multiple
indexes we'll talk about in a second and
these are called multi index access
methods so all opal has a bunch of
different names for the access methods
there's like heaps can row ID scan but
to best my knowledge these are all just
gonna be the same thing right it's
either one or the other all right so
again we're talking about me you guys
here down here so special scan is it's
pretty straightforward to understand
you're basically going to iterate over
every single page in a table
you're gonna retrieve it from the buffer
pool and then your Gator ate over that
table to see whether it you should
include it in your output doesn't Matt
like this doesn't matter whether using a
mat realization montt processing model
or or volcano it's it's gonna be the
same approach and so internally Dave
system's going to maintain a cursor that
tracks the last page lot that examines
so that if you're doing this in a
iterative manner you know what you
picked and you pick up pick up where you
left off all right so yeah I'm not
feeling so great here all right kids
keeping on I mean I may I may have to
shut it off but let's get through this
real quick all right so sequential scans
in general this is always the worst
thing you want to do - wait execute
we're ease right because it's it's the
slowest thing you look at every single
tuple and every single page but there
are some optimizations we can do to
speed this up we've already talked about
prefetching before we'll talk about
parallelization later we talked about
buffer pool bypass but I want to cover
these three things here so Maps
limitation keep clustering so zoom maps
are basically a pre aggregated
pre-computer aggregations I'm going to
maintain for theatrics in a single page
and the idea is that when a zone map
versus side so when a query one-way data
stem says I want actually to query on a
on a page it has to check
I have to see whether she'd even bother
accessing that page so the idea here is
we have our original data we have this
column here a bunch of values so in our
zone map we can process we can
pre-compute some aggregations like the
min max average standard things like
that so when our query comes along we
don't find this case here what value
greater than 600 we could look in the
map and say well we know for this page
there's no value greater than 400 so we
don't need to look at it yeah guys I am
NOT very good I think I'm gonna pass out
so we're stopped okay
sorry let's just say that I haven't been
that sick since I ate at Taco Bell when
I was in high school so I've been
sleeping the last 48 hours but now I'm
fine that's what the stomach flu is it
comes and goes right so I like how all a
professor how much I love the flu shot
and that'll protect you from you know
terrible diarrhea okay so we're gonna
pick up where we left off last time
we'll go a little quickly so that we can
get into what we should have talked
about today so again reminder project
project to checkpoint 1 is due on Monday
midterm exam will be on the 17th
I'll send update about that and there'll
be a review session the day before that
but for that class and then tomorrow the
scream Divi guys are coming to give a
talk in the CIC so where we left off
before Emma's passed out was that we
were talking about processing models and
we said these are the different ways we
can we can organize or architect the
system to read tuples and and process
the query right we said that the volcano
model or the iterator model was the most
common approach most data systems use
this where you have this next function
you call next X and X going down and you
grab single tuples at a time from your
access methods at the bottom then we
said that the alternatives would be the
vectorize approach where it looks like
the volcano model instead of getting a
single tuple you get a batch or vector
tuples and this is better for OLAP
queries can be vectorized operations on
batches of queries and then the other
approach was the materialization model
where said of going from the top going
down you start with the bottom go up and
you each operator shoves up the entire
output or all the tuples that it wants
to that it processed into its next
operator and you don't go into the next
one to the one below it finishes
right so this is all bit of a blur so
we'll just go to this from the very
beginning was the active methods so yeah
cthe methods are how we're actually
going to access the data in our database
right it's it's the bottom part of the
query plan right there's no there's no
equivalent operator for an access method
in the relational algebra because
relational algebra game was just an
abstraction over how we would execute
queries so now we need to talk about how
do we actually implement these access
methods how do you actually get the data
we need from from our database in order
to pass them up into that to our query
plan and do additional operations on
them so at a high level there's only
really two approaches you had either do
an index scan or your sequential scan
right there's really the only way two
ways you can actually get data there's
things like materialized views but those
are usually stored it's just tables if
you use multiple indexes that's still in
index again so at a high level there's
essentially two classes of approaches
but we'll look at also what happens when
you have multiple indexes or what
Postgres calls a bitmap scan because
this is kind of confusing when you look
at explain you look at the query plan
and Postgres says oh I'm doing a bit mad
scan you may not know exactly what that
is it's essentially is doing an index
scan so look at look at both these and
what optimizations we can apply for each
of them so as we said many times about
the semester the sequential scan is the
fallback option for a database system we
don't have an index or how many fancy
thing we can do to actually derive the
answer we always can just scan the
underlying tables and it's essentially
just nested for-loops
for every single page in our triple
we're gonna then iterate over to see
every single to point each page and just
do whatever it is that what we need to
do right we can compute an aggregation
apply a predicate do filtering right
we're just going over it one by one
so how those are typically implemented
is that the especially in a volcano
model or iterate a model is that the
database system is going to maintain a
internal cursor for your query that just
keeps track of where did I leave off in
the scan so if you're familiar with
writing iterators and python you have
that yield function right that's just
syntactic sugar underneath the covers
Python is maintaining its own iterator
sorry its own cursor
to know that when you go and ask for the
next thing it knows how to jump where it
left off and it's in this sequential
scam so we're gonna do this on a per
query basis right and in the
materialization model we don't like to
do this because we're just going to read
everything and shove it up but if you're
doing the vectorize or the volcano model
when you call next and omit the tuple
back up to you when you call next again
you need to know where you left off in
the case of scrunch a can it's just page
ID and all set so there's not really any
magical way we can make sequential scans
run faster right because again it's oh
it's gonna be bound by how fast we can
read pages from disk right we if we need
to read a thousand pages we have to read
a thousand pages but there are some
optimizations we can do to try to
eliminate or reduce the number of pages
we have to read to to minimize that the
amount I oh we have to do so we've
already talked about prefetching right
prefetching was a it was a way to know
I'm gonna scan ahead a bunch of pages so
let me go ahead and fetch a bunch of
them in order bring them to my buffer
pools so that one actually need them
they're there for me we'll talk about
how to do parallel special scans and a
few more lectures when we talk about
parallel query execution and then we
also talked about the buffer pool bypass
in Informix and Postgres where instead
of polluting the your buffer pool with
the the pages you're reading during
scheduled scan you just maintain a
little side buffer for your query that's
just you know they only require uses and
that way you don't you don't have
sequential flooding you're not you know
you're not blowing away all the the
locality information you have in your
cache so I said one I'll talk about
these three other optimizations we can
do again these are things that we can
apply to potentially make the amount of
work that they do during sweat your
scans be less so zone maps are a way to
pre-compute aggregations on individual
pages and then use those precompute
aggregations to know what pages you can
skip during a cilantro scan alright so
the way to think about this is I have a
bunch of pages and I have a bunch coms
in those pages and I'm gonna go ahead
and pre compute the standard a Gregorian
as we have in the sequel standard you
know count min max some average things
like that and we restore this zone map
in a separate page different than from
the original data page
and the zone map itself is gonna be
pretty small so we can store multiple
the zone maps for multiple pages in a
single page and so what happened is now
if we come along with a sequential scan
operator like this select start from
table where value is greater than 600 if
we had to do if we didn't have a zone
map you'd have to go fetch the page and
just scan in linearly inside that page
to see whether we have any values that
match this with the zone map instead we
can examine the predicate and say well
it's looking for values that are greater
than 600 in my zone map I know the max
value for this column here is 400 so
there's never going to be a tuple that
is that will match my predicate so
therefore I don't need to bother looking
at this page I just go ahead and to skip
it and again the idea is that the data
pages when we must will be much larger
than the zone map pages so for a single
page fetch to go get a zone map like
that main encompass or cover may be
dozens of pages and I can use that to
figure out which ones actually need to
go look at so this idea is is is not new
it's been around for a while Oracle
calls it zone maps and for better or
worse you know in the database community
when you say zone map we just mean the
Oracle you know brand name of it but
it's not specific to Oracle it's used in
a bunch of different systems so IBM has
it in db2 for blue cloud era uses this
in Impala
Netezza has this Vertica it's in the
park cave file format for cloud systems
we'll talk about later in the semester
so this approach is used all over the
place mem sequel has this sometimes the
called pre computed aggregates but he's
a zone maps they essentially mean mean
the same thing the next thing we can do
is called late materialization for
columnstore systems Samara will
columnstore systems I said that in
general you can think of every single
column or attribute for a table will be
stored in pages by themselves and so as
I'm processing the query I only fetch
the pages that have the columns that
actually need to in order to process the
query so in late materialization the
idea is is sort of a logical extension
to this is that as I'm going up the tree
query plan I only go fetch the pages
that I need for that particular operator
I don't try to stitch the entire tuple
back together alright so say that we
have it query like this select average
and sieve and food joining them bar and
then we have our joint predicate and
then a where clause or a is greater than
hundred so say our query pan looks like
this and we're going to focus on the
right side of the tree the scan on foo
so as we're doing this crunch we'll scan
on foo and we want to apply our
predicate on a we know that the only
thing at this point to evaluate that
predicate is just a so the only column
we need to go read you know in pages we
need to go read this for the attribute a
and then when we're done scanning we
actually can throw away any values of a
that we brought into memory and only
pass up offsets because we know at this
point in the query plan because we know
what the query plan is because this
sequel is declarative we know that
there's no other point up in this tree
where we're ever gonna have to look at a
again so we don't even need to pass it
around we can just throw it away and
just pass up our offsets same thing when
we go up here and do our join we only
look at B or just the subset of B that
match our offsets Pass then more offsets
up to the aggregation and now at this
point we have to materialize right we
can't pass back the user offsets because
that's an internal representation that
our ternal you know marker that means
nothing to the outside world so at this
point we do material materialized the
tuple meaning me go grab for the offsets
we grab the data that it actually needs
so this is useful in some cases where
the offset to be much smaller than the
actual tuples themselves the values of
people's themselves let's say I had you
know C was a was a varchar' of 100 and
so that would be you know 100 characters
I would have to pass round from one
operator to the next but would late
materialisation I guess passed around a
64-bit integer per tuple then only when
I had to go get the give his alt back to
the user then I go fetch the page as I
need for C right so again it's sort of
this is you can do this in a
decomposition storage model or the
column store system because the columns
are broken off you couldn't do this in a
easily in a in a and a row store because
when
go fetch the tuple you're going
impression the the all the rows for it
alright so the last optimization is
called heap clustering so we've sort of
already talked about this before and we
talked about index organized tables and
the idea is that we're gonna have an
index that's gonna tell us how we should
store tuples in our pages right so say
we have our index like this we have a
short direction right calling along the
leaf nodes we're going from left to
right say it's going in the sending
order and then our pointers now from the
index to our tuples and inside our pages
what we sort it in that order right so
now that means that for some cases
instead of you may be doing a leaf node
scan along here and going fetching and
fetching the pages one by one I can
maybe just jump to one location and just
fetch the table pages because I know
they're gonna be in the order that I
want so as I said so we talked about
this before we said that some database
systems like my sequel for example don't
actually have separate table pages they
store the tuples themselves inside the
leaf pages of the index right so that
essentially you get a clustering index
for free in other systems like in my
sequel or sorry in sequel server and
oracle you can tell it that you want
this index to be a clustering index and
it'll maintain the the tuples sorted in
the pages like this in systems like
Postgres and you can declare that you
want a clustering index so they have a
cluster command and it'll do this
sorting for you but it doesn't actually
maintain it so every single time you
update the table after you run cluster
it's not going to guarantee that they're
gonna be in sorted order this will make
more sense when we talk about how they
do could hurt your control or mostly
versioning but in general they're not
doing it because that'd be extra work
for it's like something like my sequel
because the tuples are started you know
in the pages themselves the leaf pages
then they get it for free so again this
allows you to do some things like jump
ahead to where you think the tuple you
actually need will be instead of having
to look at more more pages alright so
the other access method is to do index
scan and we talked about this before we
talked about how to in the case of look
at covering index we can process the
entire query just on
what actually being stored in the index
nina games basically it's gonna help us
to figure out what pages we've have to
go read in order to process the query
and that's a point again having to do a
sequential scan so the question of what
index to pick depends on a lot of
different things
depends on what attributes are in the
index and the different indexes that you
have available to you depends on what
athlete you're actually referencing in
your query in the where clause or other
parts of the query depends on the the
value domain of the index like if I have
a index on whether you know a student is
their gender is male female right that's
not gonna be that useful because it's
gonna be 50/50 mostly depends on how the
the with the where clause looks like you
have conjunctions or disjunction ands or
ORS and then depends on whether they're
unique keys or non unique keys so
basically what happens is you write your
select Cueva select statement in in
sequel and it's up to the data system
job to figure out which index you want
to use potentially for it index scan so
that particular question we're gonna
focus on later in lecture 17 after the
midterm and when we talk about query
optimization this is a pretty hard
problem and there's a lot of literature
on how to do these kind of things but
for our purposes we'll look at a high
level and then we'll see what are the
different design decisions or
implementation decisions we can have
actually how to execute a query for an
index scan based on these these
different questions so let's look a
little bit simple examples so say we
have a single table of students and we
have a hundred tuples and we have two
indexes we have one index on the
students age and one index on the
students department and we're gonna run
this query here select star from
students where age is less than thirty
department equals CS and the country
equals us so we don't have an index on
the country just Department in age so
the first scenario would be there are 99
people in the table that under the age
of 30 which is usually accurate for
universities but then there's only only
two people in the CS department so which
of these two indexes would we actually
want to pick okay pick one right so we
have an index on age but then there's 99
people out of 100 under age of 30 and
we're looking for students under age of
30 so the index can be really helpful
there
no cuz it's gonna pack 99% of them
anyway right and then we have only chill
MCS Department out of 100 so in that
case here we had index on department
alright we can jump exactly to the two
tuples that we had that we want alright
so the idea here is that we want to pick
indexes that are gonna be the most
selective for us that's gonna filter out
the most things as soon as possible it's
the lowest portion in the query plan
because the idea is we want to minimize
the amount of data we have to transfer
it from one operator to the next that's
sort of what late materialization was
trying to do minimize how much data you
move around and the idea here is again
to filter out things as soon as possible
I picking the index that's the most
selective right if you can reverse this
say there's not a 9 people in the CS
department but only two people under age
of 30 in this case here we want to pick
the index on age because again that'll
find the two people that we want right
away so there's nothing really special
index can write you you you know what
the predicate is in your where clause
you know what attributes are in your
index and you follow it you follow that
you know the tree or do a hash lookup
and you find the thing you're looking
for and then you just pass them up to
the next operator alright there's really
nothing interesting there it's pretty
straightforward
where things get interesting is when you
actually use multiple indexes together
so these are called the multi index
scans Postgres again calls in the bitmap
scans and the idea here is that say the
data citizen recognizes oh for my
particular query on this table I have
two indexes that both look pretty good
and I and instead of picking one versus
another actually want to use both them
and then combine numbers there their
results set together and use that as as
as the you know the result set for my
operator so the idea here is that we'll
take all the indexes we want to use and
we compute sets of record IDs that match
the particular predicate we're
evaluating on our index and then we're
gonna combine together the the records
record ID sets from the different
indexes either using a union or
intersection intersection if it's an and
Union if it's an or and then for all
those records that come out of the the
matching set we then go to our look
optic applying the original two tuples
in the pages and
pass them up to to the next operator in
the tree so we go back to our example
here again we have two indexes on age
and Department so what we'll do is we
first retrieve all the record IDs in the
age index that match age less than 30
and then we'll retrieve all the
recognize that match Department equals
to yes in the second index take the
intersection of the two of them right
because it's a it's a it's an Ann clause
in our in our predicate and then fetch
booze tuples then we go check now to see
where the country is is us visually it
looks like this right so again we do I
look up on age less than 30 in that
first index we get the set of record I
used to match that do a lookup on the
department index get a set of all those
record IDs and now we just take the
intersection of the two of them and
that's that's the ones we know match age
less than 30 and Department equals CS so
you can implement this with a bitmap if
the Postgres does you can use a bloom
filter you can use hash sets hash tables
all right it doesn't actually matter
Long's you have set membership and a way
to combine them together right all right
so the one widgets were probably gonna
have and we'll see this come up again
and we talked about sorting is that the
if an index is not ordered on the key
that we want to the intercept is not
ordered on the key that we want to do
our lookup on then we may end up with a
really inefficient index scan and the
may actually been better if we don't
just a straight sequential scan all
right so then here's our index it's say
the it's the scan Direction is in this
this way based on some key and now if we
follow along the leaf nodes and start
reading reading the pic the tuples are
you know Phung the pointers down to our
pages we'll see that they're going all
over the place right this is an
uncluttered index the index is just
pointing to where those tuples are it's
not saying anything how it's physically
sorted on the actual table pages so now
if we do a if we follow along the leaf
nodes and do our special scan or indexed
and that way well end up happening is
that we're gonna basically thrashing our
buffer pool because we're fetching pages
in
and then throwing them away immediately
to go fetch another page so say a really
simple example is I only have space for
one page and my buffer pool so if I do
my scan for all these pages following
along belief note orders then what will
happen is that all these different the
different boxes represent every single
time I had to go fetch a page right
because I'm not reading mindful of the
locality of where the data is actually
being stored
I'm just blindly saying oh I want page
102 let me go get it
all right now I need page 103 why they
take one or two output 103 n so again so
I'm just ping-pong game pages in and out
and that's gonna make things go really
slow so a simple optimization is that
just do the index scan first don't
actually fetch any tuples just figure
out what are all the pages on my
actually gonna need to access the
records I need to access and then you
sort those those tuples the record IDs
based on the page ID so now you go then
and say all right well alright I'll do
all the fet I'll fetch page 101 first do
all the reads I need for that then pet
page 102 and do all the reads for that
and I never go back to page 101 so what
went from you know maybe over over 10
page reads append ten page i/os before
we did the sorting now ends up going to
be to four which is the bare minimum we
actually need to exit the scan so even
though you have an index doesn't mean
everything's gonna go super fast for you
right you wanna be a little bit smarter
about how you your schedule will be the
disk i/o operations you want to do again
there's another example of the beauty of
the relational model because we don't
care that the output is not in the order
that you expect it right unless you tell
us we want to order by it's gonna come
out and you order it at once so if we
just took your query and executed almost
exactly how you expressed it we would
end up maybe in this situation here and
that would be slow we can be a bit
smarter and say all right well if I sort
things ahead of time then I'll basically
have sequential access and I'll have a
good locality because I'm reusing every
page every page I read in I'm reading as
much data as I can out of it before I
move on to the next page so this is this
is a standard technique that a lot of
systems use all right so the last thing
I want to talk about is how do we
actually value
predicates so we have these where
clauses we have these expressions how
these actually represent and how we
actually implement them so the way to
think about it as we talked about before
the the query plant itself is a tree and
then inside each operator in our tree we
can have another another tree called the
expression tree and this represents you
know the where clause or whatever
expression we have for that particular
operator so the nodes and the tree are
gonna represent all the different types
of expressions you can have comparisons
arithmetic expressions conjunctions
disjunction it's things like that and it
says you just evaluate them and they
return you know true or whatever the
type of value they want to return and
then you use that to figure out whether
you know tube will match the predicate
or what's the output you want for that
for that tube or in the query so this
take our simple query like this and our
where clause we have a ID equals B ID
and B values greater than 100 so we
would represent that in a tree like this
so at the root we have the conjunction
clause and that returns true or false
and then on one side we have the equal
sign and when other side we have the
greater than sign all right at a high
level this is how every David Simms
going to represent these expressions
let's see how actually how you how you
evaluate them so say we have our we have
a query like this and it's a prepared
statement so we have a we have a clause
with a where clause with a placeholder
for a value at run time so as we're
doing our mental scan or index scan for
every single tube with that that we're
gonna evaluate this expression on we
would maintain some extra qge in context
about what we're examining at that point
in time so say I have a thousand tuples
and for every single tuple I'm gonna
build this execution context and then
traverse the tree to see whether its
value is to true or not so at the top
here you see that we have the the
current tuple that we're looking at in
our scan the query parameters that are
get passed in at runtime to fill that
value in and then the schema for the
tuple that that we're evaluating here
because we need to know in the
expression tree it'll say I want to look
at attribute you know Val you know where
that is in the actual tuple so we do
basically just walk to this tree in a
breadth-first manner all right so we
stirrers talk about you know at the root
is equal sign we go down the left it
says attribute value so we
this is a reference to the for the
current tuple what actually we want you
want value so we didn't look up in the
table schema and say well what offset
and the tuple is corresponds to the name
value and then we look in the current
table
the current tuple that we're looking at
and we get the value that we 1/1000
traverse down the other side we have the
parameter expression that tells us we
want 999 because we want that we want
the first one in our query parameters we
go to constant it's just just one so
there's a plus one and then everything
gets fed up now into the tree until this
thing produces you know true or false
and if it's true if it's true then we
know what our tuple you're examining
satisfied our predicate and we can
produce it in our and our need immediate
output alright pretty straightforward so
the what I'll say is that this is this
primitive as I said it's pretty much how
everyone does it this is actually a slow
way to do it
and the current trend which we'll cover
in the advanced class is actually using
cogeneration or just a time compilation
is instead of traversing this tree we're
actually generate a program to compile
this and run this exactly machine code
so instead of saying you know does
something equal 99 plus 1 I'll just you
know in traverse that treated generate
that value I'll just generate machine
code that does the exact same thing and
it's way faster there's announcement I
think Postgres just added this and
posted us 11 which comes out later this
year but a lot of major commercial
systems do this alright so the main
takeaway from all this is that the same
query plan could be actuated in much
different ways and one approach versus
another will will have different
advantages or disadvantages based on
what kind of workload you're trying to
turn the deal with and it and for at
least most systems they're going to try
to use index scan as much as possible
because it always going to be faster now
there are some systems like Vertica for
example they have no indexes at all
won'ting lets you declare them but they
pre sort everything which is essentially
almost the same thing as I as an index
and then in the expression tree just and
just to show you that what what they
look like to understand how these where
clauses are gonna get evaluated the way
I'm showing you here is super flexible
you can have any kind of expression you
would want could be represented in these
trees but it's gonna be slow the way if
you traverse it manually
okay so any questions about this des I
make a mess unless I can do it like a
Geo I give you put the G to the B to the
T comes I play the game wears on the
cuffs is because I put the bus a cap on
the road by the 12-pack eight seven four
six pack for the egg gets the Real ID
replete with your drinking proper 12 ow
they say bill makes your flat butts a
nice is straight so it really don't
matter