[Music]
they'd be on the Jill's Nick okay so
real quick before we dive into the
material just again the reminders for
administrative things right homework one
is due tonight at midnight and then if
you if you're not gonna make tonight's
deadline check the syllabus all right
for both projects and homeworks you're
given for slip days so if you're one
minute over or whatever great scope says
is midnight then it's considered late
and then you're docked one one of those
four missed days the second announcement
is that in class on Wednesday I will be
releasing and presenting to you guys the
the first project and we'll spend a
little time sort out lying pallid before
projects that you're gonna be working on
fit together and how it's related to the
discussions we're having in the lecture
so far and then the last thing I want to
talk about is sort of a confession and
that is to say that I sort of lied at
the beginning the semester and I said
that the only two things I care about
are my wife and databases I really
really love vaccines
I've even got mine already today uh my
shirt says vaccinate kids so everyone
should go get the flu vaccines are free
again I've realized some people medical
conditions and you can't right but
there's no excuse if you're healthy you
should be getting a flu vaccine to give
you an idea how obsessed I am about
vaccines two years ago I try to get them
to set up the flu vaccine center or the
the table at the cs department gates
they wouldn't do that and then my first
year I try to give extra credit if you
got the flu vaccine if you had a selfie
of like them sticking the thing in your
arm apparently that's illegal and I
couldn't do that so then last year we
try to buy some illegal flu vaccine from
Mexico and started giving them out the
students apparently that's illegal too
but so I went through all this effort to
try to get vaccines it's super easy you
can make appointments or go whenever
they have the free clinics okay okay
all right so let's jump into databases
now my second love of my life okay so
there were some questions at the end of
last class that people were started
grappling with trying to understand
where I was going with you know this
this database storage the file level and
breaking things up the pages right and
they were trying to understand what's
the big picture of what I'm trying to
talk about here and how's this gonna fit
into the things that we talked about
talked about in in subsequent lectures
so everyone's been a little bit time
talking about sort of going over again
what I mean by a disk oriented database
system architecture and then I'll show
sort of an overview of what the sort of
the the high level semantics of the
system we're trying to build and why the
various things we've talked about so far
or how they fit into this this overall
system so I said this course is about
disk oriented database management
systems and the definition I gave for
disk oriented was a database management
system where the Edit the architecture
is predicated on the assumption that the
primary search location of the database
is on disk and so that means that any
time a query needs to read something I
read read a tuple and we've already
talked about how two balls are starting
pages and pages of shortened files right
whenever needs to read one of these
tuples it's going to assume that it's
not in memory and therefore it's gonna
go out the disk to get it copy it into
memory and then it can do whatever it is
that it wants to do on it and the reason
why that we're saying this is just going
to is its again is this major assumption
because a lot of things that we're going
to talk about as we go along will see
that we have to add certain protection
mechanisms or certain functionalities in
the components of the database minute
system just because anytime we go read
something it may actually not actually
be in memory right we'll see this when
we talk about concurrency control
allowing multiple queries or
transactions to run at the same time and
any given time I could read something
and it's not memory I'm gonna stall
because I have to go to disk and get it
and meanwhile all the queries are gonna
start running at the same time because
I'm running and therefore the database
management system needs to protect the
data so that when I say protection I
mean
sort of at a logical level from other
queries doing the same thing trying to
operate on the same date at the same
time right and get this will make more
sense when we talked about concurrent
whole unlocking and latching and other
things like that but that's the
high-level idea of what we're trying to
do here remember since you're trying to
manage the movement of data back and
forth to be disk in the memory so that
we can handle databases that are larger
than the total amount of memory that we
have so that is that clear for everyone
here right and yeah I was sort of as a
as a precursor or as a teaser for the
advanced class in the advanced class in
the spring the disk goes goes away we
assume everything's in memory for
reading writing data and that allows you
do a bunch of optimizations that we
can't actually do here right so you can
sort of take this as a classical
database system architecture well though
it's you know the most widely deployed
implementation that that's around and we
can make it more run faster in some
cases if we assume everything's in
memory for our purposes here we assume
there's a disk and we'll see how we
actually deal with that so to better
understand now what we've talked about
so far in the last lecture and how it's
going to fit into the subsequent
lectures that we go through I want to
sort of begin present this sort of
high-level diagram of what a database
meta system is going to look like and
you'll see how all the various pieces
fit together so I said last class we
talked about the database storage right
we assumed that it was going to be one
or more files on disk writes equal
lights a single file other systems will
break it up into different multiple
files sometimes it's like one file per
table one file per database all right
for our purposes it doesn't matter and
then we said that the way the database
type system was going to organize data
inside of these this file is in pages
right and we said there had to be sort
this this sort of special page it's
called the page directory that
essentially is a map to say if you want
page 1 2 3 here's the offset or here's
the file to go get the thing that you
want right so this this is what we see
when you know the database is at rest
it's just on disk right there's the you
can't actually operate on we've got to
bring everything in memory so now when
we start want to start operating on this
as I said you have to find the page you
want and copy it into memory and so
we'll discuss this in the next class
but the thing that we're gonna end up
building to manage this movement and
memory back and forth is called the
buffer pool now remember I said that we
could let the OS do this and use virtual
memory with with the with em map of the
memory map files but we said that for
our performance reasons and that we
don't actually want to do this actually
for correctness reasons as well we want
to manage everything ourselves so this
is what we're not end up having to build
this buffer pool thing so when you first
turned the database system on there's
nothing in the buffer pool right we had
these sort of empty frames or these
slots where pages could be but there's
no data actually in it yet that's not
actually true when you boot the system
they usually preload a bunch of stuff
but again for the simplistic diagram
here there's nothing in there so then we
come along now with this execution
engine this is the thing that's gonna
execute queries execute transactions and
read and write data I'm drawing this as
a cloud right to shut it trying to be
nebulous just to say that we don't
actually care at this point what this
actually is
we'll cover this later on but assume
that there's something up here that has
a sequel query and once they're reading
read and write data so the way it's
going to interact with sort of the
storage layer that we're building in
this first part of the semester is to go
to the buffer pool and say I want a page
that at this particular pick with this
particular page ID how it got it whether
you know it read an index or somehow
magically poured it out out of the air
it doesn't matter right this is the
interface that's gonna interact with the
the buffer pool so now the buffer pool
managers are gonna go down and say well
I need to figure out where this page
actually is so let me go get the page
directory page because I know where that
is because it's a sort of a special page
and it has to know where it is in order
to bootstrap anything and it goes and
copy the directory page into memory
right now it takes up a slot or frame
and our buffer pool and now we can go
and say we want page number two well
here is where it is let me go copy that
into memory and and and you know put it
into another free slot so then we get
back now a pointer to this page to the
execution engine and the sort of the
guarantee is at any time that its
operating on that page it will be pinned
in memory again we'll see how this works
in the next class right cuz obviously
would be bad if I try to start reading
data and the purple manager all
so then swaps out the page I was reading
while I was reading it and I would have
problems right and then there's some
additional logic up in the execution
engine that knows how to then interpret
whatever the layout is of that page to
do whatever it is that needed to do
remember we talked about the different
page layout schemes we'd have a log
structured one which is a pending law of
records you could have a slotted page we
have actual tuples and the slots to
point to where they are inside the page
right from our point of view here down
below in this storage layer we don't
actually care what the layout is we just
were told hey get us page two and we'll
go hand it off to something else in the
system who then knows how to interpret
it okay so now it's sort of map this to
the schedule for the semester
we've already covered pages in the last
class and we'll cover a little bit more
today all right so that's lecture three
and for the buffer pool manager stuff
will be covered on Wednesday's class
right because there's a lot of stuff
that's going on here that I'm yeah be
super high-level about right how do you
have to copy things in how do you make
sure that things don't get swapped out
how do you decide what the swap out
right we'll cover all that next class
and that'll be the first project you
guys implement then we'll just talk in
section lecture six how do we actually
represent in memory the page directory
with hash tables and then we'll cover
how do you have to interpret the bytes
in lecture ten and actually a bunch of
the other lectures that do query
processing okay
this make more sense now right we're at
words we're starting with files on disk
right we then copy them into memory and
then there's some layout to the to the
files and some layout to the pages that
other parts of the system know how to
deal with again we're going up the
layers of the database minute system
ideally it'd be nice if sort of a clean
abstraction from one layer to the next
but we'll see in a second that it's not
always the case cuz how how you're gonna
decide actually how you layout pages or
the data in pages will affect how you
build your execution engine all right so
it's not a clean abstraction in some
ways but at a high level it's it's it's
good enough okay I say this is sort of a
road map for us for the next level weeks
question now okay
all right so now today's class we're
gonna pick up where we left off last
class where we we were talking about the
the files we talked about the the the
the page directory we talked about the
the the page layout and then we talked
about how you actually layout tuples
inside those pages so now the first
thing I'm gonna talk about is how do you
actually represent into individual
values for tuples inside of a page and
then we'll talk about the system
catalogs at a high level which is the
internal metadata the database system is
going to maintain to figure out how to
actually you know what data is actually
being stored and how to actually
interpret the bytes that are inside of
tuples and then we'll finish off talking
about storage models which is a way to
think about how to then take data in
tables and then map them to pages or how
you actually organize the values in
pages which is sort of higher level
concept that goes beyond all the things
we talked about here so far okay okay so
as I said last class the tuples from the
data assistance perspective there's
nothing magical about them right it's
just a sequence of bytes and the
database minute system knows how to
interpret those bytes to then derive
structure on and and and extract values
from them right I can just open up you
know char array and see and write a
bunch of crap but then the database
system will know how to then take
different offsets in that byte array and
say well this is an integer I know how
to represent do whatever operations or
manipulations I want to do assuming that
it's 32 bits but the the CPU and the
operating system it doesn't see that it
doesn't know about the schema it just
sees a bunch of byte arrays and so we'll
see this in the catalog the catalogs
again is the metadata we're gonna use to
figure out what the actual values
actually mean in that in that byte array
so here we want to talk about the again
how do we actually represent basic types
in this byte array so there's sort of
four broad categories of types inside of
a database system will cover
user-defined types or complex types
later in the semester but at high level
when you think about it there's
essentially four things you could be
right you can have integer types and the
different types even you'd be you can
define determine how many bits you want
to use to store data all right seeking
of integer which is 32 bits 4 bytes big
in 64 bits small in 16 and tiny int is
is a single single byte or 8 bits right
and so for this we're gonna represent
this data just using the built in sort
of C or C++ representation of the data
right if I open up a seat you know make
it C program and I say int and declare
an integer right the internally the CPU
knows how to represent that those bits
to mean an integer and we're just gonna
leverage the same thing in inside of our
database system there's certain nothing
magical there again in C and C++
you have uncie you know 32-bit integer
64-bit integers all those map to to this
the sequel types where things get tricky
is when you want to start having
decimals or floating-point numbers and
there's this trade-off between having
what are called floating-point numbers
that are using the built in Hardware
primitives and then there's the fixed
point decimals where we're going to
manage that ourselves inside our
database system to ensure that we have
you know accurate calculations accurate
numbers so as a quick show of hands who
here has ever heard of the I Triple E
754 standard a few I actually a lot of
you awesome yeah all right so the 784
standard defines how Hardware should
actually represent data or these serves
for these floating-point numbers and it
tells you what should happen when you
when you manipulate them right and we'll
see in a second if they're if you're
having sort of a variable precision
numbers
you're not gonna guarantee accuracy in
your cab calculations but they can be
much faster because you can do this in
hardware whereas if you want a you want
to guarantee accuracy using fixed point
decimals we have to manage this
ourselves in our database system and we
course we pay a performance penalty to
do that then we can have variable length
values so varchar' VAR binary and blob
right varchars just is you know it's
like a string and it can be any
arbitrary length you could have a char
field
which is just always gonna be the same
size with padded with zeros or spaces at
the end and a varchar' typically what
happens is you you put the header in the
header the size of the value and that
tells you how how many bits to go into
your values complete right and we do
that instead of having an Ultraman in
there but I can see because we need to
know exactly where to jump to from one
value to the next and then you can have
timestamps and dates and times right
very often these are usually represented
as just the number of seconds since the
UNIX epoch I actually don't know what
Windows or sequel server does in Windows
for this and we saw I think a few
lectures ago how you know the various
systems to represent these things in
different ways and they have different
properties and different accuracy just
because everyone does different things
for this right the standard says one
thing but every one every one slightly
deviates so I want to spend more of our
time talking about the varible precision
numbers because again this is a good
example where you know we could this let
the OS or certainly hardware do this
Vivi's manage these data types for us
but if we do it ourselves we can get
better accuracy but we're gonna pay a
performance penalty for it so for baro
precision numbers as I said these are
represented by the 754 standard and
these would be float floats reals or
doubles sometimes real and double or
just map to the same thing they're
synonyms float would be a 32-bit
floating-point number and real and
double is a sickie little bit reown
double right the again the problem with
these native types is that they can't
actually accurately represent decimals
or floating-point numbers right because
it's just the the hardware can actually
can't handle this
so to give it a really simple example
say we have a little C program like this
and we want to take two 32-bit floats x
and y make one B zero point one and one
and one B zero point two if I just you
know add these two numbers together and
print it out I get widely different
numbers versus just outputting zero
point three right we as humans know that
one zero point one plus zero point two
should equal zero point three but in
both cases either just printing 0,3 or
adding those two numbers again
you get wildly different numbers this is
because the harbor can't actually
accurately represent these
floating-point numbers so this would be
really fast to do but if you have your
if your database is maintaining things
like money or measurements from
scientific instruments right this would
be problematic because now you can have
weird rounding errors which would be
inaccurate so the way to solve this is
to use fixed point precision numbers
alright so these are typically you have
a called numeric or decimal and so the
idea here is that we're going to store
some extra data in for the type in line
in the tuple that's going to tell us all
the things we need to know to actually
represent one of these decimals and in
some cases some systems like Oracle as
far as I know you can declare that you
want a float or even an integer but it's
always going to end up getting mapped
back to one of these sort of managed
values because they want to guarantee
that your accuracy in your calculations
again you pay performance penalty but
for a lot of cases this is okay and so
we'll see in a second how we actually
can represent this but at a high level
the way to think about it is you're
basically gonna store the the actual
number almost like a string and then
you're have some extra metadata but you
store in line with the tuple that'll
tell you you know where the decimal
point should be you know what is the
scope and things like that all right so
I'm gonna do a quick quick example in
Postgres give you show you sort of how
how expensive what the performance
differences between these different two
different types alright so let me do
this
remove that my secret to the bottom all
right so what I'm gonna do is well this
is post rest ten so I'm gonna turn off
they have a new parallel query execution
engine I'm turning that off just to see
that it'll make the performance
difference much greater so I'm gonna
create two tables one of real values so
that the the floating-point numbers
right and one of decimals right the
built in this sort of a custom Postgres
datatype that's doing fixed point
precision numbers and then what I've
done is I've ran a simple Python script
that generated a a simple CSV that has
ten million
numbers two columns with ten ten million
ten million rows of two random decimal
values and then I can load this into my
two tables in the CSV file by using the
copy command alright because a copy
basically is a command you can tell the
Davis system hey go local on your local
file system get this file and it's a CSV
file or whatever it's it's whatever file
and there's a departs parse it and load
it into the in the table right so now if
I do select star from test decimals just
to show you what it looks like right
baby two numbers like this right again
we have one table starting them as
decimal it's a fixed point precision one
table storing them as a floating point
position so now what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna add together every single every
single for every single row I'm going to
add together the the first column with
the second column and computer
aggregation computer some for that so
I'm putting two keywords in front of
this query if you've never seen this
before
explain is a command that tells the
database system to return back the query
plan that the optimized are generated
and we'll discuss what query plans look
like later in the semester but you
essentially get something like this
right it's a tree that says do a
symmetric an on the table and then
computer and aggregation and you can see
what will cover this later on but it
shows you things like here's the number
of rows I think I'm gonna read and
here's how long it's gonna take me right
but if I add if I add analyze in front
of it
this tells to be hit to actually run the
query explained just does just spits out
the query plant doesn't actually run the
query he had analyzed it actually runs
the query and show you shows you the
query plan right so for this I run out
like that get a run for a bit and then
tells me what execution time is one
point four seconds right so it planned
for for a fraction of a millisecond and
then it ran for 1,400 milliseconds so
that's the one with real so that's using
the floating-point precision so now
let's use the fixed point precision same
query same data different table
representation and now it took 2800
right took twice as long right and just
to show you that it doesn't matter if
it's cash I can run the same query again
shouldn't be turn on timing right I got
a little bit faster but if I keep
running it again over and over again it
should roughly be the same right because
now everything's in memory and it's just
reading as fast as it can and doing
these calculations same thing for the
reals
right and so what all right so what now
the next thing to point out is we notice
at the when we've run out of decimals we
get something starts two nine nine nine
eight but then we run it with the reals
we get one point zero 1 4 and then
scientific notation so we can actually
see what that value is either so we can
cast it as a decimal
right so with with the decimals at the
top we got nine and eight with reals we
got 101 or one zero zero one right so
same data technically the same
calculation two different data type
representations we're getting two
different results so let's see let's try
to figure out what the actual correct
value is so we can run a really simple
python script so i'm gonna import the
load it loading the same data set that I
load it into Postgres and and just you
know add the two numbers together
casting the values as float and then we
can print out what the total is 9 9 9 8
so in this case here python is doing
something to make sure that it has
accurate calculations just like Postgres
is right so that would tell you the
correct value is what what we're getting
at the top here what you can you you
can't see me high like that right so
again we we use the built in primitive
types of the hardware and and and c++
then we're getting much better
performance but we're gonna have
inaccurate calculations because of
rounding errors if we want if we care
about these things then we then we want
to use fixed point precision or fix
point decimals but are going to be much
slower okay okay so let's understand
what's actually going on how this
process is actually implementing this so
this is actually from the real Postgres
code this is the internal type
representation that they define to
represent a decimal or numeric right so
you can see what I was saying before
where at the bottom we're gonna have a
string sorry the bottom here in numeric
digit this is essentially the most like
at the varchar' of the of the actual
string representation of the the of the
value and then there's all this extra
stuff we're storing to say what the
weight is the scale factor whether it's
positive negative or not a number
right the where the the you know where
the decimal point is things like that so
what what we could have stored as a
32-bit integer is now storing this as
what 4 8 16 20 and then whatever the
arbitrary saying is so went from 4 bytes
to you know possibly 30 or more just
store the same value and then when we
actually look at the code now see how
you they actually add two of these
decimals or numerix together right it's
way more complicated then then just
taking two numbers and adding together
which is a single instruction on the CPU
right you again this is from the real
Postgres code I think it's nine six or
nine five right this is just the add
function right just to add to these
numbers together that there's all these
cases you're checking to see whether
it's negative or not a number right and
then at the very end you end up just
actually being just you know adding to
these two numbers together so again in
my example for this is all the code
we're running when I was using decimals
just to add the two numbers together and
then in the obviously the same kind of
calculations for you know for
multiplication subtraction and other
aggregations as well okay again so the
main takeaway is you want to use fixed
point precision when you care about
accuracy anything with financial data
anything with scientific data if you
don't care about these things then using
the floating-point numbers or is the way
to go and you sort of start to see this
the same kind of ideas in in in machine
learning right instead of using 32-bit
floats for all your weights and your
neural networks maybe you drop down to
sixteen sixteen bits and that's that's
you still give good results cuz accuracy
doesn't actually matter in that
environment that much alright so now we
want to talk about how we actually store
so we know how to store integers we know
how to store a dates we're usually in
just integers and decimals and and
varchars
for this we're all assuming that we all
of these things can just fit in our in
our slot at pages where our tuple lives
right typically most database systems
don't let you have a the size of a tuple
exceed a single-page right but that
would be problematic when you have
really large values like a var binary or
blog because they can often be larger
than than a single page so to handle
this we would use what's usually called
overflow storage pages so basically a
place where you can store large values
that aren't no longer going to be in
line with the tuple itself right so in
this case here inside of our tuple say I
have this attribute C it's a var binary
and it's more than than the size of a
single page instead of actually storing
the value inside my page with my two
pool I'll just have a pointer page ID
and an offset to a overflow storage page
that tells me where my actual value is
all right so in Postgres they do this if
the value trying to store is larger than
two kilobytes and my sequel they do this
if the value trying to store is larger
than half size the page there's actually
we're not I'm to cover this but is
actually a bunch of other optimizations
you can do for these overflow storage
pages that you can't actually do in the
regular tuple pages right so in the case
of Postgres and we've had this thing
called toast I figure what it stands for
but that's where they store these large
values they can actually compress these
pages on disk because you know for these
things it's not like you're trying to
insert update things all the time right
I write a tuple I write a large value
I'm usually not going back and updating
that large value over and over again
because that's actually not what a
database system would be good for
there's also a way to do well covering
this when we talk about logging but all
the protections you would have for your
regular data that fits in the regular
tubule pages you have to have for these
overflow pages as well because because
in from the outside point of view from
from the application standpoint you
don't know whether your app your tuples
stored across two pages you just know if
you crash you come back you want to make
sure everything's still there so in some
cases you actually don't want to store
large files entirely in your database
because it's expensive to do instead you
have what's called an internal value
storage and it almost looks exactly the
same as as the
large value storage in the last slide
the difference is that the pointer from
the attribute for the regular tuple is
not going to another page managed by the
dating system it literally is just a
file path to somewhere on that's
accessible to the database system where
the data is actually being stored
alright so think of this say I have a
photo application right and my database
is storing photo information instead of
storing the really large photo files
inside of my database I can just have
them strewn across a directory and then
inside my data system it just has a
pointer to to where that file is that it
wants to store right so from the query
execution standpoint these external
files are essentially gonna be treated
the same thing as a bar binary or blob
right the upper levels of the system
don't know that you read this data from
the file system right does it need to
know just knows that if you need to read
it here you know internally I know how
to jump to that file and then and stream
it in stream the bytes in then hand it
off to whatever what other part of the
system it actually needs it so in Oracle
they have a special type called B file
in Microsoft they have a file type
called file stream I spent some time
looking at other major systems and as
far as I can tell they they they all
sort of have something similar to these
but these are the two main ones that I
that I can I know about so now the thing
to point out though is unlike in the
last slide with the overflow
values the database systems not be able
to protect or do anything with these
external files other than just reading
it okay so in the case of Oracle they
don't let you actually manipulate or
dude updates to these these files but
has to be managed all outside of the
database system right and then we'll
also see the case and that means you
also don't get protect transaction
protections meaning if I try to
manipulate this thing inside the
database system and I in some concept of
transaction and I crash and I come back
Davis is not gonna know how to replay
the log to recreate the the changes that
you made right these are Sitter
considered external so you see this a
lot of times where we're database
systems are really
are really expensive and storage is
expensive and you can store these
external files on like a distributed
file system or ass and that's external
to the data system that's actually much
cheaper to do right a lot of times you
see this and like you know if you if
you're paying per gigabyte on your
database system some vendors actually
charge this way instead of storing all
your large files in the database you
just have it point to the these external
files and then you don't pay extra to
store them right again inside the tuple
we're just storing now the file path
question yes her question is for the
overflow page will there's always be a
fixed sized page sorry is the overflow
page is each overflow place gonna be the
same size yes so typically in a database
system there wasn't clear from last
class if my if I say my page size is is
8 kilobytes every page is a key light
regardless whether it's a logging page
regardless of whether it's a one of the
overflow pages they're always gonna be
the same size and the reason is because
when we saw that buffer pool manager I
had those slots where I wanted to put my
pages in I don't want to have variable
length slots now some systems I think
db2 you maybe it'll tune this to change
the page size / buffer pool but in
general it's always gonna be the same
size so now the next question might be
asking is if if my database system has 4
kilobyte pages and the value I want to
store is larger than 4 kilobytes so what
do I do
we just have now a pointer inside of
this thing to say I can only store 4
kilobytes but here's the point into the
next page where you can continue reading
these things right and now we get into
so what are the optimizations you can do
to make streaming this data in very
efficient well if I know I'm gonna store
a 1 megabyte value in one of these
verbling fields I want to be allocate a
bunch of for kalaiy pages all
contiguously on disk so that you know
yes there's a pointer to go to the next
one but it's you know it's it's not I
know I can jump ahead and read
everything ahead of time without having
to jump around to different locations
right I wish I had numbers for this but
there was a
there is a paper from it from a few
years ago actually 10 years ago now
where basically they try to figure out
at Microsoft what was the right cut off
point of making decision and when to
store things as large values inside the
database and when to store things in
external storage and I think the number
they came up with it was like really
small like 256 kilobytes that seems too
small when they had the sequel like guy
come here here a few years ago they were
actually they did experiments they were
showing that it's better off to store
like in like phone apps he were storing
like 1 megabyte thumbnails you were
actually better off storing the
thumbnails inside the database system
because it was super fast to read these
files to write you know from from disk
because you already had the file handle
open right so there's no there's no
conventional ways from a hard fast rule
to say when you store things like this
so when you store things in an external
file different people say different
things I would say the from it from a
management standpoint if you stored
inside the database if I do a dump now
of the database everything's always
there if I have these external files I
maybe copy the data from one machine to
another I got to make sure I copied the
database plus the files make sure the
file paths are all point correctly right
so there's different trade-offs for each
of these from a performance standpoint
you know don't store one gigabyte files
in a database you can some systems will
let you do this I think Tara data was
like gee do there's like 2 terabytes for
a single value don't do that
ok so see your question these pages are
always being the same size and then for
external files it's whatever the
operating system or the file system
actually uses right we don't care we
just know how to stream things alright
so as I said in beginning the tuples are
just byte strings or byte arrays there's
no meaning to them other than what the
database system you know in parts on it
from interpreting those bytes and the
way it's going to be able to do this is
through its system catalogs so the
system catalog is the internal metadata
about the data right tells you what
tables you have what comes they have
what types they are what their names are
what the ordering is everything about
indexes and views alright we need all
this for for query planning because we
didn't
whether you know if you do a read on a
table does that table actually exist and
we need to know when we actually read
tuples inside that table how to actually
find the data that we need interpret it
correctly so in general almost every
single database minute system
essentially stores the catalog
in its own database format so it stores
information about tables inside of
tables and we'll see it in a second it
actually makes it really easy they can
then find information about these tables
because there's there's sort of a
standard location or standard view if
you want to call it that where you can
see all this metadata but internally
what's gonna happen to the data systems
gonna know when they call create table
and define four fields right and these
fields have these different types so
when I read a tuple I know what those
those types are all right so the the
ANSI standard I think is in the single
standard now says that the everyday
there's no system has gonna have
catalogs you won't expose this through
the user through what's called the
information schema catalog information
schema view right again this is
basically all the information about
tables and columns and everything that
the theaters could use internally this
is just a way to get to it as you're as
in your application code so as well see
in a second although there is a standard
way to get this information or every
single database system that I'm aware of
has their own little shortcuts to to
make it easier to do this because you
know writing queries against information
schema can is kind of cumbersome in law
so let's say that you want to real
simple get the all the tables inside
your database the sequel standards say
that you do select star from a from
information schema dot table and then
you pass along table catalog is the name
of the database but in Postgres of my
sequel and sequel light they have their
own idioms to get this information real
quickly right /d four-post grass or /d
plus gives you more information
show tables for my sequel and dot tables
in sequel Lite so say now we want to get
all of the tables were started all to be
all the tables in the student database
in Postgres you use /d student my sequel
with describe student and dot schema
student in sickle life so again the main
takeaway I don't
is that when we call create table we
stir all this information in our
catalogs that is then propagated to the
execution engine part that was it sort
of in the cloud that I was showing my
diagram that says all right you're
reading this page is from this table
here and here's here's how to find the
offset for an attribute they may be
looking for right so we'll cover I think
if you have try to cover more about this
in the in the later in the semester
but I find catalogs are actually very
interesting because they vary widely in
implementation and the this is something
that actually the research doesn't
really cover because it's not sexy right
like writing a catalogue with the da
system you need to have it but there's
no nobody actually doesn't really well
my sequel you should actually just store
files on and on disk and that was the
way that you could figure out what more
tables you actually have actually we can
give a little demo of that we want to
see that all right so this is Postgres
at the top I'm at the Kinect again
alright so as I said I can do select
star from information schema that tables
and you get a bunch of stuff right so I
can do where table catalog equals Pablo
right and this tells me all the internal
tables that I have right these anything
with PG underscores is an internal thing
that Postgres sets up for you I can also
do like this your /t and it shows me all
of the tables that have /gx sx then it
shows you what the schema is there we go
alright so my sequel the same thing I
can use select star from
information schema top tables well it's
a bunch of stuff it's hard to see I said
so in case here they're showing every
possible thing every possible table
that's in type of entire system right
alright so there are shortcuts to show
tables right or show databases here I
want to do a database as a hat right so
the this is post this is my sequel 5,7
post goes my sequel 8 they've actually
fixed this and they actually now store
all the stars could tell all the catalog
information in tables themselves in this
earlier version they would actually
store this in they would actually store
this in in the file system so if I go to
VAR live my sequel right I see a bunch I
see a bunch of directories here and and
it matches up with what tables or
databases that have so it says I have a
dangerous caught information schema our
performance schema and there's a there's
a directory up above or it says you know
performing schema that I have a data is
called test insist
and there's directories called system
test so what my segal basically does is
when you say show me the Davises you
have it looks in this directory and any
directory it sees it assumes that it's
the database right so we can fake it out
by saying let's make a directory called
xxx and down below and I show show do it
show up call show databases and voila
xxx alright
I'll see what happens if I try to ask
what's inside of it or use it let me use
it
nothing's in there so let's go see in
here there's nothing there's no files in
there let's see what happens I call it
table
I don't know what's gonna happen here
yeah didn't like it cuz there's nothing
there
anyway so so show databases xxx is there
come back here we'll delete X X X X X
it's gone
alright so the main takeaway here is
gonna say post curse does a much better
job most data systems do a much better
job of actually storing all the
catalogue information that we use to
understand what the data looks like
inside of tables themselves my sequel
got better in this in version 8 there's
a bunch of weird stuff though that they
don't do correctly which we'll talk
about when we do transactions where
although it looks like a regular table
and you would think what had the same
transaction semantics the regular data
has in some cases it actually doesn't
write because these catalogs are sort of
special cased in the system and they
don't they don't always get it right
again I am extremely interested in
catalogs I just find it really
fascinating just sort of a you know my
stupid thing okay
so now I want to talk about storage
models and I think this is a really
important concept and in some ways like
this is probably one of the things that
you were a design decision you have to
consider when you go out in the real
world and you and you say maybe you're
not building a database system from
scratch but you need to pick one all
right the thing we're talk about here it
actually can make a big difference right
so remember that there in the relational
model that there's nothing about it that
said the defined how we actually had to
store the the tuples inside of our data
inside of our pages right and that means
that what I mean by that is in all my
examples so far when I said let's store
tuple I showed like this array with
these attributes contiguous to each
other
right and when the middle see what think
about a database and think about like a
row or a two point of data is they
always start to think about like that
you have one attribute after after
another but again the relational model
doesn't say anything about this because
a relational model is a is a high-level
logical concept which means we can store
it anything you know sort of data in any
physical way that you want as long as we
expose it to the user as you know as you
know tuple has these these values these
attributes so the reason why this
matters because storing it the way we
took that so far storing everything as
rows with Katti keys batteries may
actually not be the right thing for some
workloads so to understand this bit
better I'm going to use this sample
schema it's actually derived from the
real application the real software that
runs Wikipedia right you can download
this thing called MediaWiki it's written
in PHP uses my sequel if you look at
their DDL files you'll see something
that roughly looks like this we've I've
modified it slightly to make it more
simple so when have two tables we have
user account pages and revisions
revisions have a foreign key reference
to the user account table and the pages
table and then the pages table has a
foreign key reference to the revisions
table so users have accounts users make
pages or you just have accounts there
are pages like articles on Wikipedia and
those pages can have revisions right and
there's religions are created by users
that's the basic schema so the two
classes of workloads that we're going
talk about our OLTP and Ola ap or OLAP
so LLC OLTP stands for online
transaction processing right think of
this as the applicant application where
you have people interacting with a
website and you're you're making you
know filling out forms and submitting
things and you're recording new data
right so think of like in like on
Wikipedia I can go and create an account
right
I go felt the form and click Submit then
the data system takes that data and
stores it as a new record inside the
database alright so and these workloads
the the queries can actually going to be
usually pretty simple right they're not
talking about you know very complex
joins very complex aggregations
because because your your the queries
gonna be operating on a single entity at
a time in the database again
think of like going to Amazon I have my
Amazon account I can add things to my
cart I can make purchases I can I can I
can make payments I'm the the actions
I'm doing only affect my account right
so the transactions the queries that are
executing um based on my invocations of
the the website only touch my data from
you know my entity so this is typically
what people usually build first like if
you're gonna be a start-up and you say
I'm gonna build something that you know
wants to do machine learning analytics
you need to get data first this is how
you're simply collecting that data or
you set up a website people use it and
then you know installs new data in the
database so in the case of our Wikipedia
example the queries that would fall
under this category would be simple
things like click get all the revisions
for a page by doing a join update my
user account by saying the last time I
walked in with the current time and then
inserting new things into revisions
right and these are simple operations
doing that only touching a small amount
of data and operating on a single entity
now contrast this with OLAP or online
analytical processing these are more
complex queries that will be reading
large segments of the database or tables
that go across multiple entities so
again using Amazon an example under LTP
I make purchases I buy items right I'm
only operating on my account under OLAP
I'm doing calculations like you know
compute the the the five most bought
items over a one-month period for these
these these geographical regions right
now I'm reading large sections of data
to compute some kind of aggregation I'm
deriving new data from the data I've
collected from the OTP side alright so
you typically do this after you've built
the OTP side and you collected your data
and now you want to infer some meaning
or derive new knowledge from it so in
the case of our Wikipedia example the
sample o that like query that I'm
showing here is that we're going to a
sequential scan over every single user
account record look at the hostname the
C's well see whether they ends with the
dot-gov
donate no name domain name suffix and
then compute the number of times they
logged in for each month all right is
that
real query you can do you can see you
know you can see which government
employees are going on to Wikipedia and
modifying things a few years ago there's
much of Congressman where they have
their and their assistants go modify the
Wikipedia page to make a more flattering
writing so this query could could find
people like this why is this sort of
clear the LTP is for transactions and
updating new data and just in new data
in you're modifying the database the
OLAP is more analytical queries so a
high level diagram it's sort of a really
simplistic view of what the differences
are would look something like this and
this is from article written by Mike
Stormbreaker from a few years ago so
long the y-axis we have the operation
complexity how complex of the queries
and then on the x axis is its whether
the workload is you more rights or some
more reads so in the bottom corner you
have OLTP where you're doing simple
operations that write data and then in
the top corner you have complex
operations and OLAP queries that are
that are typically read-only now social
networking is sort of this weird thing
in the middle because it's a mixture of
both
right you're updating your your timeline
you're making posts on Twitter but
they're still doing calculations to
figure out you know who you should be
friends with and things like that but
for now our purposes we just focus on
all it to be an OLAP so now the storage
model is we're going to talk about is
the way we're going to represent tuples
across our pages and how we want to deal
for OTP is actually gonna be different
how we're going to do it for OLAP and as
I said so far we've assumed about tuples
are stored as contiguous rows and the
mathematical term for this is called NRI
storage storage model so the an airy
storage model is where you store all the
values for the attributes contiguously
inside of a single page now again you
can have the overflow pages or the
external files for our purposes that
doesn't actually matter at this point
it's just if I have a tuple I have five
attributes I'm gonna have some location
inside of a page where I have my header
for that tuple and then I'm gonna have
all those five attributes in line with
each other right and so this is ideal
for o2b workloads because as I said most
of the queries operate on a single
entity so and you typically you're going
to try to read all
the attributes for that single entity so
if I want to get my account information
right I want to do a select star query
wit from account where username equals
no Andy I want all my attributes so when
things are in things are in mind this is
ideal because it's one fetch to go get
the page we need and then one read to
get you know across again everything we
need right so it looked like this so say
that we have a page with four tuples
right we can divide it up where the the
the first of all starts followed by the
second tuple and third tuple right
there's no data for the first tuple
intermix with the second tuple only when
it ends does does the the second start
and this is the architecture of the
slotted page design that we saw before
so now I can represent this in a single
page that's stored in my database with a
bunch of other pages so say these are
all the pages for this user account
table right for every single page
they'll have all the values for just one
entity so if I gonna need to go get that
entity or get the data for that single
entity it's one fetch to go get it let's
see how we'd actually write queries on
this so let's say we didn't want to do a
select star from user account where
username equals something and patent
user password equals something right so
there's some index we're going to use to
say to map a user account to the actual
tuple ID or page ID and offset that we
want for our purposes we don't care
about what the index looks like at this
point you can just think of it as a hash
table or tree we'll cover this in
lecture seven but this is gonna tell us
for this query for this user account
here's the one page you need to go get
get and then we know how to jump to the
offset inside that page to jump to the
starting point and then it's readable
data right across right it's really
simple if you want to do an insert well
that's easy too again we just find a
free page using our page directory and
then we just jump to inside inside of
that page we dump some offset and we
write all the data one after another
right in this case it's really simple
cuz it's sort of we assume we have a
byte buffer of the byte array sorry we
have a bite buffer of the values we want
to insert from the insert statement and
we just write them continuously with a
single write operation or mem copy into
our page right so again for all the TP
this works out great
for OLAP though not so much let's take
that query we had before we want to do
the scan across the user account table
and trying to find all the records with
someone logged in with the the gov
hostname so for this
it's a sequential scan there's no index
is going to help us because we want to
look at every single user account record
so that means we have to touch every
single page we're gonna look at every
single page so let's say that we go grab
the first page we fetch it bring it into
memory write what are we gonna do well
we will next do this query basically we
want to just look at our where clause
and figure out what what attributes do
we actually want to read we care about
the host name so that's stored here so
what's going to happen is we're gonna
fetch this page in and then we're gonna
scan through and jump to the offset as
defined by our catalog to where the host
name is and then check to see whether
that matches the query or the the
predicate and our where clause and if it
does match what do we need next well we
need the login right because we want to
do the group line it's the same thing as
we're going long as we check the host
name if it matches then we want to go
also then read the last login to then
build out our hash table or if we're
doing sorting aggregation to fill out
some intermediate heap or byte array to
say here's the values we're actually
back to pass our predicate and we can
use them for the aggregation later one
so what's the problem with this what's
the problem for this query but I've
talked about so far what data did itdid
I have to read for this query I only
access two attributes right last login
and hostname yes exactly I only need two
columns but I had this huge chunk here
that I had to fetch in because they're
stored together with the tuple all right
it's unavoidable so even though my query
doesn't need this it comes along for the
ride when I go fetch the page so this is
all now uses data so for you can sort of
think about as the the the data that I
actually I need to read it to actually
process this query I produced the result
I also have to read other useless data
just because they're they're tucked in
the page with them right and that's the
problem with the the row storage of the
NSM storage model for for its peak
queries so what the advantages are that
it's really fast for inserts updating
deletes because all the data that I need
is gonna be right there I can just do
whatever I need to it without having to
go fetch other pages and it's good for
queries are doing select star because
again everything's always there but as I
said it's bad for doing OLAP queries
that typically only scan a portion of
the total number of columns and have to
look at the entire table so this is the
alternative is called the decomposition
storage model or more closely known as
column stores so column storage and the
idea here is that instead of storing for
a single tuple all its attributes and
then go to the next tuple strong strong
its attributes we're gonna take a single
attribute or column and store all the
values continuously for all the tuples
for that single attribute together in
our pages so then what happens is when
we have to go then read that data and
our query we only end up going to read
the data we actually need we don't read
stuff that we don't need so to go back
to our example before again this is when
we were storing as a row store or the
NSM if we break up now all the
attributes in two columns and now store
them all within a single page right sort
of think of the row stores like this the
column store is storing things like that
so I'll take the I'll take the host name
column and I'll make a page it only has
the host name so this is the host name
for the first two bullet and then host
name for the second tuple and so forth
all my single page and I'm not going to
mix up data from other attributes if I
have space right we say this page only
stores data for this column and so I'll
do this I'll have you know different
pages for for all the attributes so now
if we go back to our query that we have
problems with in the row store now to
execute the the scan with the where
clause on hostname all I need to do is
actually really only get these two pages
right the first page will have the host
name and I've is ripped through this
really quickly and just check to see
what chuckles actually match and then
for the ones that do match then I can go
back to the hostname I started the the
the last login page and just go get the
values I need right in the case of the
row store
I didn't know what two poles actually
match until I actually looked at the
hostname so you end up reading not only
that the columns you know only actually
need you end up reading the the last log
and attribute for some people as you may
not need either as well in this case
here I'm only need to get the data that
I actually need that satisfy the first
predicate so is this clear right and
then you can do this sort of same
architecture as the slot is designed
that we talked about before it's just
now the slots are pointing to where you
can put the next value in so what's the
sort of big problem with this then yes
right so he says he won't do a select
star you got to go bunch of pages and
stitch things back together
you go over verse two if I went to an
update or an insert I gotta take it
split it back apart and write up read
this all out absolutely yes anything
else so I said here right as I'm as I'm
ripping through my host name some of
these will match some of these won't
match now I need to go back to the last
login page and find out find the tuples
that that that correspond the ones that
matched yes exactly
so your question is and then what I was
alluding to is how do you reconstruct
the tuple absolutely right so there's
two ways to do this the first you can
use all sets the other one you can use
the bedded IDs
so with all sets the way it works is
that you assume the attributes are all
fixed length right you know say column
is an integer they're always gonna be 32
bit or 32 bit integers so now what'll
happen to say if I'm if I'm ripping
through the host name field assuming
it's fixed length and they say v tuple
matches now when I want to go get its
corresponding attributes from values for
the last login column I just know how to
jump to the to the fifth one right when
you have variable length fields this
gets tricky you either have to pad them
out so they're always the max size of
what they'd actually could ever be or
you can use diction
encoding where you destroy things as
fixed-point fixed with integers and then
you have a mapping table to map those
integers to the original values alright
different systems do different things so
you can use offsets the alternative
which I think this shows up in some of
the literature but I don't think anybody
actually does this is to actually embed
the values of the tuples or the tuple ID
inside the every single value inside the
column itself right so for 2 plus 0 and
column a I've to store it and same
fourth same as for all the all the other
columns I don't think I'm actually does
this because you still need an index to
say if I want you know offset 5 or 2 yd
5 how to jump into that as far as I know
all the column stores actually use the
offset approach alright alright so the
the advantages of the DSM is that for
OLAP queries we only uh know how many
read the data that we actually need and
this is to make things be much much
faster we'll see this later on when we
talk about query processing there are
some additional optimizations we can do
where if we know that we're just
operating on on on all sets the columns
maybe we don't actually retrieve the
data until the very last moment we
actually need it right we just
manipulate these offsets as far as we
can up the query plan and then only go
back and get the data when we as you
have to finally show an answer to a
human the for compression there's some
optimizations we can do because we now
we know all the values are going to be
sorted in the same domain so we can do
want more more sophisticated encoding
schemes beyond to sort of you know gzip
or dictionary compression so for example
if I know that I'm throwing a sex field
and to say that's just either male or
female it's only be either one or two
values so now maybe I can run length
encoding or other ways to compress that
down further and then the disadvantage
is what he pointed out was now anytime I
want to do an insert or I do a select
star I had to break everything apart
across the columns to store things or
put it back together to produce our
final result all right now there are
some optimizations we can talk about
later on of how to make inserts and
updates really fast by sort of having a
roast or in front of a column store and
this is the general approach that most
people use but if you have a sort of
pure columnstore you would have to split
up each time alright so any high-level
questions about this yes alright so his
question is how do you support native
how do databases that need to support
both types of workloads actually do this
that's a whole nother lecture actually
we could do so the there's a couple
different ways one is that you said we
have two storage engines or two two
executions inside the same database
system so mem sequel does this mem
sequel you can declare you have a row
store and then you can also declare you
have a column store in that in their
case as far as I know in that system you
have them you can't sort of
automatically migrate data from one to
the next you have to sort of dump out
the data from the row store and then
reinsert it into the column store now
there's some systems that try to be
clever and underneath the covers do that
migration transparently we're originally
doing this for our system at CMU we end
up banning it because it was too much
engineering overhead the other approach
is to actually have a you basically
maintain a Arena link copy of the
database in a column store format this
is called fracturing mirrors this is
what Oracle does so I insert everything
as my row store and then in the
background I'll make a I'll make a copy
of it as a column store and any
analytical query that could use it is
then redirected to that thing all right
so there's a bunch of approaches leave
the most of this way to think about is
do you have a little mini roast or that
you just append changes to and then
every so often there's a background
process that merges it into the column
store but that case you have to be
careful about making sure that like you
know if images a read in one side you
know if they're reading something that
hasn't made it to the column store yet
that you don't miss it because it's an
it's in the the deltal store so this
question is do you always use twice
twice amount of storage if you're doing
the fraction mirror approach if you're
making the copy you have to yes it's not
always gonna be exactly - twice as much
because again on a column store you can
compress it much better
roast or but in general if you're not
compressing then in that case yes if
we're doing the Delta store know the
Delta stores usually much smaller and
then you migrate things to the column
store where it exists permanently
I mean I'll check the schedule maybe we
should talk about this a bit more too as
later on alright so comm stores are hot
now open which every newer database
system that's doing analytics that's
been developed in the last eight or ten
years is a column store but the core
idea is not new it actually goes back to
the 1970s so there's a early system
called cantor from the Swedish military
and this would never released publicly
there's only like one or two papers that
describe it they're in English and they
don't really describe it as being a
database system because back then you
know that that term wasn't wasn't you
know wasn't common as it is now and they
were mostly manipulating files but they
talk about these files being as a calm
oriented format then the 1990s there was
sort of the first academic paper that
describes what the decomposition storage
model looks like from a theoretical
standpoint but it was until the 1990s
when somebody actually actually
implemented what we now understand to be
a column store a DSM system so sybase IQ
was a in-memory query accelerator it's a
sort of big example I said before where
you have your roast or your doing
updates and then you could use sybase IQ
to make a in-memory columnar
representation or copy of the database
to make those queries go faster sybase
IQ actually still exists Sybase was
bought was a database start up in the
1980s got bought by sa p and the as far
as you know that the system is still
peoples to actually still use this in
the 2000s when the concerts really took
off there was a big movement a bunch of
newer systems that were built from
scratch not to be quit accelerators or
copies of the database actually to be
the primary storage location in the
database Vertica is probably most famous
one in full disclosure Vertica was was a
startup founded by my two advisers
before i started grad school got bought
by HP and then they got sold off again
to a holding company actually Vertica
has an office here in Pittsburgh and
there
if you wanna go talk to them
dr. wise and monie to be our two systems
that came out of Europe but in the two
thousand is when people should recognize
that for if you're doing any little
queries column stores are the way to go
and part of the reason why bees took off
in the 2000s because this is when the
internet was sort of starting to take
off and now a lot of people had a lot of
data right back in the 1980s 1990s only
really a small number like the fortune
ten companies have big data sets right
maybe some the big banks some of the big
retailers but now you know you can go
whip out a you know a Twitter app pretty
easily I start collecting a lot of data
so people are hitting these problems
with existing systems and this one comm
stores really took off then as I said
now in the 2010s
like if anybody is building a new
analytical database system and it's not
a column store it's it's a non-starter
right cuz users not gonna get the same
performance benefits you can get using
the DSM storage model versus the row
store and then this is just sort of a
smattering of a bunch of of a bunch of
column store databases that or that that
I'm aware of there's way more than this
but that just I quickly put up a bunch
of them okay all right any questions
about this column starts are hot you'll
see this all the time but it's good to
understand what's actually going on okay
so the main takeaway at this point
before we start moving now into memory
so the memory side of the database
system is that the storage manager
ideally would be independent to the rest
of the system but in actuality in some
ways it's not always the case
right because we'll help expose some
information about you know what the
layout is or how we're actually storing
these pages to the upper level parts of
the system that we can then use for
optimizing our queries or doing other
more sophisticated operations on the
data other than is treating as you know
black box on the file system and then as
I said choosing the right storage model
for your database system is really
important at the very beginning because
you want to make sure that you can get
all the optimizations are targeted right
sort of workload based on what you think
you need to do and so what I mean by
this is that it's
be very difficult to take a row storage
system and then build that out and then
come back okay I want to be calm store
it's not just you know just changing the
actual the to how you storing tuples in
the pages there's a whole bunch of other
see later on that if you that is
predicated on knowing whether you're a
pro store versus a column store so some
people try to do this with Postgres
right there's there's some people that
have extensions for Postgres to actually
store data as as a column store inside a
row store but the actual execution
engine itself is still a row oriented
storage engine whereas something like
Vertica which was based on Postgres they
actually ripped out all the execution
engine stuff and the store stuff and
built it from the ground up to be
explicitly a column store and you get
much much better performance all right
so it's sort of goes beyond just the
storage model stop but the main takeaway
here is again you have to know this
ahead of time because there's a bunch of
design decisions we're gonna make later
on
that'll be predicated on this you know
on this decision okay all right so next
class as I said in for data storage
there's these two parts right we've
covered the first one now we know how
the David says was gonna represent files
on disk
alright the actual data itself and now
we want start talking about how do we
actually bring this into memory in our
buffer pool and move data back and forth
okay any questions hi guys enjoy the
rain and I'll see you on Wednesday
yes it's the SD cricket IDE pests I make
them less unless I can do it like a Geo
are you with the G to the e to the T
comes dope I play the game with no rules
homies on the truck so yah was because I
drink bro
put the bus a cap on the road on the
with a party by the 12-pack case of a
bar six-pack for the act against the
Real ID replete with your drinking
proper 12 ow they say bill makes your
flat out what's a nice is straight so it
really don't matter