[Music]
they'd be on the jill's Nick okay this
Thursday we have another speaker coming
for our seminar series on hardware
accelerator databases this would be Todd
Moe stack from map D he's the CEO and
co-founder so again this is another
database system that uses cheap used to
accelerate the execution of queries so
we're not quite there yet in discussing
how we execute queries but sort of we've
talked a little bit about doing some
actual scans these systems are
essentially doing super parallel special
scans on data that's been put inside of
the GPU and they can run that own
parallel really fast of course the
downside as we know we've been talking
about this already about how to move
data back and forth between the disk and
to our buffer pool in memory these guys
have another problem they gotta move the
data from memory up on the CPU down to
memory in the GPU right so these talks
are describing how they actually want to
manage that so administrative things is
that reminder the homework started
project one is due Wednesday September
26 that's next week
at midnight homework 2 will go out later
today after class originally was due the
same day as project 1 but I bump that to
be the Friday on the 28th but I just
sort of give you some extra time ok
again everything's everything's on great
scope so any questions so far about
project 1 and no couple you have some
technical questions on on Piazza we'll
sort of those things out yes yes
yes if you feel the first one it doesn't
do the after meeting yes okay okay did
you post on Piazza about this a person
pee outside will fix it okay any like
non-technical like the greater the
greater thing doesn't work right so to
high-level questions I'm a fist
confident they can filter my buffer pool
manager right okay the last thing I also
want to bring up is just a reminder what
I said at the beginning the semester I
really want you guys to stop me as we go
along if you have questions about the
material as as I'm speaking right now
but I don't want is for people to come
up with the front and ask me questions
about there's something on slide 20 that
occurred 30 minutes ago right this
serves two purposes one if you have
questions about material then somebody
else probably does too so it's better
just to stop me and make sure I clarify
or speak more clearly about what it is
that you're confused about but also it
serves a you know as sort of a way to
make this material better for the next
year because I can always go back and
watch the video and see what you know
the students ask this question this part
wasn't clear and actually try to make
the slides better so that you know the
thing you were confused about can be
described in a better way the next time
around okay so it means again if you
come up at the end of the smell at end
of the class and ask questions about the
some of it something that's not about
like the homeworks or something you know
beyond the course material I will not
answer the question right I'm not trying
to be an asshole just like just I want
you guys to stop me because it's not you
know I just want to speak here for hour
and a half and just go through all the
slides if you have questions stop me and
we can we can go over things more detail
okay again there's no stupid question
the only stupid question there is is is
this a stupid question
right so you can ask me anything I don't
care
all right so where we're at now again
just to ground ourselves understanding
where we're going along in the semester
is now we're started talking about after
we know how to organize our data from on
disk and memory now we're going up
further up the stack and talking about
how we're actually going to have queries
execute execute in our system and read
and write data so for today's lecture
we're sort of talking about how we
support them to internally maintaining
metadata among other things but sort of
broadly you can think of like we're at
this point here called access methods
Naxos methods are the you know sort of
mislike
self-describing they're the methods or
the mechanisms inside our data system
that's gonna allow queries or threads to
access data and the the data structures
we'll be talking about for the next two
weeks can be grouped in sort of two
categories we'll have the hash tables
that we talked about today and then
we'll have the order preserving trees
that we'll talk about on on Wednesday
this week and then Monday next week so
to understand where these data structure
is going to be used and how they're
gonna help us xq queries we refer to our
what are some cases where can we
actually use them inside of our air
system so as as I first already said we
can use these to maintain the internal
metadata of the database system and you
guys are already doing this for your
buffer pool right you have to build a
hash table for the page table to map
page IDs to frames in the buffer pool
right that's what I mean by internal
metadata it can also be used for the
core data storage of the system so we
can use either hash table or an order
preserving tree to actually organize the
underlying pages or tuples inside of our
pages so the easiest way to think about
this for a hash table right I'll there's
some no sequel systems that are key
value stores or these are just hatchet
with that map keys to to values in the
case of order preserving trees like B
plus trees but we'll see some systems
like my sequel actually organize all
that the pages and the tables themselves
inside of the trees right it's not just
sort of like a service of separate
auxiliary data structure
the the next thing we can use them for
is temporary data structures during
query execution so that means as we're
executing our query we can actually
build a hash table on the fly based on
the query the data were reading for our
query do whatever it is that we need to
do using that hash table and then blow
it away throw it away immediately when
the query is done right and this
actually turns out to be much faster
than just having to scruncho scans over
and over again right well see this case
and hash joins but you can Pete
aggregations this way right the group by
clause you can think of that just again
using a hash table to group the you know
they differ different categories or
clusters together and the last one it's
probably what most people think about
when they think about hash tables and
and and or preserving trees is using
them for for table indexes and the the
main takeaway I want to get from this is
that there's certain trade-offs as we go
along that we'll talk about where
sometimes the design decisions for
certain hash tables or certain order
preserving trees will be good for table
indexes but may be bad for internal data
structures right may the mitten the way
we maybe design our hash table to do our
page table is not the same way we want
to do a hash table to do joins because
again they have different trade-offs in
terms of performance for the amount of
memory they have to maintain so again
we'll see this as we go along throughout
the semester but this is what we're an
ability talking about this week or the
building blocks we want to use to solve
all these problems and then we can build
on top of this and do more complicated
things so the two major design decisions
we're going to have in in just when
discussing our data structures are the
data organization and the concurrency
methods so data relation is essentially
just how we're gonna lay out the the
physical bits of the data we're trying
to store in our data structure in in
either memory in the heap or in pages on
disk so that we can support efficient
access to that the data that we want
right and it's getting it's it's how
we're gonna at the data plus the usual
metadata we may have to store inside of
our data structure to figure out what
what what we need the second part is how
to allow
multiple threads to safely access and
modify our data structures at runtime so
for this discussion for this week and
for Monday next week we're actually
going to for the most part assume that
we're only going to have a single thread
accessing our data structure but
obviously in a modern system we can have
multiple cores and multiple threads
running so you're gonna want to have you
know multiple threats access your data
structure at the same time and now you
need to protect its contents both at a
logical level and a physical level to
make sure that one thread doesn't write
something that another thread is reading
and get and it gets corrupted data so by
logical versus physical what I would
mean is the physical data structure
would be again the underlying bits that
are stored inside of the data structure
and we don't want to modify something
that calls us to have an out a pointer
to an invalid memory location all right
that's what people normally think about
when they think about allowing willful
threads to access a data structure and
we can protect you know we can protect
the data structure using latches the
logical contents of protecting the
logical contents of the data structure
has to do with things like what queries
are actually seeing while they're
running while other queries are running
at the same time so this is a more
complicated nuanced topic we'll cover
much later on when we talk about
transactions the way to sort of think
about this is a simple example would be
say I had my query delete an entry in my
in my data structure my hash table if I
go back and check to see whether that
key is still there it better not come
back and say it's it's still there right
physically could still be there because
maybe the data structure is going to
remove it later on with a garbage
collection process but the the the bits
are still there but logically we don't
see it so there's a whole bunch of other
mechanisms we're gonna need to protect
these data structures to make sure this
occurs and we'll cover this actually on
Wednesday next week and let's see this
more in detail when we talk about
transactions and control so our purpose
here for this discussion is really going
to focus on the first one here and we're
the first design decision and we're just
going to assume that we have a single
thread accessing our our data structure
it makes things much much easier so our
focus today is on hash tables so the at
a high level a hash table
it's gonna provide you with a
associative array interface that is
gonna map keys to values right for some
arbitrary key we want to map it to a
value if you're familiar with Python
it's the dick data structure the
dictionary data structure same thing if
you've written Java it's the Java hash
map class and the same idea keys to
values so the sort of chord concept of
how this is all going to work is that
we're going to have a hash function that
we can use to compute some location or
offset in a in dissociative array that
will that can point us to the value that
we're looking for for our given key so
the the absolute easiest way to
implement a hash hash table is what is
called a static hash table so think of
this is just a giant array of slots and
for this we're going to assume that the
values we want to store in our and our
hash table are fixed length so we know
that the the offset at every location we
know how to jump to it based on you know
whether we want the tenth item or the
hundred item we know how to do that
rithmetic to jump to that memory
location so what will happen is that
we'll just have some hash function and
it'll for the given key we want to look
up the simple hash function could just
take the key and the bits and modify the
number of elements that we have so we
just order these different slots from 0
to n assuming that we have and n keys
that we want to store and then now we
want to store something again we just
hash the key and then we can dump the
value inside of there right
super simple this is the easiest hash
table you could actually build what are
some obvious problems with this what
assumptions did I make no collisions but
why would it be no collisions
first of all what is a collision right
he said the same key hashes the same the
same officer in AI array so why am i
assuming that there's no collisions
because I'm assuming I know exactly the
number of keys I want to store n right
and I just take every key and just mod
by n it's gonna put me in the same
location right it's sort of real simple
case they're here the other big
assumption is that my values are fixed
length so I know how to jump exactly to
the location that I want so that's not a
big deal right to handle arbitrary
length keys all we have to do is sort of
have this sort of separate storage
location over here and now our giant
array doesn't actually contain values it
contains pointers to some other memory
location or some other page location
that has the values that we want right
so again we the problems with this
approach is that we assume that we know
the exact number keys that we had ahead
of time we also assumed that all the
keys would be unique which in many cases
it's not going to be and at this point
we don't have any way to handle that and
also assume that we had what is called a
perfect hash function so a perfect hash
function is a theoretical function that
given two keys that don't actually are
not equal to each other the the hash
generally about our perfect hash
function will not be equal either right
you sort of think of this there's like
if hey my domain of every single
possible key I could ever have I can
have a unique hash output or hash value
for every single key again these exist
in literature in theory you can just
build this with an additional hash table
or additional giant giant you know
slotted array map but in practice nobody
actually does this because this be very
expensive to maintain so the way one
handle do this is by approximating
so the two design decisions we're going
to have in our hashed hash table is what
hash function we want to use and what
hashing scheme we want to use and I
would say that the combination of these
two things is actually what defines a
hash table right when you say I have a
hash table implementation it's you have
to you have these two things so the hash
function the way think about this again
is we want to take a large key space of
every possible key b1 or store and we
want to map it to a smaller domain right
and the reason why I want to do this
because otherwise we have that store I
don't have a perfect hash function or
store you know a potential slot for
every single key you could ever see so
for this the big trade-off is when we
talk about how what hash function we
actually want to use is gonna be this
this trade-off between how fast our hash
function is and versus what our
collision rate is right because again
we're doing this running queries we're
doing this while we're you know trying
to access pages and our page table we
want our hash function to be really fast
cuz you don't want to have to maybe you
know do this huge traversal and long
lookup just to figure out where the key
is that we want in our hash table so you
want to be really fast but then we don't
want to have all our keys mapped to the
same location because as I'll see in a
second depending on your hashing scheme
this isn't required you to do
essentially a scruncho scan to find the
thing that you're looking for so what's
this what's the fastest hash function
you could ever possibly build what's the
dumbest fastest hash function yes
exactly always she said always return a
number I'll make it even easier always
return one so every single possible key
no matter you know what name you have in
the directory what email address it is
always returns one it's super fast
because it's just return one the problem
is collision rate is abysmal because
everybody's gonna map to one it's gonna
map to the same location in our in our
array so we want to be able to smarter
about this and that this is what we can
have different hash functions do for us
the next decision we have to make is the
hashing scheme and this is essentially
how we're going to handle collisions
which are gonna be unavoidable because
we don't have a perfect cache function
and we're not trying to store a giant
array they could handle every possible
slow
Franky's so you want to have a a hashing
scheme that describes exactly what
method our heuristic we're going to use
to handle collisions when they occur and
again for this the trade off is going to
be almost the classic computer science
trade-off where we're going to sacrifice
or give allow us to use less memory to
store a hash table in exchange for
having to execute more instructions to
deal with collisions when they occur and
again if I just had a I could build my
hash map that's two to the 64 possible
entries that possibly take all the
memory I have in my single machine I'll
never have a collision so the number
instructions I have to execute they deal
with collisions will be will be minimal
but I've allocated that all that memory
and now I can't do anything else not in
my machine right so again this is
classic trade-off that we want that we
want to handle one I do not want to get
better with Windows and do not want
update okay so for today we're going to
turn up talking about the different type
of hash functions you can possibly have
and this isn't you know this is not an
algorithms class this is not a
cryptography class so we don't really
care how it's actually implemented we're
more interested in the the properties
that they have and then we'll talk about
the two different types of hashing
schemes that you can have you can have
static hashing and dynamic hashing and
the extent just you know as a ground you
guys what we're talking about the
extendable hashing is an example of a
diamond dynamic hashing scheme okay okay
so for a hash function
can anybody give me an example of a hash
function area with the one that needed
used in you know at an internship or
further projects other than STD hash crc
yes that's a good one
sha-256 perfect example okay so CRC is
is a non cryptographic hash right you
can take some arbitrary byte stream and
it'll generate you a a you know a hash
function he said sha-256 sha-256 is a
cryptographic hash function we don't and
has certain
properties that it's not gonna leak data
either the more keys that you give it
right and it's very difficult to reverse
we don't care about security on the
inside of our system right the caveat
that for our eternal data structures
that the information is never gonna be
exposed to the outside world we don't
care about cybersecurity or don't care
about cryptography inside of this so
sha-256 is an overkill for what we want
first of all it's expensive it's you
know it's more expensive than crc32
which is a single instruction on on x86
CPUs and it actually can reverse it if
you have the public the public private
key you can take a shot to v6 and
reverse it right we don't care about
reversing it we just want to know what
what offset do we jump to in our you
know in in our and our and our table so
we don't want to use cryptographic hash
function we have something we want
something that's fast and something that
provides us with a local Asian rate so
crc32 is a good example and we'll see
some other ones from Google and some
other people that are pretty common so
the I should actually conclude crc32
next year I'll I'm opponent but the
these are some of the most common hash
functions that are used in real systems
today I will say the commercial guys and
Postgres and my sequel these are much
older systems so they have their own
custom hash function but most of the
data new data systems that I know about
that come out in last ten years or so
when I we talk to the developers they
tell us they're using one of these guys
here and these are all open source so
murmur hash came out in in 2008 it was
really put out with some random dude on
the internet posted on github or
something right and then people who sort
of picked it up and started using it it
is designed to be a fast general-purpose
hash function again these are one-way
hash functions where we gave him some
key it produces some output and in
theory if you saw enough of the keys a
key value pairs or keys to hashes you
could reverse it but we don't care about
that right we're not we're not worried
about leaking any information because
it's all internal so murmur hash again
was designed be this fresh beyond a
purpose hash function Google ended up
picking it up in and actually extending
the version two of member hash and they
design
to be better faster for shorter keys
keys are less than 64 bytes right and
they wanted to do this because in their
in their internal workload and their
services this is what the kind of data
they saw all the time and so they wanted
a hash function that was optimized for
these things and then Google standard
City hash in 2014 with farm hash and
this was further improved to have better
better better collision rates in 2016
they actually came out with another hash
function called Highway hash this is one
that actually does have some
cryptographic guarantees our protections
against analysis on the data again we
don't care about that so we're not gonna
use that for this and then the last one
here is steel hash so this was
interesting this one came out of Canada
from a professor up in Montreal named
Daniel Amir and this is actually using a
different kind of math called carry less
multiplication there's a link there for
the Wikipedia article you want to learn
more about it but it was interesting
about this is that the idea of carry
less multiplication is not new it's just
in 2014 or so Intel and AMD added
instructions to do this kind of math in
the hardware itself so now is actually
possible to do this arithmetic very very
fast so this hash function became an
actual a viable option so just to give
you an idea what these things sort of
look like in terms of performance so
this is this is an experiment I ran on
my workstation which is a newer one of
the newer Intel Core i7 CPUs so this is
written by somebody on github and I
sorta extended it to use Co hash so
basically what they're doing is they're
gonna hash a key a bunch of random
strings of different sizes as fast as
possible and measure what the throughput
rate is and so what you see is that when
the keys are kind of small the hash
function is all sort of more or less the
same but then as you increase the key
size and then though the y-axis is
throughput so it's how many how many
bytes of a key can you can you hash as
fast as possible so up to a certain
point they all sort of sort of plateau
and you can see the sed hash in there
the black line that you guys are using
for your for your for your project again
it's it's reasonably good but the two
psaltery pattern lines are from the the
city hash and farm hash from google and
as I said they designed it
be optimized for 64 64 bytes or less
than 64 bytes and then the the the
points where it sort of goes up and goes
back down these are where they're
aligned to cache lines so cache line is
when you do a fetch into memory you just
don't get like just the one thing you
want you get a whole bunch of stuff
along with it that are nearby because it
assumes your apply gonna need that too
and then you can start packing them into
64 byte cache lines so now if you can do
a bunch of operations or instructions on
data that's sitting in a single cache
line you never have to go back and fetch
more to maybe the upper levels of your
cache so that's why you see this like
when it gets to 32 bytes or 64 bytes
it's on you know you're getting much
better performance because it's it's
from one cache miss they're doing a more
work as for one cache miss you're doing
you're generating more output for the
same amount of read data read/write so
that's why there's the salty pattern and
there's to throw CL hash and this again
you see the same kind of the same kind
of ups and downs based on how you're
actually packing thing into registers
the main takeaway I want to give you
guys for this is like for things that
are less than 64 bytes you can use City
hash or farm hash for larger strings you
maybe want to use something else for our
project purposes we're not trying to run
as fast as possible
you know because we're running you know
running in secret lighter and great
scope so this SE d hash is good enough
so the main takeaway here is that
different hash functions have different
properties and you may want to choose
one versus another based on what you
think the distribution of the data it is
and what you're actually trying to do
with it
but the hash functions are as far as I
know interchangeable with all the
hashing schemes that we'll talk about
next so when we talk about these hashing
schemes it doesn't matter whether using
City hash or murmer hash the actual
algorithm will still work the same it's
the question is whether you're gonna
have a higher collision rate with one
function versus another again and that
can depend on the distribution of your
data okay so now we're gonna talk about
static hashing seems so
and the hashing scheme is the the
protocol or the method that be that the
hash table is going to use when there's
a collision and we said collisions are
essentially unavoidable because we're
trying to store a large key space into a
small smaller amount of memory so things
may end up hashing to the same the same
key so first talk about talk about
linear probing hashing Robinhood hashing
and cuckoo hashing so linear linear
probe hashing is the probably the most
common hash table not the one everyone
thinks up because when you think of a
hash table most people think of the
chain hash table we'll just see in a
second but in terms of implementation
inside of database systems this is the
one that's that's the most common
because it's just so simple and so fast
so the hash table is just gonna be this
giant table slots and you take the key
you want to insert you hash it and that
that puts you in some position into into
the hash table right and so what
happened is f2 keys hash to the same
slot in our table then the we just keep
scanning down into our table until we
find a position that is free and that's
where we can go put our item in there
pick the thing that we're trying to
insert right and this is why is called
linear probing because you again we're
just going literally almost as a
sequential scan and the table going down
till we find the thing that we're
looking for
so for lookups we have again we do our
hash Mikey we landed some space we scan
down till we find the thing that we're
looking for or we find an empty spot at
which point we know that we've you know
the thing we're looking for is not there
of course now what's the problem with
with this for this approach yes he says
he says yes he's correct he said that
when you do a deletion you now make an
empty spot which sort of disconnects the
to the two chunks of the things next to
each other yes absolutely
what's another problem say I'm doing an
insert the thing I want is not there and
I keep scanning
what if I never stop right what if I
reach the bottom loop back around
I keep scanning down and now I land back
in the original position I started that
I'm stuck in an infinite loop right so
we also need when we when we do insert
through SME and and searches when you
keep track of where we left off so that
we don't loop forever so let's look at
an example alright so say on the on the
side here ABCDE F these are the keys I
went to insert and again my hash table
is this this giant array of slots so I
want to say in first first thing I'm
gonna do is insert a so I take a I hash
it and it lands at this position here
right because nobody's there I can go
ahead and take take take the slot so
inside of the the entry in my hash table
I need to store the key that I that I
just inserted the original key as well
as the value right mean the value could
be could be like a record ID even a page
ID and an offset could be an actual
value right it doesn't matter but I VI
need to store both and the reason is
because when I come back and try to
insert something else or do another
lookup the hash function is gonna tell
me where to jump into the hash table but
then then I need to still do a
comparison as I'm scanning to see
whether the entry I'm looking at is the
actual key that I want because again two
keys may hash to the same location I
need to know whether you know the the
entry is actually the key the same key
is me alright so now let's say we hash
be that points up here nobody's in there
so that's fine so now we want a hash c.c
points to the same slot that a is in but
that's occupied so okay and the linear
probe map that just says go down to the
next one and that's where we put C so
now if I do a lookup and see when I hash
it I'll land where a is I do my
comparison with the key and a and the
key or key of C they're not equal keep
scanning down then I find my match on C
right I do this and so forth and so
forth D goes where C is that's occupies
who has to go to one below egos where a
is that's occupied so it has to go all
the way down to it
finds a slot that is taken and then last
one for app right so I'm going to a he
brought up a good point about deletions
here we're gonna punt and make this easy
and just not deal with deletions so for
a hat for certain operations this is
fine for a hash join or aggregations
this is fine because you're not gonna go
back and delete the entry as you're
doing your hash drawing so just I
realized you might not about hash join
is but the basic idea is I want to join
two tables I build a hash table for once
I put the keys in there and then on the
other of your other table I do a program
the hash table I'll see whether I have a
match right so the the hash table is
read-only same thing for aggregations I
never go back and delete something so in
that case this is fine and this is super
fast for deletions exactly as he said
you have to do some reshuffling and copy
things around to fill in the gaps and
that becomes expensive so this is
another example of a trade-off where
this is be great for some operations
work insert only and read heavy but if
you want to do updates and deletions you
don't want actually use this a linear
leaner proving hashing method the other
big issue that we have to talk about is
how we actually handle non unique keys
so for this I've assumed that all our
keys are are unique but that's not
always the case so there's two
approaches you can do to handle non
unique keys so the first is that you
just maintain the values of the for the
duplicate key in a sort of separate
linked list area so let's say that I
have my hash table I have keys X Y Z ABC
these instead of having the values
embedded inside the hash table itself
they just have pointer to some pages or
some memory location in the heap we're
now just a list of those values so now
what I'm going to say give me all the
values for X Y Z I do might do my hash I
jump to my location in my hash table
I may have to scan down depends on where
it actually is and then I when I find
the entry that I want now I have a
pointer to this other area and then I
know that the the the elements are the
values in that area only correspond to
the key that was pointing to it the
other approach is to just restore the
store that we've done it keys and the
values together so
set up breaking it up at XYZ ABC and
their value separately in my hash table
I just store XYZ and the values together
like that so what are some downsides of
the top approach is it more space
efficient no because you know I'm not
just me allocating single entries for
every value I'm gonna organize things
usually in pages and so if a single key
has one value I may be storing you know
have to allocate an entire page just
store that one value we're in the bottom
approach I don't have to do that because
I just add another entry into into my
hash table the downside of course again
the top one is more efficient when I
want to say give me all the key give me
all the values for a single key I just
jump to my one key then you know find my
key then jump to the value listen
everything's already there in the bottom
approach I just have to scan through so
there's another example of trade off in
databases where do we want to favor the
reads versus the rights right the top
one is is is more efficient for for for
reads but maybe less efficient for
writes because we have to allocate the
sector space the bottom one is super
efficient for for for writes because you
just plop our new thing and they're not
to allocate any space but Riis may be
more expensive because you have to scan
through to find it so that's how you
handle non unique keys for our purposes
going forward for all my examples and
these hash tables we'll just assume that
keys are unique but you but if you need
a hand or non unique keys you have to do
something either one of these two
methods and I say most people do do the
bottom one I actually don't know anybody
that does the top one okay so we said
that one of the big issues with the
linear probing hashing method I have two
hashing scheme is that we have all of
these wasteful comparisons potentially
when we have collisions right again when
you try to pick a really good hash
function to produce there are collisions
that we have but in real data set it's
gonna be unavoidable so the issue is
again when we have a collision we have
to scan through linearly and and start
looking at you know every entry define
the thing that we want worst case
scenario is that the
the key that we want is the the previous
key in our hand our hash table so we
land at one position and then have to
scan through the entire thing loop back
around then get to the very end and just
find the thing that we're looking for
and in that that case you know the the
the hash table is essentially useless to
us because we could have just done a
special scan on the data and try to find
that thing when we were looking for it
but now we're paying this this penalty
or this cost overhead I'm maintaining
this hash table and building it and
didn't actually help us in any way right
what should have been an o1 lookup is
now an own Oh n lookup in the worst case
scenario so again I said the way we can
try to avoid the number of collisions is
just by allocating more memory the
theory works out the math works out that
on practice if you want to reduce you
know the sort of the best or an average
reduction of collisions would be
allocating a hash table that's two times
the amount of of keys you actually want
to store but it's still not gonna help
our case where well yeah this reduces
the collisions and reduce the amount of
work we have but maybe there's other
approaches we could apply to actually
reduce the number of scans we have to do
or lookups we have to do to find the
keys that we're looking for so the two
approaches to do this are robin hood
hashing and cuckoo hashing so Robin Hood
hashing is a variant of the linear
probing scheme where instead of a when
we do an insert instead of just finding
the first free slot that comes after the
you know where we should be in the in
the in the hash table we will actually
allow new keys that are be inserted to
steal the slot of existing keys if they
are richer in quotes than we are right
so Robin Hood is the you know the the
folklore that the tale of medieval
England Robin Hood would steal from the
rich people and give it to the poor
people so the idea of our hash table
here is you want to have poor keys steal
from the rich keys and I'm defining rich
in terms of how many positions or jumps
they are from where where they actually
should be in their optimal position in
the hash table so when we do an insert
if we can't get to our position where we
want to be if as we start scanning
if we come across a key that is closer
to where they want to be in terms of
their optimum position to where we
should be then we'll we'll go ahead and
steal their slot and then move them down
to a worser position so let's go back to
our table we had before again keys who
owned an insert as ABCDEF and we said
that a when we hash it and gets inserted
here and now you can see in our hash
table in addition to the original key
and the value
I'm also going to store this this
position that says that getting the
number of jumps who are from our optimal
first position so in this case here when
we inserted a nobody else was in a slot
so a got to take it so a is position for
that it's this it's distance from its
optimal position is 0 because it's 0
jumps from where it should be because
this is exactly where it should be same
thing for B be hashed up here it's it's
it's it's a position counter is 0 so now
we want to insert C C wants to go over a
is so now we want to do a comparison to
say what's a optimal position counter
versus our optimal position counter now
at this point seed it hasn't gone
anywhere right we merely hashed at this
slot here so our position counter at 0 a
special counter is 0 so we leave a alone
and we just do what we did before in
linear probing the original version and
just jump down to the next one but now
you see that for cases see we made its
optimal position counter b1 because
we're one jump away from where we want
to be which is where a is so now we want
to do a do insert on D D goes where C
wants to be DS position counter is 0 C's
position counter is 1 1 is greater than
0 so DS not allowed to stoop from C and
D has skipped moved down here now you
see this this stealing thing actually
work when we try to insert e so e wants
to go where a is but they're both 0 at
that point so it doesn't steal from a
then we go down here to where C is
seized position is one E's position
counter is 1 so that it leaves C alone
but now we go to D so now E is
two hops away from where it wants to be
e D is one hop away 2 is greater than 1
so E is allowed to steal from eat eat e
is a lot of soot from D steals its lot
kills it and it moves it down to the
next position here and now DS counter is
2 right
same thing with F one more time F once
ago over D is 2 is greater than 0 so f
can't go there so f goes down to the
down below right so this is this is
again this is a what we're trying to do
here or what this is supposed to do
better than the linear probing hashing
scheme is that on average the the amount
of scanning you have to do to find the
key that you're looking for is is
reduced right sort of cuz right where
we're sort of shuffling things around to
minimize the number of hops any one key
could actually ever be so my exam all
before ever I said it was in the worst
case scenario would be the the key that
I'm looking for this is actually 1 above
where I hash to that can't occur under
this scheme because before you got there
things will get swapped around right
because there's likely to be one that's
actually worse than than you so this is
an old technique this is from like 1985
and it's one of those things were like
the paper came out in 1985 no one
actually read it
and then or paid paid attention to it in
sort of the system's community and then
the last 10 years it sort of showed up
on Hacker News a couple of times and
some systems were actually implementing
this the in practice what I'll say
though is that the the research shows
that this actually does not this is not
better than linear probing it seems like
it would be but it's not because on
modern CPUs all this sort of these
checking these these these counters and
movie things if necessary this is doing
additional branch misprediction which is
slower on superscalar architectures I
get the flush your your your pipeline
cache your pipeline and load everything
back in and it's also extra copying so
for a single insert I may have to copy
one things out and move it to the next
one I don't do that on our linear
because I just keep scanning to the
final thing that I want and the scanning
is actually cheap yes your question is
back here when we were inserting e your
question is at this point here when we
want to steal from from from D we're
saying that your question is is this
ensure that D is no nakri worse than e
or e Zachry worse than D yes correct so
his statement is in this case here when
we're stealing the idea of stealing is
that we're gonna make it so that the
victim the person were stealing from
it's no it's gonna be they have the same
number of steps but it's not gonna be
worse and we're defining worse and then
again the number of jumps you are from
where you should be so in this case here
II was to D got moved down and then D
was gonna be two as well so it's not
going to the scenario where D would be
three right actually it could be
actually cuz because if the one below
this was two then D would keep going
down but then at some point it would it
did find somebody could steal from so
there's no guarantee that actually
stealing would actually not make you
worse than the one you stole from you so
way to think about this in sort of human
metaphor would be I could steal from a
rich person take all their money and now
they're more poor than I am all right
that can happen under this yes wait so
the statement is that like in my example
here the total amount of steps is is
essentially still the same for everyone
right
the in this example here the my hash
table is tightly packed right in a real
hash table if you allocated enough size
large enough then the likelihood that
they'll be an empty slot so that you're
not sort of just keep cascading down and
and still ending up in even worse
position is unlikely it's not always the
case the other thing I'll say too is
like own average this makes the the
number of steps per key minimum exactly
right so this is trying to avoid the
worst case scenario where that I have to
scan through the entire thing that's all
the scheme does yes right so the same it
is and I agree with it is that this is a
trade-off between the guys are in the
optimal position potentially versus ones
that actually be you know really bad yes
absolutely right so again the literature
says that although this seems kind of
like you know a need nifty idea this
actually is worse than linear probing
because you're not gonna always getting
to get the huge benefit that that you
know you're minimizing everyone's number
jumps are steps you have to take and we
have to do more work in order to
reshuffle things so in our linear
probing I just scan through until I find
my my slot that's free and just put it
in there right under this I have to do
the you know the copying of the new one
in and the copy the old one out and
moving it down so that means cache
misses branch mispredictions on the CPU
and other other issues like that alright
good so another alternative to handling
these collisions is to do what's called
cuckoo hashing
so with cuckoo hashing the idea is that
we're going to maintain actually
multiple hash tables at the same time
and use multiple hash functions to hash
keys to the different hash tables and
the idea is that a key can only exist in
either I or one of the to one of the
hash tables right so for simplicity
would say there's just two but you could
have more than two and when we want to
do an insert we hash
the key twice find a free slot in either
one and pick that free slob but we want
to do a lookup again we hash our key and
we we check both both of the hash tables
now the issue is that how we're gonna
handle collisions we're gonna sort of
ping pong back and forth between the two
hash tables because if we have a
collision as we want to insert something
and that slot is taken we'll steal from
the whoever's in there now and then move
them to the next hash table all right
the idea here is again we don't it's
it's to to to minimize the number of the
amount of work we have to do to do a
lookup but we're going to pay a penalty
about having more extensive insertions
so let's eat an example like this so
this again for simplicity say we have
two hash functions in practice everyone
pretty much always does - I have some
heard of some people use three but no
one does more than three writes just the
overhead is unnecessary so let's say I
want to insert a again I'm gonna have
two hash functions one for each hash
table so when I when it comes along I
hash both of them and it's going to
point to these two locations here and at
this point both hash tables are empty so
I could go in either one position but so
I'll just flip a coin and tell me go to
into the first one now I want to hash
beat or insert B same thing I'll hash it
twice the first hash function points to
where a was inserted in the first hash
table and that's occupied so we don't
want to steal it because in the hash to
the second hash table it's an empty slot
so we'll always choose the empty slot
and put put B in there so now let's say
we want an insert C we hash that twice
it points to our a is and it points to
where B is in the two hash tables so now
we need to make a decision which one we
actually want to steal from and in in
practice it's just random right you can
be a bit more sophisticated and maybe
assume make maybe compute some metadata
about the collision rate on one hash
table versus another but as far as I
know nobody actually does it's just not
worth the engineering overhead so we'll
flip a coin and decide that we want to
steal from the second hash table so
we'll still beat beasts slot put in C
there and now when you take B and put it
in the other hash table so now we'll use
the first hash function
corresponds hash-table 1 we hashed that
but as we saw in the beginning it wanted
to go where a is now right member we
started be a hash tre is and turn an
empty slot in the second hash table so
we chose the empty slot now we want to
put be back on the other side now we
have that collision again because we're
never going back where a is so here
again we steal from a put be there hash
a put the second hash function and then
that puts us into the second side here
right so these two hash functions
essentially could be the same thing I
can be murmured hashed can be city hash
we just provide it with a different
random seed so that they have different
distribution properties but it doesn't
happen when I say different hash
function hash function one hash function
- it can be the same algorithm it can
just be a different seed value to give
it different randomness right and of
course what's the issue with this for
doing these insertions and moving things
back and forth infinite loop exactly
right so we have to maintain some
metadata to say where did we start off
when we first inserted so that if we
come back around we see the same key
trying to put it back in the same spot
we know we're stuck in an infinite loop
and at that point we have to rebuild the
entire hash table
so again typically we didn't tell about
rebuilding so much for the other two but
typically what you do is when you
recognize that my collision rate is too
high and I'm stuck in all these infinite
loops you double the size of the hash
table so you would do the same thing
here if my hash table is too big for
actually for both of them because it's
too small I have too many collisions
I'll get a new hash table doubled that's
double the size and take all the keys
that's another in the first one and put
it back into the second one alright and
you have to potentially lock the hash
table or put a latch on it while you do
this anybody from reading writing it
because you're just an she's rebuilding
the entire thing from scratch so the
math works out that with two hash tables
and two hash functions that you probably
won't have to rebuild the tree or sort
of rebuild the hash table until you're
out 50% full in the likelihood that
you're going to hit a key that'll get
stuck in an infinite loop won't really
happen to about 50% pool if you have
three hash functions or three hash
tables the math works out that you
probably need to rebuild it until you're
90% pool
of course now this means again you're
allocating a third hash table so you're
paying the penalty of extra memory for
having to execute fewer instructions so
cuckoo hashing shows up in a couple
different systems I know IBM db2 does
this for their memory accelerator this
one actually is pretty common the best
open-source implementation of the cuckoo
hash table is actually from CMU from
dave anderson so if you google like lib
cuckoo you'll find the CMU version of it
was written by Dave Anderson and his
students with Robin Hood hashing I only
know one system that does this when we
asked him why they do this they said
that the engineer sold on Hacker News
thought it was a good idea so they
implemented that but the literature
pretty much shows that for all these
approaches the linear probing is always
good always the best there's always me
the fastest so searching for hash joins
okay so these again these were static
hashing schemes right that means we knew
what the the number of keys you want to
store it ahead of time and she may be
asking water you know when is this occur
right when what actually when when when
is it possible I would actually know the
number keys that I have in your page
table you don't right cuz you the data's
can always keep growing you add new
pages so you don't know the number of
keys you need to store the actually
that's not true and we'll come back to
that but a stable a static because your
profitable size of static so it's always
a fixed number of pages
it's the directory that grows so again a
really common scenario is again for hash
joins so say I have a simple query here
I don't have two filters
I already filters on these tables so I
know I'm gonna read or do a join on
exactly the number of tuples that I have
in both of these two tables right so in
this case I know exactly the size of my
hash table because I know the number of
keys I need to examine so I can use the
linear probing I can use cuckoo hashing
or I can use the throttle approach right
if we get too big then we have to sort
of stop the world and read you know
double size and rebuild it right and
we'll see this later on when we start
doing estimations of the cardinality or
selectivity of predicates in our query
plan we get this
all the time and that's gonna make it
really expensive for us if we have to
resize our hash table in the case which
you guys are ready for the buffer pool
the in-memory page table is always going
to be fixed size because you you have a
fixed amount of memory but the page
directory can always be increasing in
size so you may not want to use one of
these these methods we've been talking
about because you may have to resize it
as you go along so this is where a
dynamic hash tables gonna help us so the
basic idea is that we're gonna be able
to grow our hash table incrementally
based on whether the number of entries
get you know goes up or down without
having to stop the world and rebuild
everything so it actually should be
three approaches we're gonna look at
chain hashing cinema hashing and linear
hashing alright so chain hashing is what
pretty much everyone thinks of when they
when you think of a hash table right
this is what you get when you when you
create a you know use the hash map class
in Java and the JDK this is the
underlying data structure that they use
so we're just gonna have a we'll have a
slot array that's going to maintain the
these pointers for every single key to
these the head of a linked list of
buckets I'm just going to store all the
values we have in these buckets and the
way we're going to handle collisions is
that we're just gonna scan along
linearly inside the bucket until we find
either the thing that we want if we're
trying to do a lookup or we find a free
slot that allows us to insert something
right so it looks like this again we
have our slot array that's gonna point
to these linked lists if there's nothing
then if nothing is hash to a particular
position in our slot array then would
you store null right there's no reason
to the point of allocate memory that we
don't need yet and then we have our
buckets and the buckets again they're
just going to be the same entries that
we had in the linear probing hashing
method where we have to store the key
and and the original key and the value
and let's say that we want to do an
insert into this this first bucket at
the top and it's - and it's full as we
follow along the linked list then we all
we have to do is just allocate a new
bucket and extend out our bucket chain
or linked list like that right
now we sort of see the same kind of
issues we have in linear probing if
everything hashes to the same bucket
then I'm since you're going to do a
squinter scan or linear scan across
every single element in the bucket list
to find the thing I'm looking for or
find a you know a free slot to put
something yet right so it's sort of
unavoidable of you if you have a lot of
collisions then you and you end up sort
of degenerating into a scrunch will scan
the right so these bucket lists can can
grow infinitely and that becomes
problematic in terms of how you actually
MIT implement us to be thread safe it's
actually really easy because you just
have to take a latch on the actual
bucket itself right you can easiest
thing to do is to take a latching entire
hash table or use take a latch on the
slot inside of the the slot array with
the pointers but even you mean more
fine-grain latching would be take just
latches on the individual pages and you
know nobody's going to modify as you're
scanning it so again the downside of
this approach is that these these
buckets grow infinitely and it's real
hard it's hard to shoot or shuffle
things around because I essentially we
had to rehash everything or just rebuild
the entire hash table so a more
incremental approach is what you guys
are building in your for your first
project is called extendable hashing
again these are there's an old ideas
from like 1982-83 but it's it's widely
used in a bunch of different systems the
it's basically an extension of the chain
hashing approach but instead of letting
the link list of the buckets grow
forever we're gonna we're gonna split
them and and move elements around and
the idea here is that rather than again
rebuilding everything from scratch we
want to do this incrementally so that
the impact of having to do a split is
not a large you know major stall in our
thread that's executing all right again
we building entire hash table is
expensive we have take a latch entire
thing no one can read and write from it
and I have to you know copy everything
one hash table and put it to another one
the idea of extendable hashing is that
we can do this a little bit little
cooperatively to sort of smooth out the
the access time across all threads
so let's look an example so we're gonna
have our slot array again these are just
me Big B pointers to our bucket list and
then what we're gonna have these
different counters that that's gonna
keep track of the the depth of number of
bits we have to look at to figure out
what bucket we should be going to so
we're gonna have the global death that
says the the maximum number of bits we
have to examine across all of our slots
and then for each bucket they're gonna
have a local death that says the number
of bits we need to that you need to get
get here or whatever we're actually
representing so for the local deaths we
don't actually need these to figure out
where we need to go the global death we
do we do need but the local deaths are
essentially metadata for us to keep
track of you know who's pointing can be
potentially pointing to us right so that
we can reverse this all right so the
first thing we see that now in our in
our in our slot array we have the values
that you have the output of our hash
hash function of the hash values and for
this purpose here the global death is
two so I only care about the first two
bits of the hash value so in my example
here I'm going from left to right I
think the text book goes left to right
some of the examples go right the left
it doesn't actually matter the algorithm
is still the same whether you go from
least significant or most significant
bit it's everything's still the same so
let's say I want to do a find on a so
the first thing I do is take the value a
the key a and I'm gonna hash it and I
could produce some some bit sequence
like that and then I look at my global
death and says I need to examine the
first two bits of the value of the hash
function to figure out where I need to
go to find the element that I'm looking
for or fine to find the bucket that I
want so in this case here I need to look
at the first two bits which is 0 1 so
that tells me I want that entry in the
in my slot array and it's gonna point to
the this bucket here at the top and then
I just do a special scan and that and I
find the thing that I'm looking for so
this is a good example of the difference
being the global death and the local
death the global death is to means I
always have to look at two bits but as
we see 0 0 and 0 1
Matt - the same bucket that has a local
depth of 1 so that means that to get to
get here the way what happened was I
only had to look at the first bit which
was zero and that's why they get back to
the same the same location here right
again global death you use for the look
up the local deaths to keep track of
what what you had to do to get there so
now I want to do ok and in certain on B
same thing I look at the global death
achill death is 2 so when I hash it I
just want to look at the first 2 bits of
the hash value that points me to 1 0
here and that points to the second
bucket and there was a free slot so I go
ahead and and add my entry right that's
fine
now let's say I wanna do another insert
on C and again global death is 2 I look
at the the first two bits that tells me
to look at here but now it's pointing to
the second bucket but there's no more
free slots so this bucket is full under
chain hashing I just have a new bucket
and extend out the linked list but
understandable hashing I'm actually
gonna split this and and and rehash it
so that some of the elements in the
bucket went to the to the new new bucket
and some almost stay in the old bucket
so what happened here just go back and
again right I'm gonna change the the
global depth of 3 extend out Mike my
hash array and for this bucket the
global death was now 3 and that's good
updated like that and so I'm gonna look
now at for all these elements on a look
at the first three bits and then I use
that to figure out my hash table where
they belong to so I should have maybe
drawn this and more more steps so back
here I say oh I need to split I'm too
big so now I look at my global death is
2 so my local death is 2 so that says
now I need to go to 3 and so now I'm
gonna look for each key in here I'm
gonna look at the first three bits and
when I extend out my slot array
that'll tell me whether I stay in the
original bucket or I go to the new one
with now the local death is 3 as well
and the globe
gets up to d23 because that's the
largest number of the local death we've
seen so far so now I haven't still
haven't started C yet right because I
just did my split because I couldn't
have sorted what I wanted so now when I
go and do insert and see now I look at
three bits and then that points me to
this bucket here and tells me where I
need to go I'm seeing blank faces is
this clear alright it's not found that
tricky right yes his question is when I
find a bucket do I still have to do a
spiritual scan to find a free slot net
yes right this is just some block of
memory and I know where my starting
point is and I said to scan to find the
slots of them but hey I know what my
boundary is of the bucket so if I go
beyond that then I need to split correct
so his statement is the local death is
just for extending it's not actually
used to find what you're looking for
right so once you're inside the bucket
you don't care the number of bits that
you use to get there you just actually
do the same checking that you would do
in all the other cases it's when you
split and say all right I version was
too
now I'm three so anything that's inside
of me now I need to figure out where
that actually needs to go and I could
stay in the bucket that I was originally
or can go into the new bucket I just
generated yes the statement is
essentially if they're still at the
rebuild everything rebuild everything
inside the bucket and the entire hash
table no so it's just this question is
do I start the rebuild everything in the
hash table
no the change is localized to just the
bucket back and that overflowed all
right so all of these like all these
other ones here this guy here and this
guy here the bottom they stayed the same
and actually now when I go and I'm
staying my slaughter right now I'm
looking at three bits I see that the the
first two guys they were still pointing
the first bucket they still do and then
now these guys over here are still now
pointing to this one as well again if
I'm just looking at bit
0:04 these two guys in the first bit
0:04 these cool guys first bit they're
all still still pointing to the same
bucket with a local depth of one yes
it's gotta collect yes yes yes yes you
are increasing the slides of the size of
the slot array like you have to double
the size of that but like that's not
that's not the big part the big part is
all this crap in here right because
again I'm storing keys and values if I
have to reshuffle this that's expensive
extending that is easy you you rebuild
actually means something very specific
and a hash table it means like literally
rebuilding a brand-new hash table this
is just a small change internally to the
the internal metadata which is cheap
right because I can all like okay these
are all gonna be 64-bit pointers and
it's gonna be some a small array right I
can create the new one copy everything
over and do compare and swap to put the
new one and install it in right that's
way cheaper than hashing and reshuffling
everything yes so this question is what
would happen if for for this first
bucket if I inserted maybe two more
things in it and it and it overflows
right so again the global the local
depth is 1 so I'll increase its local
depth of 2 so now for every single key I
have in here I'll look at the the first
two bits and that'll tell me where I
need to go so the the first else of the
first two bits will then get split up to
do separate buckets so everybody
everybody was pointing everybody the
starts at the zero points of this one
here right zero zero zero zero so now I
look at two bits so I'll have a bucket
for zero zero and a bucket for 0 1 0 0 0
1 so it'll be two new buckets the 0 0
guys will point to that one the 0 1 guys
will point to the other one and then I
look at the two bits
for all my keys and that tells me which
of the two I want to go into his
question is rights do I start to
maintain a pointer from the bucket back
to the global slot why now you know what
you get local death tells you who's
pointing to you because you know who's
pointing to you based on your local
depth right local death is one that
means that anybody that has right
anybody that has zero in the first bit
because I can look up what's inside of
me it has to be pointing to me right
it's cheap it's nothing yeah yes so his
question is are you asking in the real
world asking for the project his
question is do we have to shrink the
hash table in the real world yes and the
project now
we'll see in later hashing can with a
little time in linear hashing it's
actually really easy to do it's actually
not hard to do this either right you
just have to recognize that like oh well
if I go back from three my global depth
of three to two
well like can I collapse the everything
and not have to you know reshuffle
everything it's more expensive to go
deletion in this case then then
extending whether that's yeah go around
yes this question is if I have four
entries the same hash key what do you do
after you split like so so we were here
yes sir I think sirs question is say in
this case here I did I'm gonna either
split because I'm gonna insert C because
I wanna put four elements and then I I
can only start three let's say I split
this again and worst case scenario it
hashes again to the same thing I'll do
the same bucket which which then
overflows you have to split again if the
whole edge key is the same then it's
always be the same then that's the worst
case scenario that means you have a
terrible collision rate then you have to
keep extending extending this thing over
here until it doesn't this question do
you not need to cover this in the
project your your page table is not
gonna be that big right so again this is
you're storing the number of bits is
could be up to 64 bits the likelihood
that a page ID and your project will map
to to the same value from to 264 is
unlikely okay
all right the bunch of the questions I
want to finish up and talk about linear
hashing before we run out of time so
linear hashing I don't actually don't
know if it's in the textbook this is
another approach I think it's kind of
elegant again same thing it's from the
1980s but a lot of systems use this word
you again we're gonna do incremental
splits
we're going to instead of just splitting
the exact bucket that overflowed we're
actually gonna have a pointer that can
say what's the neck bucket we want to
split and so what will happen is every
time we do a split because some other
bucket overflowed we split whatever
we're pointing to and they move the
pointer down by one and keep going to
reach the bottom and then loop back
around and then split again alright so
this is this is even more incremental so
we'll define overflow in in for our
purposes here it's just when the when we
go from one bucket to two buckets but in
your actual implementation it can mean a
bunch of different things right it can
mean that the length of the chain has
gotten too long on average for the
entire system you have low space
utilization for some buckets and you
want to go in different directions it
doesn't matter but for our purposes we
just assume that we the we assume that
it's whatever um whenever you go from
one bucket a two bucket the thing we're
trying to solve here and I think some of
you guys brought this up in an external
hashing is instead while hashing every
single time I did a split I had to
double the size of the that directory of
a slot array in linear hashing we don't
have this problem we don't have to do
this group we're gonna do this one at a
time alright so say it again we have
four elements and we have four four four
four buckets that were pointing to so
the split pointer again is going to be a
sum page or some sorry sum bucket we're
gonna split whenever we overflow so for
this also as well it's gonna look a lot
like cuckoo hashing we're going to have
multiple hash functions but instead of
actually applying them at the same time
we only apply them one at a time and we
don't need to go look at additional hash
functions if the thing we hash to is
below our split pointer that'll make
more sense in a second but as we extend
the directory add more hash functions we
always start off with the first hash
function and we may not need to go look
at the other hash functions unless we
are above the split pointer all right so
let's say we're going to find on six
again simple hash function we're just
gonna modify the number of slots we have
so 6 mod mod 4 goes to 2 so we go find
our entry there right that just looks
like chained hash table no problem
now when doing insert in 1717 mod for
hashes to 1 so that goes here but again
we can only store three entries so we
have an O it we have to extend it by
adding a an additional bucket now this
triggers our overflow because we said
every time we make a new bucket that
counts as an overflow so now what will
happen is this whatever the split
pointer is pointing at
that's the bucket we're going to split
not the one we just we just overflowed
the extendable hashing was always the
one that overflowed its foot pointer and
later Hachem it's always the one that
we're pointing to so in this case here
the slip pointer is pointing to position
zero so we're gonna want to split this
one at the top so all we have to do is
add an additional location to our slot
or a lot directory and add a new hash
function that's going to be based on the
number of keys times but the key mod by
the the the double the number of keys we
have in our slot all right now
so we region have n elements now when
we're gonna do a mod would have mod 2n
but as we'll see in a second nobody
although we haven't allocated to n
entries over here in the slot array no
one's actually actually going to ever
get to there because you have to first
always look at the hash function and if
you the hash function if you hash here
and you're above the split pointer then
you look at the second one and we know
that we're never gonna hit anything but
anything beyond we've already allocated
so in this case here we add four and
then we split the first guy here so it
had 20 in it now 20 goes at the bottom
and we would move the split pointer down
by one so now let's say we won't do a
look-up on 20 so we always start off
with the first hash function right 20
mod 4 which is the number Ellis we have
initially equals 0 so that points to the
slot array here at the top but now we've
said that we know that 0 is above where
the split pointer is I sort of think of
this the slip pointers a threshold and
anything above that says I not after
I've hashed the first use the first hash
function I found my above with slip
pointer is then I have to use the second
hash function and then that will map me
down down below and then I can find the
entry that I'm looking for
right so every time I had there's an
overflow I do a split and I move the
slip corner down by one if I hash the
first hash function I'll and two above
the slip pointer then eyes you have to
use a second hash function at where I
really need to go and the math works out
that again you could never have anything
mapped to five six seven eight even
though you haven't allocated those
spaces yet okay because anything that
could get there would always land in the
below with a split pointer yes he says
what if you want to find thirteen so
simple I take the first hash function 13
mod 4 would tell me that it's 1 1 is
below the split pointer so I don't need
to look at the second hash function
so I'm apt right to the bucket and find
what I want if I want to look up on 8 8
mod mod 4 will be 0 I know I'm above my
my split pointer so I look at the second
hash function 8 mod 8 is 0 so there you
go it's right there yes this question
this is only work for integer keys no
because the hash function is gonna
return you back where to always return
you a integer like 32-bit or 64-bit
I'm just showing integer keys to keep it
really simple here yes it's always with
me the same hash function it's but
you're just a mod but by a different
number right so again hash functions
return a value from 0 to you know 2 to
the 64 we always mod it by the number of
slots we have to ground us where we need
to go right within within the number
Ellis we have at some point the split
point will reach the bottom at that
point we've extended it out to be double
the size of the number Alice we started
up originally so then we delete the
first hash hash key and reset the slip
pointer back at the top and start start
over again yes
he says if you want to is hurt 21 so 21
was 21 mod for one right so you hashed a
one you land here you you this would be
overflow and you insert into there oh
yeah so yeah for this in here that would
count actually yes this question is with
that count as a overflow getting depends
on how you implemented it if you say
it's only when you create a new bucket
then no it wouldn't overflow if you say
that it's whenever you your the thing
you're pointing at has an additional
bucket then yes you would count as an
overflow depends on the implementation
the math still works out correctly in
both cases though so his question is how
do we determine when to split a bucket
in linear hashing it's whenever I run
out of space so the very beginning right
I was here I want to insert 17 it hashes
to this bucket 1 the bucket are here's
three elements I can't put another
element in so I have to overflow it
right and I said globally I said
whenever a bucket overflows creates a
new bucket in the chain that triggers
the split pointer to split whatever its
pointing at so we ended up then at this
point here we split the first one
depends on that's implemented if you say
again you can say whenever I create a
new bucket split or if the flip hunter
is pointing at a bucket that's already
overflowed then I split so you could
have it say okay I'm in my sleep owner
down here this thing's already
overflowed so immediately go then split
split it and move it down again it
depends on the implementation no one way
is better than another and so we have
like two minutes left there's a quiz a
quick question order
let's go question so what pointer points
to 17 this this one does this it's like
a chain hashing it's an overflow it just
says I it's like if the thing you're
looking for is not in this bucket oh by
the way here's a pointer to the next
book you should go scan and you have to
scan the entire thing okay
I think we covered most of this the only
thing I'll say also - about linear
hashing what's really nice about it is
it's really easy to go in the other
direction right you could say all right
well whatever my bucket is as empty then
that's the same thing as a as as a
reverse and I just go then do a reverse
split on whatever the slip pointer is
pointing at from before and move it back
up right so you can do addition and a
retraction very easily much more easily
than you can and some of the other
schemes alright so just to finish up I
would say that all the data structures
we talked about here today ideally will
give you oh and lookups
the constant factors actually matter and
it depends on your collision rate you
end up may having to do a sequential
scan across all elements or all keys to
find the thing you're looking for right
but it again there's this trade-off
between having very fast look ups and
insertions with the flexibility of not
having to rebuild everything every time
you touch it so I don't have time to do
the demo I mean we can just keep going
and people have to leave but I give a
quick Postgres demo what I'll say is
again that this is hash table they're
probably usually not what you want to
use for table indexes because they can
only do single key lookups does
something equal something you can't do
range scans right you can't have partial
keys you have to have all the key
because otherwise not gonna hash you the
same thing and the way we can do better
is to having the the order preserving
indexes like in B plus tree okay any
questions okay next class we're going to
do B plus trees so some most of time of
that we'll spend a little bit time on
skip lists and radix trees or tries but
trees are really the the the granddaddy
of all the data structures okay SP
cricket I des I make a mess unless I can
do it like a Geo
are you put the G to the e to the T
comes do I play the game wears on the
truck so y'all move about the buck a
[Music]
party by the 12-pack case of a four six
pack 40 act against the real I treat
please put your drinking proper 12 ow
they say build nation flap but sane eyes
are straight so it really don't matter